<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:owl="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#" xmlns:wgs84_pos="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:rdaGr2="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:ebucore="http://www.ebu.ch/metadata/ontologies/ebucore/ebucore#" xmlns:doap="http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#" xmlns:odrl="http://www.w3.org/ns/odrl/2/" xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:svcs="http://rdfs.org/sioc/services#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:dqv="http://www.w3.org/ns/dqv#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><edm:WebResource rdf:about="https://digital.ucd.ie/view/ivrla:6962"><rdf:type rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/FullTextResource"/><ebucore:hasMimeType>text/html</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">47471</ebucore:fileByteSize></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="https://iiif.ucd.ie/loris/ivrla:6963/full/full/0/default.jpg"><dc:format>image/jpeg</dc:format><dcterms:extent>2368x1771 pixels</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent>9.75 x 13.25 (cm)</dcterms:extent><dcterms:extent xml:lang="en">1 still image : digital</dcterms:extent><ebucore:hasMimeType>image/jpeg</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">923509</ebucore:fileByteSize><ebucore:width rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">1771</ebucore:width><ebucore:height rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">2368</ebucore:height><edm:hasColorSpace>sRGB</edm:hasColorSpace><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#DCDCDC</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#FAF0E6</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#696969</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#2F4F4F</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#808080</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#000000</edm:componentColor><ebucore:orientation rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#string">portrait</ebucore:orientation><dcterms:isReferencedBy rdf:resource="https://data.ucd.ie/api/img/manifests/ivrla:6962"></dcterms:isReferencedBy><svcs:has_service rdf:resource="https://iiif.ucd.ie/loris/ivrla:6963"/></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="https://iiif.ucd.ie/loris/ivrla:6963/full/600,/0/default.jpg"/><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm009291"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Reflections</skos:prefLabel></skos:Concept><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127595#concept"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Statues</skos:prefLabel></skos:Concept><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm006699"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Modeling (sculpture)</skos:prefLabel></skos:Concept><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm009290"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Sculptors</skos:prefLabel></skos:Concept><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm007721"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Photographs</skos:prefLabel></skos:Concept><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/51"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">Skulptur</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hi">मूर्ति कला</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Bildhauerkunst</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">Kuvanveisto</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="be">Скульптура</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Скульптура</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pt">Escultura</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bg">Скулптура</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lt">Skulptūra</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hr">Kiparstvo</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lv">Tēlniecība</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">Sculpture</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">Szobrászat</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="yi">סקולפטור</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bs">Skulptura</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hy">Քանդակագործություն</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ka">ქანდაკება</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="uk">Скульптура</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sk">Sochárstvo</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sl">Kiparstvo</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ga">Dealbhóireacht</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">Escultura</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="mk">Вајарство</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sr">Вајарство</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sv">Skulptur</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ko">조각</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gl">Escultura</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">Γλυπτική</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Sculpture</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="is">Höggmyndalist</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">Scultura</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="zh">雕塑</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="es">Escultura</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">Skulptuur</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cs">Sochařství</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ar">نحت</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cy">Cerfluniaeth</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ja">彫刻</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="az">Heykəl</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pl">Rzeźba</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ro">Sculptură</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">Skulptur</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="he">פיסול</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="tr">Heykel</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">Beeldhouwkunst</skos:prefLabel><skos:note xml:lang="no">En skulptur (av latin sculpere, «hugge ut») er et tredimensjonalt kunstverk av enhver type. Tradisjonelle skulpturer kan være hugget i stein eller tre, eller være fremstilt av materialer som bronse, gips eller porselen. Moderne skulpturer kan være laget av industrielle materialer som aluminium eller plast, og skulpturer kan også være ferdig produserte gjenstander (readymades) som kunstneren har valgt ut i en bestemt hensikt.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hi">शिल्पकला (sculpture) कला का वह रूप है जो त्रिविमीय (three-dimensional) होती है। यह कठोर पदार्थ (जैसे पत्थर), मृदु पदार्थ (plastic material) एवं प्रकाश आदि से बनाये जा सकते हैं। मूर्तिकला एक अतिप्राचीन कला है।</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fi">Kuvanveisto on taiteellista ilmaisua kolmiulotteisessa muodossa. Nimityksenä käytetään myös nimitystä plastinen sommittelu, joka ehkä paremmin kuvaa nykyaikaista kuvanveistoa. Kuva taas on kaksiulotteista ilmaisua, jossa kolmas ulottuvuus esitetään illuusion avulla. Kuvanveistotaiteen harjoittajia kutsutaan kuvanveistäjiksi.Vaikka sanaliite -veisto viittaa veistämiseen, siis tekotapaan jota sovelletaan esimerkiksi kiven tai puun työstämiseen, veistos-sanaa käytetään yleisnimityksenä kaikille kolmiulotteisille taideteoksille, niiden tekemiselle ja tekoperiaatteille. Veistoksia ovat myös esimerkiksi valetut, muovatut tai hitsatut, eri tavoilla kootut kolmiulotteiset teokset ja kuvanveisto on niiden tekemistä – veistoksen tekotekniikka voi siis olla luonteeltaan poistava tai lisäävä. Kuvanveisto on osa perinteistä kuvataidetta.Veistokset ovat tavallisesti uniikkeja eli niistä tehdään vain yksi tai korkeintaan muutamia kappaleita. Sarjavalmistukseen suunnitellun kolmiulotteisen esineen suunnittelua ja muokkaamista kutsutaan muotoiluksi.Veistokset voivat olla patsaita, jolloin ne yleensä ovat vapaina seisovia, tai korkokuvia (pintakuvia, kohokuvia), joilloin niitä sanotaan myös reliefeiksi. Reliefit ripustetaan yleensä seinälle tai upotetaan seinään, mutta joskus, sangen harvoin, pidetään lattiatasossa. Henkilöä esittävä veistos voi olla joko korkokuva, rintakuva (pää ja hartiat) tai patsas, jossa henkilö on kuvattu kokonaan. Veistos näyttää eri suunnilta erilaiselta, samoin valaistus vaikuttaa veistoksen ulkonäköön. Patsaan muotoiset veistokset sijoitetaan usein puistoihin tai muuten näkyvälle paikalle, ja yleensä niiden ympäri voi kävellä ja niitä voi katsella eri suunnista. Kaikki veistokset eivät ole patsaita, vaan veistoksia ovat myös esimerkiksi puusta, kivesta, metallista tai savesta tai muusta muotoiltavasta materiaalista, myös nykyisin lumesta ja jäästä, tehdyt korkokuvat eli reliefit, jotka ovat pintakuvia, joissa kuvan osat ovat kohollaan pohjasta. Muinaisissa kulttuureissa kohokuvat olivat yleisiä ja ne esittivät usein historiallisia tapahtumia. Veistokset voidaan myös tehdä paitsi katseltaviksi myös kosketeltaviksi. Veistos voi esittää ihmistä, eläintä tai kasvia luonnonmukaisesti tai tyylitellen tai olla abstrakti taideteos. Jos veistoksessa on liikkuvia osia, nimitetään sitä mobileksi.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="be">Скульптура, пластыка (лац.: sculpo — выразаю, высякаю) — від выяўленчага мастацтва, творы якога маюць аб'ёмную, трохмерную форму і выконваюцца высяканнем, выразаннем, лепкай, коўкай, ліццём ці іншым спосабам з цвёрдых ці пластычных матэрыялаў (камень, метал, дрэва, гліна і інш.). Мастацка-выразнымі сродкамі скульптуры з'яўляюцца пабудова аб'ёмнай формы, пластычная мадэліроўка (лепка), распрацоўка сілуэта, фактуры, часам колеру.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ru">Скульпту́ра (лат. sculptura, от sculpo — вырезаю, высекаю) — ваяние, пластика — вид изобразительного искусства, произведения которого имеют объёмную форму и выполняются из твёрдых или пластических материалов — в широком значении слова, искусство создавать из глины, воска, камня, металла, дерева, кости и других материалов изображение человека, животных и иных предметов природы в осязательных, телесных их формах.Художник, посвятивший себя искусству скульптуры, называется скульптором, или ваятелем. Главную его задачу составляет передача человеческой фигуры в реальном или идеализированном виде, животные играют в его творчестве второстепенную роль, а прочие предметы являются лишь в значении придаточных или обрабатываются исключительно с орнаментальной целью.Слово скульптура, помимо самого вида искусства, обозначает также каждое отдельное его произведение.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pt">Escultura é uma arte que representa imagens plásticas em relevo total ou parcial. Existem várias técnicas de trabalhar os materiais, como a cinzelação, a fundição, a moldagem ou a aglomeração de partículas para a criação de um objeto.Vários materiais se prestam a esta arte, uns mais perenes como o bronze ou o mármore, outros mais fáceis de trabalhar, como a argila, a cera ou a madeira.Embora possam ser utilizadas para representar qualquer coisa, ou até coisa nenhuma, tradicionalmente o objetivo maior foi sempre representar o corpo humano, ou a divindade numa forma antropomórfica.É considerada a quarta das artes clássicas.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bg">Скулптурата е вид изящно изкуство, чийто произведения се изработват в обемна пространствена форма от твърди или пластични материали. Те се създават чрез оформяне или комбиниране на твърди материали, предимно от камък, като мрамор, метал, стъкло или дърво, или пластични материали като глина, плат, полимери и по-меки материали. Терминът може да се отнася и до произведения, включващи звук, текст и светлина.Отлети обекти могат да бъдат представени като скулптури. Материалите могат да бъдат третирани чрез отстраняване, например резба. Могат да бъдат сглобявани, например чрез спояване, или правени по-твърди, например изпичани, формовани или отливани. Може да бъде прилагана декорация на повърхността, например оцветяване. Скулптурата се определя като едно от пластичните изкуства, защото включва използването на материали, които могат да бъдат отливани или моделирани.Скулптурата е важна форма на общественото изкуство.Ваенето е изкуството на оформяне на обекти, които могат да са с всякакъв размер и от най-различен материал. Може да бъдат изработени по два начина: чрез извайване (с твърд материал - камък, мрамор, бронз, дърво и др.) и чрез моделиране (с пластичен материал - восък, глина и др.)Човекът, изработващ скулптури, се нарича скулптор. Скулпторите обикновено учат в художествени школи, както повечето художници, и в даден момент се насочват към този вид изкуство.Измежду най-известните скулптори са Микеланджело Буонароти, Леонардо да Винчи, Огюст Роден и др. Някои известни български скулптори са Андрей Николов, Георги Чапкънов, Красимир Рангелов, Иван Лазаров,Крум Дерменджиев, Любомир Далчев, Петко Москов, Георги Данчев, Величко Минеков, Георги Филин, Спас Киричев, Вежди Рашидов и др.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lt">Skulptūra – meno šaka, apimanti erdvinių estetiškų, meninių objektų kūrimą iš įvairių medžiagų, kopijuojant aplinkoje egzistuojančias formas, sureikšminant ir pabrėžiant tam tikras jų ypatybes arba kuriant abstrakčius objektus, remiantis pagrindinėmis geometrinėmis formomis.Tai – vaizduojamosios dailės šaka ir seniausia trimačio meno rūšis. Skulptūra sukuriama pridedant vieną medžiagos masę prie kitos (pvz., lipdyba, koliažas) arba nuimant medžiagos dalį (kalimas, drožyba).Svarbiausios skulptūros meninės išraiškos priemonės – formų erdvinė padėtis, proporcijos, siluetas, ritmas, faktūra. Pagal padėtį erdvėje būna apvalioji skulptūra, reljefas, pagal funkciją – paminklinė, dekoratyvinė, kamerinė skulptūra, smulkioji skulptūra. Svarbiausios skulptūros formos: statula, skulptūrinė grupė, biustas, galva, torsas, medalis, plaketė, gema.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hr">Kiparstvo, također skulptura (lat. sculpere = sjeći, rezati) i plastika (grčki plassein = oblikovati) grana je likovne umjetnosti; vrsta likovnog izražavanja trodimenzionalnim oblicima i tijelima - skulpturama; umjetnost oblikovanja volumena u prostoru.Neki teoretičari umjetnosti, npr. Marcel Bačić, strogo razlikuju termine skulptura i plastika. Kod skulpture praktično se radi o oduzimanju materijala od površine umjetničkog djela, npr. kamena kod klesanja, a kod plastike se radi o modeliranju materijala, npr. gline. Ovo značenje termina već implicira njihova etimologija .Za razliku od slike koja ima samo dvije dimenzije (visinu i širinu), kip ima i treću – dubinu; kiparsko djelo se može osjetiti, odmjeriti, pa i "pročitati" dodirom ruke, tj. taktilno – opipati. Stoga kiparsko djelo promatramo drukčije nego sliku. Da bi smo ga sagledali u cjelini, valja ga vidjeti sa svih strana. Za razliku od slike koja ima samo jednu kompoziciju, kiparsko djelo sadrži toliko kompozicija, koliko ima kutova gledanja (svakim pomakom motrišta gledanja mijenja se odnos dijelova skulpture prema cjelini).Kipar je umjetnik koji se bavi kiparstvom. Njegov zadatak je da oblikuje (modelira) materijal s kojime radi, kao što su glina, kamen i sl. Kiparstvo je umjetnost trodimenzionalnosti, stoga se naziva i prostorno-plastičko oblikovanje.Kakve će oblike kipar stvarati ovisi o materijalu koji može biti savitljiv i rastezljiv – kao što su glina, plastelin, vosak, koji dopuštaju da se obliku dodaje i oduzima, dok primjerice drvo, kamen ili bjelokost, zbog krutosti građe, omogućuju samo oduzimanje. Javni kipovi, sakralni i profani, podizani su svecima i ljudima, pobjedama i porazima, znanstvenicima i vojskovođama, umjetnicima i državnicima, običnim ljudima, u spomen na različita zbivanja i pojave. (Npr. Požega i Osijek – "kužni pilovi", Zagreb – "brončani Šenoa", "Matoš na klupi" …).Uz to, kiparstvo se služi nebrojenim materijalima, ali su sva klasična kiparska djela oblikovana u drvu, kamenu, mramoru ili bronci. Svakom materijalu odgovara neka kiparska tehnika.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lv">Tēlniecība ir tēlotājas mākslas veids, kurā no koka, akmens, bronzas vai kāda cita materiāla tiek radīti telpiski mākslas darbi (ciļņi, skulptūras u.c.).</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fr">La sculpture est une activité artistique qui consiste à concevoir et réaliser des formes en volume, en relief, soit en ronde-bosse (statuaire), en haut-relief, en bas-relief, par modelage, par taille directe, par soudure ou assemblage.Le mot sculpture vient étymologiquement du latin « sculpere » qui signifie « tailler » ou « enlever des morceaux à une pierre ». Cette définition, qui distingue « sculpture » et « modelage », illustre l'importance donnée à la taille de la pierre dans la civilisation romaine. Au Xe siècle, on parle d'« ymagier » et la plupart du temps, le travail du sculpteur est un travail d'équipe avec un maître et des tailleurs de pierre (Voir architecture romane et art roman). Plusieurs équipes travaillent simultanément sur les grands chantiers des cathédrales.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hu">Szobrászat bármely háromdimenziós művészi kifejezés. A szobrászat elsődlegesen a térrel áll összefüggésben: kitölti, viszonyul hozzá és hatással van az érzékelésére.A fogalom egyúttal művészi alaptevékenységet is jelöl: egy tárgy fizikai vagy jelentésbeli jellemzőjének megváltoztatását, úgy mint hely, forma, méret, tömeg, szín, szerkezet, hőmérséklet, illat, környezeti viszony, összetétel, összefüggés. Sok kortárs szobor az elrendezéssel, határvonalakkal vagy egyszerűen az elnevezésével közvetíti jelentését. Egy szoborként definiált tárgy létrejöhet emberi kéz hatására vagy természetes úton.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="yi">סקולפטור איז א דריי-דימענסיאלער אביעקט, וואס פאר די ציל פון איר באשאפונג איז זי געמאכט געווארן דורך א מענטש, און ארויסגעהויבן און אנערקענט אלס קונסט פאר די מאסן צו באטראכטן און באוואונדערן.מען קען סקולפטארן כל מיני חפצים. א סקולפטור פון א מענטש אדער א חיה, אין גרויס פון א לעבעדיגער מענטש אדער גרעסער, רופט זיך סטאטוע.דער מענטש וואס בויעט דאס הייסט א סקולפטאר.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bs">Skulptura je svaka trodimenzionalna forma kreirana u cilju umjetničkog izraza. Većina skulptura ima čisto estetski cilj. Kada trodimenzionalni objekat ima osim umjetničkog i funkcionalni aspekt, možemo ga nazvati skulpturom samo ukoliko je umjetnički aspekt predominantan. Kada su funkcionalni i umjetnički aspekt balansirani, nazivamo ga funkcionalnom skulpturom.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hy">Քանդակագործությունը պատկերում է հիմնականում մարդուն, կենդանիներ (անիմալիստական ժանր), սակավ՝ բնությունը (բնապատկեր) և առարկաներ (նատյուրմորտ)։ Քանդակը, սովորաբար, նախ կերտում են կավից, պլաստիլինից կամ մոմից, ապա ձուլում գիպսից. գիպսե ձուլածոները ծառայում են նաև որպես մոդել՝ քանդակն ավելի մնայուն նյութերով (փայտ, քար, մետաղ) վերստեղծելու համար։ Քանդակն ունի 2 ենթատեսակ՝ բոլորաքանդակ (ստեղծագործությունը բոլոր կողմերից տեսանելի է) և ռելիեֆ (պատկերը հարթության վրա փորագրվում է կամ կերտվում որոշակի ցցունությամբ)։ Ռելիեֆները, ըստ ծավալային պատկերաձևերի, լինում են բարձրաքանդակ (քանդակապատկերի ծավալի կեսից ավելին դուրս է մակերեսից), հարթաքանդակ (քանդակապատկերի ծավալի կեսից պակասը դուրս է մակերեսից) և խորաքանդակ (մակերեսից խոր ընկած քանդակապատկեր), որոնք հարդարում են շենքի ճակատը, գոտին, ճակտոնը, ներսի պատերն ու առաստաղը (առաստաղապատկեր)։ Քանդակագործության մեջ տարբերակում են մոնումենտալ, հաստոցային, դեկորատիվ և փոքր ձևերի քանդակներ։ Մոնումենտալ քանդակի նպատակը կարևոր գաղափարների, պատմական իրադարձությունների, ականավոր մարդկանց դերի քարոզումն է և հիշատակի հավերժացումը. դրվում է բաց տարածության մեջ և հասարակական վայրերում։ Հաստոցային քանդակը բնական կամ ճարտարապետական միջավայրից կախում չունի. դրվում է թանգարաններում, հասարակական կամ բնակելի շենքերի ներսում։ Մեծ հնարավորություններ ունի թե՜ բոլորաքանդակում, թե՜ ռելիեֆում մարմնավորելու թեմատիկ զանազան իրավիճակներ և արտահայտելու կերպարի ներաշխարհի առանձնահատկությունները։ Դեկորատիվ քանդակը զարդարման միջոց է և սովորաբար համադրվում է ճարտարապետության հետ։</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ka">ქანდაკება, სკულპტურა (ლათ. sculptura, sculpo — გამოჭრა, ვთლი) — სახვითი ხელოვნების პლასტიკა — გამოსახულება, რომლის შექმნასაც აქვს მოცულობითი ფორმა და სრულდება მაგარი ან პლასტიკური მასალებისგან.სკულპტურების მთავარი ჟანრია — პორტრეტი, ისტორიული, საყოფაცხოვრებო, სიმბოლური, ალეგორიული გამოსახულება, ცხოველების გამოსახულება. სკულპტურების სამხატვრო გამოხატულებაა მოცულობითი ფორმის შექმნა, პლასტიკური მოდელირება (გამოქანდაკება), სილუეტის შექმნა, ფაქტურის, ზოგიერთ შემთხვევაში ფერისაც კი.განასხვავებენ მომრგვალო სკულპტურასა (სტატუა, ჯგუფები, სტატუეტი, ბიუსტი, შეიძლება შეხედოთ სხვადასხვა მხრიდან) და რელიეფურს (როცა გამოსახულება მდებარეობს სიბრტყეზე). მონუმენტური სკულპტურა, ძეგლები, მონუმენტები ურთიერთობაშია არქიტექტურულ მხარესთან.სკულპტურების შემადგენლობა შეიძლება იყოს ლითონი, ქვა, თიხა, ხე, გიფსი და სხვა. მისი დამუშავების მეთოდებია გამოქანდაკება, გამოძერწვა, ამოჩხაპნა, გამოჭრა, გამოთლა და სხვა.იტალიური რენესანსის დროიდან მოყოლებული მოქანდაკეები ქმნიდნენ რეალური საგნების, რეალური სამყაროს მეტ–ნაკლებად ზუსტ გამოსახულებებს. სკულპტურა ამ პერიოდში ჯერ კიდევ არ წარმოადგენდა თვითგამოხატვის საშუალებას. ეს იყო სახალხო ხელოვნება რომელიც შენობებს,სხვადასხვა დაწესებულებებს დეკორს უკეთებდა. სკულპტურა გამოიყენებოდა სხვადასხვა ისტორიული მოვლენის, დღესასწაულის თუ პიროვნების უკვდავსაყოფად.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="uk">Скульпту́ра (лат. sculptura, від лат. sculpo — вирізаю, висікаю) — ліпка, пластика, вид образотворчого мистецтва, твори якого мають об'ємну, тривимірну форму і виконуються із твердих чи пластичних матеріалів. Скульптура зображує головним чином людину, рідше тварин, її головні жанри — портрет, історичні, побутові, символічні, алегоричні зображення, анімалістичний жанр. Художньо-виразні засоби скульптури — побудова об'ємної форми, пластичне моделювання (ліпка), розробка силуету, фактури, у деяких випадках також кольору.За своєю формою розділяють два види скульптури: рельєф та круглу скульптуру. Остання в залежності від призначення ділиться на монументальну (великі архітектурні ансамблі, пам'ятники), монументально-декоративну (прикрашає будинки та парки) та станкову (зазвичай представлена в музеях, на виставках або є частиною інтер'єру)</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sk">Sochárstvo je trojrozmerný druh umenia, ktoré na svoju prezentáciu používa formovanie pevného (rôzne druhy kameňov – najčastejšie mramor, kov, drevo), alebo plastického materiálu (keramika, sklo, porcelán…). Sochy z pevného materiálu (skulptúry) sú vyrábané tesaním, vyrezávaním, odlievaním do foriem, brúsením, rezaním, zváraním… Sochy z plastického materiálu (plastiky) sú spravidla formované modelovaním, po ktorom nasleduje tepelné spracovanie, ktorým sa dosiahne pevná štruktúra výsledného sochárskeho diela. Človek, ktorý vytvára sochárske dielo sa nazýva sochár.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sl">Kipárstvo (skulptura, plastika) je vrsta umetnosti, kjer kiparji izdelujejo trorazsežne oblike - kipe (skulpture). Večina kipov ima zgolj estetski namen. Kadar ima trorazsežni predmet poleg umetniškega tudi uporabni vidik, ga lahko imenujemo kip le, če umetniški vidik prevladuje. Ko sta umetniški in uporabni vidik uravnotežena, ga imenujemo funkcionalni kip.Temeljni kiparski zvrsti sta obla plastika (okrogla, prosto stoječa) in relief (ki je vezana na ploskev). Po vlogi in nalogi je kiparsko delo samostojno ali vezano na arhitekturo (arhitekturna plastika). Dela so lahko namenjena enemu ali več pogledom, lahko so nepremična ali gibljiva, spremenljiva (mobili). Med osrednje naloge kiparstva je sodilo upodabljanje človeškega lika ( celopostavne in doprsne upodobitve, torzo itd.). Z besedo kiparstvo sta tesno povezana izraza skulptura (ki v jedru pomeni umetnost odvzemanja – rezljanje, klesanje) in plastika (ki pomeni umetnost oblikovanja z dodajanjem snovi – modeliranje). Vendar kiparska dela nastajajo tudi s konsruiranjem (varjenjem, lepljenjem itd.) in ulivanjem v kalupe. Kiparstvo uporablja različne tradicionalne in nove materiale.Če začne prevladovati uporabni vidik, kiparstvo postane oblikovanje (dizajn). Materiali, ki jih kiparji lahko uporabljajo, so lahko poljubni. Tudi velikost kipov nima omejitev. Tehnike in način dela: modeliranje, vlivanje, upogibanje, rezanje, klesanje, kovanje, rezbarjenje, tolčenje (torevtika), spajanje, instaliranje.Zgodovino kiparstva preučuje umetnostna zgodovina.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ga">Is é atá i gceist le dealbhóireacht ná obair ealaíne thríthoiseach a chruthaítear nuair a lúbtar nó nuair a mheasctar ábhair éagsúla, mar shampla cloch (carraig nó marmar), miotal, gloine, adhmad, fuaim, téacs, solas agus araile. Is minic a thaispeántar dealbha mar ealaín phoiblí.Tugtar dealbhóir ar ealaíontóir a cruthaíonn dealbh.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ca">L'escultura és una de les belles arts. A diferència de la pintura, la qual es crea en un pla –un espai fictici de dues dimensions–, l'escultura ho fa en un pla tridimensional exempt o en relleu, tot utilitzant l'espai real. L'escultor actua sobre diferents materials que transforma mitjançant processos de talla i modelatge, que són els mètodes tradicionals. L'ús de diferents combinacions de materials i mitjans ha originat un nou repertori artístic que comprèn processos com el constructivisme i l'assemblatge. En un sentit genèric, s'entén per escultura l'obra d'art plàstica feta per l'escultor. Giorgio Vasari (1511-1573) inicia la seva Le Vite de' più eccellenti pittori, scultori, ed architettori italiani amb un pròleg força tècnic en el qual parla d'arquitectura, escultura i pintura, unes disciplines agrupades sota la denominació d'«arts del disseny». L'obra és un tractat informatiu sobre les tècniques artístiques emprades a l'època. Pel que fa a l'escultura, explica: Des dels temps més remots l'home ha tingut la necessitat d'esculpir. Al principi ho va fer amb els materials més simples i que tenia a mà: la pedra, el fang i la fusta; després va emprar el ferro, el bronze, el plom, la cera, el guix, la plastilina, la resina de polièster i els plàstics amb reforç de fibra de vidre, el formigó, la cinètica i la reflexió de la llum, entre d'altres. L'escultura va tenir al principi una única funció, el seu ús immediat; posteriorment s'hi afegí una funció ritual, màgica, funerària o religiosa. Aquesta funcionalitat va anar canviant amb l'evolució històrica, adquirint una finalitat principalment estètica o simplement ornamental i podent arribar a constituir-se com un element durador o efímer.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="mk">Вајарство во уметностите најчесто се однесува на скулптура, а скулптура (ваја) е било која тридимензионална форма создадена како уметнички израз.Поимот скулптура исто така се однесува на уметничката дисциплина, акт или уметност на правење скулптури низ манипулација на материјали или, во современа уметност, низ поставување на предмет или дури и акт како скулптура. Уметникот што го прави ова е наречен „вајар“ (или скулптор). Скулптура е исто така колективниот поим за колекција или жанр на скулптури т.е. грчка класична скулптура или егзибиција на скулптура. Скулптурите често се бојосуваат.Познати македонски вајари: Томе Серафимовски, Боро Митриќески, Бранко Конески, Васил Василев, Жарко Башески, Митко Тошев и други.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sr">Вајарство или скулптура (лат. sculpere - клесати, урезивати) је уметност обликовања тродимензионалних облика (кипова) у материјалима као што су камен, мермер, дрво, метал, глина, стакло, пластика и многи други. Вајарство, као сликарство и архитектуру убрајамо у ликовну, али и у пластичну или просторну уметност, јер вајар - човек који креира склуптуру - уметнички обликују простор.Већина скулптура има чисто естетски или уметнички циљ. Када тродимензионални објекат - скулптура има, осим уметничког и употребни аспект, можемо га назвати скулптуром само уколико је уметнички аспект предоминантан, а када су употребни и уметнички аспект балансирани, називамо га функционалном скулптуром, а како уметнички аспект препушта више место употребном, вајарство постаје дизајн.Велики број вајара сматра да су само линија, површина и волумен, и када се томе придода симетрија, пропорција и ритам, довољни да се изрази мисао и да се преточи у скулптуру. Такве скулптуре припадају нефигуративном - апстрактном вајарству.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sv">Skulptur (från latinets verb sculpere "att hugga ut/skulptera") är ett tredimensionellt konstverk. Skulptur har i motsats till övriga bildkonstarter en kropp, det vill säga en materiell volym i rummet. Till skillnad från byggnadskonsten tjänar skulpturen estetiska och inte materiella ändamål.Traditionellt har skulpturer formats ur hårda material som sten, metal, glas eller trä, eller ur plastiska material som lera, textil, polymerer och mjukare metaller. Idag används även begreppet för konstverk som omfattar ljud, text och ljus. Även funna objekt, som från början skapats för andra ändamål, så kallade objet trouvé eller ready-mades, kan presenteras som skulpturer.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ko">조각(彫刻)은 미술 감상을 목적으로, 다양한 소재를 이용해 만들어진 입체 작품을 의미한다. (전술한 바를 '조소(彫塑)'라고 하여, 이것을 다시 '조각'과 '소조(塑造)'로 나누는 용법도 있다. 이때 소재를 깎는 방법으로 조형해 나가는 것을 '조각', 소재를 붙여가는 방법으로 조형하는 것을 '소조'라고 하게 된다.)일반적으로 감상을 목적으로 만들어진 것이며, 생활 용구로 사용되는 공예품이나 도예품 등 실용성 있는 것들은 제외된다.조각에 쓰이는 소재는 돌, 나무, 흙(점토, 테라코타), 섬유, 종이, 얼음과 같은 자연물에서부터 석고, 금속(철, 구리 등), 수지(합성수지), 유리, 납 등 인공물을 포함, 여러 재료를 함께 조합하는 작품도 많다.제작 수법도 조각을 기본으로 하여, 깎고, 붙이고, 용접하고, 부수는 등 여러가지이고 특정 수법으로 치우치는 견해는 없다.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="gl">A escultura é unha arte que representa imaxes plásticas de relevancia total ou parcial. Existen varias técnicas de traballar os materiais para a creación dun obxecto. A escultura é unha forma de expresión artística en tres dimensións o vulto redondo, ou de relevo, altorrelevo ou baixorrelevo. As técnicas escultóricas consisten principalmente en retirar ou xuntar ou moldear materia ou ben dando forma a un obxecto, sexa cal for a súa dimensión ou material usado.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="el">Γλυπτική ονομάζεται η τέχνη της καλλιτεχνικής δημιουργίας - έκφρασης, που εκτελείται μέσω της δημιουργίας τρισδιάστατων μορφών σε οποιοδήποτε μέσο. Τα υλικά που χρησιμοποιούνται είναι διάφορα, σκληρά, όπως η πέτρα, το μάρμαρο, τα μέταλλα ή το ξύλο, ή και πιο μαλακά, όπως ο πηλός ή διάφορα πλαστικά (στη σύγχρονη γλυπτική). Είναι δυνατός ακόμη ο συνδυασμός διαφορετικών υλικών.Το πρώτο στάδιο είναι η εύρεση των αντικειμένων που θα παρουσιαστούν από τους γλύπτες. Έπειτα, τα επιλεγμένα υλικά υφίστανται επεξεργασία με διάφορες τεχνικές, αφαιρετικές όπως το σκάλισμα, ή προσθετικές όπως η συγκόλληση. Υπάρχουν ακόμη τεχνικές που τροποποιούν τη σκληρότητα των χρησιμοποιουμένων υλικών. Όταν τελειώσει το γλυπτό ή το ανάγλυφο, η επιφάνειά του μπορεί να διακοσμηθεί επιπλέον με χρήση ζωγραφικής. Τέλος, μια συλλογή γλυπτών, τοποθετούνται μερικές φορές σε «κήπους γλυπτών»</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="en">Sculpture is the branch of the visual arts that operates in three dimensions and one of the plastic arts. Durable sculptural processes originally used carving (the removal of material) and modelling (the addition of material, as clay), in stone, metal, ceramics, wood and other materials but, since modernism, shifts in sculptural process led to an almost complete freedom of materials and process. A wide variety of materials may be worked by removal such as carving, assembled by welding or modelling, or molded, or cast.Sculpture in stone survives far better than works of art in perishable materials, and often represents the majority of the surviving works (other than pottery) from ancient cultures, though conversely traditions of sculpture in wood may have vanished almost entirely. However, most ancient sculpture was brightly painted, and this has been lost.Sculpture has been central in religious devotion in many cultures, and until recent centuries large sculptures, too expensive for private individuals to create, were usually an expression of religion or politics. Those cultures whose sculptures have survived in quantities include the cultures of the Ancient Mediterranean, India and China, as well as many in South America and Africa.The Western tradition of sculpture began in Ancient Greece, and Greece is widely seen as producing great masterpieces in the classical period. During the Middle Ages, Gothic sculpture represented the agonies and passions of the Christian faith. The revival of classical models in the Renaissance produced famous sculptures such as Michelangelo's David. Modernist sculpture moved away from traditional processes and the emphasis on the depiction of the human body, with the making of constructed sculpture, and the presentation of found objects as finished art works.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="is">Höggmyndalist er sú listgrein að höggva (hlutbundna eða óhlutbundna) mynd úr steini eða öðru hörðu efni, gera t.d. líkan úr marmara eða styttu úr bronsi.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="it">La scultura è (nel senso moderno del termine) l'arte di dare forma ad un oggetto partendo da un materiale grezzo o assemblando diversi materiali.Come molte altre parole riguardanti il mondo dell'arte anche la parola scultura e quindi il concetto che essa rappresenta si sono evoluti nel tempo.È possibile modellare un oggetto per addizione o sottrazione, a seconda del materiale.Materiali come il legno il marmo ecc. permettono di scolpire intagliando o scolpendo la materia stessa. Materiali come l'argilla invece consentono di modellare per addizione aggiungendo man mano materia alla materia iniziale.Con il termine scultura si indica anche il prodotto finale, ovvero qualsiasi oggetto tridimensionale creato come espressione artistica.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="zh">雕塑是一種造型艺术，以物质材料和手段制作的三维空间形象的视觉艺术。雕塑最早主要是使用雕（通过减除材料来造型）及塑（通过叠加材料来造型）的方式，在石、金属、木、陶瓷等材料來創作，不過現代主義的雕塑，在材料及創造手法上都有很高的自由度，可以利用雕、焊接、模塑或鑄造的方式，在各種不同的材質上進行創作。石雕比其他材質易腐壞的雕塑更可以在長時間後保存下來，古文化所留下的雕塑也多半以石雕及陶藝為主。同時期也有很多傳統的木雕，但很多都已經腐朽無法保存。古文化的雕塑許多曾都有亮麗的顏色，但現在多半已經褪色。在很多文化中，雕塑是宗教崇拜的中心，一直到最近幾世紀之前，大型雕塑都還非常昂貴，非一般個人有能力可能負擔，因此大型雕塑多半是宗教或政治的產物。像古地中海、印度、中國、南美及非洲的古文化都留下許多的雕塑。西方文化中的雕塑起源於古希臘，許多希臘的雕塑家在古典希臘時期創作了許多傑出的雕塑品。在中古世紀，哥特式雕塑表現了基督教中的痛苦及激情，文藝復興時期崇尚古典作品，像米开朗基罗的大衛像就是當時著名的作品。現代主義雕塑較不著重傳統的工藝及人體的描繪，改用集合藝術和拾得物作為其作品的呈現。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="es">Se llama escultura (del latín sculptūra) al arte de modelar el barro, tallar en piedra, madera u otros materiales. También se denomina escultura a la obra elaborada por el escultor.Es una de las Bellas Artes en la cual el escultor se expresa creando volúmenes y conformando espacios. En la escultura se incluyen todas las artes de talla y cincel, junto con las de fundición y moldeado. Dentro de la escultura, el uso de diferentes combinaciones de materiales y medios ha originado un nuevo repertorio artístico, que comprende procesos como el constructivismo y el assemblage. En un sentido genérico, se entiende por escultura la obra artística plástica realizada por el escultor.Giorgio Vasari (1511-1573), empieza Le vite de' più eccellenti pittori, scultori e architettori con un prólogo técnico que habla de arquitectura, escultura y pintura, unas disciplinas agrupadas bajo la denominación de «artes del diseño». La obra es un tratado informativo y valioso sobre las técnicas artísticas empleadas en la época. En referencia a la escultura comienza así:... el escultor saca todo lo superfluo y reduce el material a la forma que existe dentro de la mente del artista.Desde tiempos remotos el hombre ha tenido la necesidad de esculpir. Al principio lo hizo con los materiales más simples y que tenía más a mano: piedra, arcilla y madera. Después empleó hierro, bronce, plomo, cera, yeso, plastilina, resina de poliéster y plásticos con refuerzo de fibra de vidrio, hormigón, la cinética y la reflexión de la luz, entre otros. La escultura tuvo en su principio una única función, su uso inmediato; posteriormente se añadió una función ritual, mágica, funeraria y religiosa. Esta funcionalidad fue cambiando con la evolución histórica, adquiriendo una principalmente estética o simplemente ornamental y llegó a ser un elemento duradero o efímero.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="et">Skulptuur (ladina keeles sculptura) on kujutava kunsti põhiliike graafika ja maalikunsti kõrval.Materjali ja töötlemisviisi alusel jaotatakse skulptuur raidkunstiks ja plastikaks.Otstarbe järgi eristatakse:monumentaalskulptuurimonumentaal-dekoratiivskulptuurivabaplastikatpisiplastikatSkulptuur teises tähenduses on ruumiline, kolmemõõtmeline kunstiteos.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="eu">Eskulturagintza edo eskultura arte nagusien mota tradizionaletakoa da, hiru dimentsiotan egindako irudiak sortzen dituena gai gogorrak (harria, marmola, metala, beira, zura) edo bigunak erabiliz. Era honetan, arte plastikoetan sailkatuta dago ere bai.Eskultura izena hartzen dute arlo honetan egindako irudiak, eta eskultore edo zizelkaria da esparru honetan lan egiten duen artista.Bestela, arte agerpen publiko gehienak eskulturak dira.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cs">Sochařství je specifickou částí výtvarného umění, která představuje samostatnou svébytnou oblast výtvarného projevu spojující architekturu s malířstvím. Od obou se však liší užitou látkou i metodou.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ar">النحت هو فن تجسيدي يرتكز على إنشاء مجسمات ثلاثية الأبعاد (3D) لإنسان، حيوان... وذلك باستخدام الجص أو الشمع، أو نقش الصخور...فن النحت أحد جوانب الابداع الفني وهو يعتمد علي المجسمات الثلاثيه الابعاد.وفن النحت من الفنون القديمه قدم الإنسان فهو أقدم من فن التصوير مثلا فإنسان اقدر علي التعبير النحتي عنه عن التعبير بالرسم.و فن النحت يتعامل مع المجسمات الثلاثيه الابعاد علي العكس من الرسم والتصوير الذي يتعامل مع الابعاد الثنائيه.و يمكننا ان نجد نماذج النحت في الحضارات القديمه باختلاف اشكاله ومنها في الحضارات الفرعونيه والرومانيه واليونانيه التي نجد فيها فن النحت من أكثر الفنون انتشارا وتعبير عن الجو المحيط مع اختلاف الغرض من استخدام هذا الفن وعادة كان المقصود منها النواحي الدينية للتعبير عن الالهه المختلفه الخاصه بهم.و أيضاً نجد انتشار فن النحت في عصر النهضة والباروك ووجود نحاتين عظام.وان كان استخدام فن النحت في عصورنا الحاليه الغرض منه أساسا الابداع الفني وتوصيل رساله معينه الي الجمهور باختلاف الأسلوب المستخدم فيه مثل التجريدي والهندسي والأكاديمي.أنواع النحتبعض الأشكال الشائعة النحت هي :قائمة بذاتها النحت، والنحت ومحاصرة من جميع الجهات، باستثناء القاعدة، من خلال الفضاء. ومن المعروف أيضا والنحت "في الجولة"، والمقصود أن ينظر إليها من أي زاوية.صوت النحتضوء النحتالمجوهرات أو مجوهراتالإغاثة—لا يزال مربوطا في النحت على خلفية؛ أنواع والنحت الغائر، ألتو، relievo، والغارقة الإغاثةموقع محددة الفنالحركية النحت—ينطوي على جوانب الحركة البدنيةنافورة—تم تصميم النحت مع نقل المياهموبايل (انظر أيضا Stabiles كالدر في.)تمثال—النحت representationalist تصور كيان معين، عادة ما يكون الشخص أو الحدث أو الحيوان أو الكائنتمثال نصفي—تمثيل شخص من الصدر بالتسجيلتمثال الفروسية—عرض عادة شخص كبير على ظهور الخيلمكدسة الفن—شكلا من أشكال النحت التي شكلتها كائنات تجميع و'التراص' لهمالنحت المعماريالفن البيئيالنحت البيئيالأرض الفن</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cy">Y gelfyddyd sy'n gweithredu mewn tri dimensiwn yw cerfluniaeth. Gwneir cerfluniau trwy gerfio neu fodelu defnyddiau megis carreg, metel, crochenwaith neu bren.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ja">彫刻（ちょうこく）とは、木、石、土、金属などを彫り刻んで、物の像を立体的に表すこと。または、それらの表面に書画や図版などを掘り込むこと。あるいは美術的な鑑賞を目的として、様々な素材を用いて立体的に制作された芸術作品のこと。また、その表現領域を指す。以下では西洋美術の概念における、芸術作品としての彫刻（スカルプチャー、英語：sculpture）について述べる。硬い素材を彫り刻む技法も彫刻（カーヴィング、carving）と呼び、それに対して、可塑性素材を盛りつけて形を作る技法を彫塑（モデリング、modeling）という。彫塑で作られた作品を特に塑像と呼び分けることもある。使われる素材は、石、木、土、繊維、紙、石膏、金属（鉄、銅など）、樹脂、ガラス、蝋など、多種にわたり、また、複数の素材を組み合わせる作品も多い。彫刻の対象（モチーフ）は元来、人間や身近な動物など具体物であった（具象彫刻）が、20世紀になると、心象を表したもの（抽象彫刻）も多く制作されるようになった。現在では、表現が多様化し、従来の彫刻の概念では収まらないケースもあり、それらを「立体」、「立体アート」と呼ぶこともあるほか、表現が設置空間全体へ拡散したものは、特に「空間表現」や「インスタレーション」と呼び分けられる。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="az">Heykəl — Təsviri incəsənətin bir növü, əsərləri həcmli formaya malikdirlər, bərk və ya plastik materialdan hazırlanır.Heykəllərin əsas janrları — həcmli portret, tarixi, məişət, simvolik, аlleqorik təsvirlər və heyvanların təsvirlərinin verilməsidir.Heykəllərin bədii hazırlanması — həcmli formanın verilməsi, plastik modelləşdirilmə, siluetin hаzırlanması və hətta heykəlin rənginin verilməsi sayılır.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pl">Rzeźba - jedna z dyscyplin zaliczanych do sztuk plastycznych. Od malarstwa i grafiki odróżnia ją trójwymiarowość. Rzeźby są wykonane do oglądania głównie dookolnego, a rzadziej np. do spoglądania na nie z góry czy z dołu. Oprócz tych cech rzeźba może posiadać fakturę (w zależności od użytego materiału) lub kolor (tzw. rzeźba polichromowana). Może być również klasyfikowana ze względu na swoją skalę (np. miniaturowa lub monumentalna). W dawnych wiekach ukształtowały się niezwykle skomplikowane techniki tworzenia rzeźby.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ro">Sculptura este o artă a volumelor în spațiu care încearcă să atingă coarda sensibilă a persoanelor umane prin expunerea spațială a diferite obiecte reale, tridimensionale. Perceperea obiectelor tridimensionale poate avea loc atât vizual cât și pe cale tactilă. Aparent, sculptura se adresează văzului, dar în realitate această formă de artă se adresează, mai ales, tactilului. Din păcate, nu poate fi atinsă întotdeauna o sculptură, așa cum ar fi firesc, dar se pot compensa cu ușurință convențiile sociale de privire de la distanță a pieselor de sculptură prin vedere, ce are remarcabila proprietate de a transmite la creier și tridimensionalitatea obiectelor, întrucât vederea umană este stereoscopică. Despre sculptori și modul în care ei s-au exprimat sculptând, în sensul ideii „clasice” de sculptură, folosind materiale naturale precum lutul, piatra și lemnul, precum și despre sculptorii moderni și contemporani, care adaugă noi fațete noțiunii de sculptură, prin folosirea unor materiale inedite, criticii de artă plastică au scris numeroase studii de specialitate.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="da">Skulptur (fra latin sculptura og sculpere snitte, udskære). Skulptur er en afbildende rumlig kunstnerisk udtryksform, som udføres af en skulptør eller billedhugger. Til skulpturer kan anvendes alle materialer som kan antage form i tre dimensioner. Klassiske materialer: ler, træ, metal, sten, gips og voks. Mere moderne materialer: kunststof, tekstil, glas, sand og is. Eksperimenter er også set med konkrete genstande (readymades/objet trouvé), døde dyr, bygningsmaterialer eller vand, og endelig med inkludering af elementer som tilfældighed, bevægelse og tidsfaktoren.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="he">פיסול הוא ענף בתחום האמנות במסגרתו יוצר האמן יצירה בעלת איכות תלת-ממדית. השינוי אשר מבצע הפַּ‏‏‏סָּ‏‏ל הוא לרוב שינוי פיזי, על ידי שינוי והתאמה של חומרים, אולם באמנות המודרנית קיימת האפשרות גם לשינוי סמנטי של החומר, כלומר לבדיקת יחסו של האובייקט התלת-ממדי אל הסביבה. התוצאה של שינויים אלו מכונה "פֶּ‏סֶ‏ל".בנסיון לענות על שאלת הגדרתו של המדיום, מבחין מחקר תולדות האמנות בין פיסול אנדרטאות, פיסול בקנה מידה קטן ו"אמנות זעירה". הבחנה זו התבססה הן על ערכים כגון גודלו של הפסל ומיקומו במרחב, והן על הערכה שיפוטית של חשיבות היצירה. "אמנות זעירה" (Minor Art), להבדיל משאר סוגי הפיסול המסורתיים, נתפשה כקטגוריה המכילה מגוון של חפצים קטנים, כגון פסלונים, נרות חרס מעוטרים, קופסאות מקושטות, מטבעות ומדליות שעליהן חקוק תבליט וכדומה. על פי רוב, אלו הם חפצים בעלי שימוש ולא נועדו רק לקישוט. כיום, המחקר מגדיר חפצים כאלו כשייכים לתחום העיצוב. ההבחנה בין פיסול אנדרטאות לפיסול היא מסובכת ובעייתית יותר, כיוון שההפרדה בין תחומים אלו מטושטשת כיום לחלוטין. הבחנה נוספת הקיימת בחקר הפיסול הקלאסי היא בין פסל, החופשי מכל עבריו, לבין תבליט, הצמוד לאלמנט אדריכלי.במהלך המאה ה-20 השתנתה באופן רדיקלי הגדרתו של מדיום הפיסול, עם כניסתן של טכניקות חדשות כגון וידאו ארט, רדי מייד, אמנות אדמה, מיצג, מיצב וכדומה. לצד השינוי המושגי שהתחולל, התלווה אל התהליך גם מהפך בתדמיתו החזותית של הפיסול - מדימוי של אובייקט בודד העשוי מאבנים חצובות, מתכת או עץ, הפך הפסל למגוון של אובייקטים העשויים מחומרים שונים ואף משילוב של חומרים וטכניקות, שינוי שערער על תחושת ה"נצחיות" של הפיסול הקלאסי.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="tr">Heykel, sanatsal bakış açısıyla meydana getirilmiş üç boyutlu formlara denir. Heykel temelde mekânın kapsanması, kavranması ve mekân ile ilişki kurulması ile ilgilenir.Genellikle insan, hayvan ya da nesnelerin heykelleri yapılır. Taş ve ahşap gibi malzemelerden yontularak yapılabileceği gibi, kil, balmumu gibi ara malzemelerden modellenerek, bronz ve tunç gibi metallerden dökülebilir. Büst, rölyef ve tors gibi heykel türleri vardır.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="nl">Beeldhouwkunst is een van de beeldende kunsten.In het algemeen verstaat men onder beeldhouwkunst ruimtelijke kunstwerken zoals portretten, bustes, standbeelden, beeldengroepen en torso's. Beeldhouwwerken worden bijvoorbeeld door een beeldhouwer gemaakt van materialen als brons, smeedijzer, beton, klei, was, gips, of door een steenbeeldhouwer uit natuursteensoorten als marmer, graniet en zandsteen.</skos:note><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ml.dbpedia.org/resource/ശില്പകല"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cy.dbpedia.org/resource/Cerfluniaeth"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://wikidata.dbpedia.org/resource/Q11634"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://war.dbpedia.org/resource/Iskultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://zh.dbpedia.org/resource/雕塑"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pt.dbpedia.org/resource/Escultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ro.dbpedia.org/resource/Sculptură"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://is.dbpedia.org/resource/Höggmyndalist"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lt.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptūra"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sh.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sw.dbpedia.org/resource/Uchongaji"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nap.dbpedia.org/resource/Scultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sk.dbpedia.org/resource/Sochárstvo"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hi.dbpedia.org/resource/मूर्ति_कला"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sr.dbpedia.org/resource/Вајарство"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fi.dbpedia.org/resource/Kuvanveisto"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tr.dbpedia.org/resource/Heykel"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://qu.dbpedia.org/resource/Ch'iquy"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pnb.dbpedia.org/resource/بتی_بنانا"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ko.dbpedia.org/resource/조각"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://it.dbpedia.org/resource/Scultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://arz.dbpedia.org/resource/نحت"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://vi.dbpedia.org/resource/Điêu_khắc"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://scn.dbpedia.org/resource/Scultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://io.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulto"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ia.dbpedia.org/resource/Sculptura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bs.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ta.dbpedia.org/resource/சிற்பம்"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ka.dbpedia.org/resource/ქანდაკება"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://he.dbpedia.org/resource/פיסול"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://an.dbpedia.org/resource/Escultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hr.dbpedia.org/resource/Kiparstvo"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nn.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptur"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fa.dbpedia.org/resource/تندیس‌گری"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://id.dbpedia.org/resource/Seni_pahat"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://si.dbpedia.org/resource/මූර්ති_ශිල්පය"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ckb.dbpedia.org/resource/پەیکەرتاشی"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tl.dbpedia.org/resource/Panlililok"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://rdf.freebase.com/ns/m.06msq"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pl.dbpedia.org/resource/Rzeźba"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://la.dbpedia.org/resource/Sculptura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uk.dbpedia.org/resource/Скульптура"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ur.dbpedia.org/resource/بت_تراشی"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://my.dbpedia.org/resource/ပန်းပု"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fr.dbpedia.org/resource/Sculpture"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://als.dbpedia.org/resource/Bildhauerei"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bg.dbpedia.org/resource/Скулптура"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sv.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptur"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://br.dbpedia.org/resource/Kizellañ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ru.dbpedia.org/resource/Скульптура"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://es.dbpedia.org/resource/Escultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nl.dbpedia.org/resource/Beeldhouwkunst"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ar.dbpedia.org/resource/نحت"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sl.dbpedia.org/resource/Kiparstvo"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ast.dbpedia.org/resource/Escultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://oc.dbpedia.org/resource/Escultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://te.dbpedia.org/resource/శిల్పం"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hy.dbpedia.org/resource/Քանդակագործություն"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://kn.dbpedia.org/resource/ಮೂರ್ತಿಶಿಲ್ಪ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ky.dbpedia.org/resource/Скульптура"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eo.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptarto"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://da.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptur"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mk.dbpedia.org/resource/Вајарство"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hu.dbpedia.org/resource/Szobrászat"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://el.dbpedia.org/resource/Γλυπτική"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://th.dbpedia.org/resource/ประติมากรรม"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ca.dbpedia.org/resource/Escultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mr.dbpedia.org/resource/शिल्पकला"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://de.dbpedia.org/resource/Bildhauerkunst"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uz.dbpedia.org/resource/Haykaltaroshlik"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ga.dbpedia.org/resource/Dealbhóireacht"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://simple.dbpedia.org/resource/Sculpture"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://vec.dbpedia.org/resource/Scultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://az.dbpedia.org/resource/Heykəl"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://et.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptuur"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://yi.dbpedia.org/resource/סקולפטור"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eu.dbpedia.org/resource/Eskulturagintza"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q11634"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://gl.dbpedia.org/resource/Escultura"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://be.dbpedia.org/resource/Скульптура"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cs.dbpedia.org/resource/Sochařství"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bn.dbpedia.org/resource/ভাস্কর্য"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fy.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptuer"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://kk.dbpedia.org/resource/Мүсіндеме"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lv.dbpedia.org/resource/Tēlniecība"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://wa.dbpedia.org/resource/Scultreye"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ja.dbpedia.org/resource/彫刻"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://no.dbpedia.org/resource/Skulptur"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Sculpture"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Carving"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Sculpture"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Sculptures_by_medium"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Sculpture_techniques"/></skos:Concept><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><edm:dataProvider>UCD Library</edm:dataProvider><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="https://digital.ucd.ie/view/ivrla:6962"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="https://iiif.ucd.ie/loris/ivrla:6963/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="https://iiif.ucd.ie/loris/ivrla:6963/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:provider>University College Dublin</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"/></ore:Aggregation><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/provider/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"><dc:description xml:lang="en">Physical location: UCD Library, UCD Library Special Collections, Curran Collection - Photographs, CUR P 19</dc:description><dc:description xml:lang="en">Photographer unknown.</dc:description><dc:format xml:lang="en">1 photograph</dc:format><dc:identifier>EADseries:IVRLA14:18</dc:identifier><dc:identifier>https://data.ucd.ie/data/ivrla:6962</dc:identifier><dc:identifier>https://digital.ucd.ie/view/ivrla:6962</dc:identifier><dc:language>en</dc:language><dc:rights rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"></dc:rights><dc:rights>Use of this resource is governed by the Creative Commons - Attribution, Non-Commercial, ShareAlike (BY-NC-SA) license.</dc:rights><dc:rights xml:lang="en">© University College Dublin, National University of Ireland, Dublin. Copyright and reproduction rights for this digital resource are held by University College Dublin and administered by UCD Library Special Collections, UCD James Joyce Library, Belfield, Dublin 4, Ireland.</dc:rights><dc:rights xml:lang="en">To use for commercial purposes, please contact the UCD Digital Library</dc:rights><dc:rights xml:lang="en">Suggested credit: "Photograph of the sculptor Albert Power working on a bust of James Stephens," held by UCD Library Special Collections. © University College Dublin. Digital content: © University College Dublin, published by UCD Library, University College Dublin &amp;lt;http://digital.ucd.ie/view/ivrla:6962&amp;gt;</dc:rights><dc:source xml:lang="en">UCD Library, University College Dublin</dc:source><dc:subject rdf:resource="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm009291"></dc:subject><dc:subject rdf:resource="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127595#concept"></dc:subject><dc:subject rdf:resource="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm006699"></dc:subject><dc:subject rdf:resource="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm009290"></dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Stephens, James, 1882-1950</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Power, Albert, 1881-1945</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Stephens, James, 1882-1950--Statues</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Sculpture</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Statues</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Modeling (sculpture)</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Sculptors</dc:subject><dc:title xml:lang="en">Photograph of the sculptor Albert Power working on a bust of James Stephens.</dc:title><dc:type rdf:resource="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/graphicMaterials/tgm007721"></dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">still image</dc:type><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="https://data.ucd.ie/data/ivrla:6922"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:europeanaProxy>false</edm:europeanaProxy><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></ore:Proxy><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/europeana/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"><dc:subject rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/51"></dc:subject><edm:europeanaProxy>true</edm:europeanaProxy><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><edm:type>IMAGE</edm:type></ore:Proxy><edm:EuropeanaAggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><edm:datasetName>2064501_Ag_IRE_UCD_IIIF</edm:datasetName><edm:country>Europe</edm:country><edm:preview rdf:resource="https://api.europeana.eu/thumbnail/v2/url.json?uri=https%3A%2F%2Fiiif.ucd.ie%2Floris%2Fivrla%3A6963%2Ffull%2Ffull%2F0%2Fdefault.jpg&amp;type=IMAGE"/><edm:landingPage rdf:resource="https://www.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><edm:language>mul</edm:language><edm:completeness>0</edm:completeness><dcterms:created>2016-11-01T11:42:01.537Z</dcterms:created><dcterms:modified>2017-08-25T10:16:51.799Z</dcterms:modified><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962#contentTier"/><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962#metadataTier"/></edm:EuropeanaAggregation><svcs:Service rdf:about="https://iiif.ucd.ie/loris/ivrla:6963"><dcterms:conformsTo rdf:resource="http://iiif.io/api/image"></dcterms:conformsTo><doap:implements rdf:resource="http://iiif.io/api/image/2/level2.json"/></svcs:Service><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962#contentTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-17T09:52:50.997Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/contentTier3"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962#metadataTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-17T09:52:50.997Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/2064501/https___data_ucd_ie_data_ivrla_6962"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/metadataTierA"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation></rdf:RDF>