<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:owl="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#" xmlns:wgs84_pos="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:rdaGr2="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:ebucore="http://www.ebu.ch/metadata/ontologies/ebucore/ebucore#" xmlns:doap="http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#" xmlns:odrl="http://www.w3.org/ns/odrl/2/" xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:svcs="http://rdfs.org/sioc/services#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:dqv="http://www.w3.org/ns/dqv#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449"/><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/173449"><rdf:type rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/FullTextResource"/><ebucore:hasMimeType>text/html</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">160271</ebucore:fileByteSize></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pageimage/46085682"/><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.archive.org/download/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL.pdf"><ebucore:hasMimeType>application/pdf</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">10882509</ebucore:fileByteSize></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"><ebucore:hasMimeType>image/jpeg</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">245012</ebucore:fileByteSize><ebucore:width rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">1321</ebucore:width><ebucore:height rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">1414</ebucore:height><edm:hasColorSpace>sRGB</edm:hasColorSpace><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#D3D3D3</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#F5DEB3</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#FFE4C4</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#DCDCDC</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#000000</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#C0C0C0</edm:componentColor><ebucore:orientation rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#string">portrait</ebucore:orientation><dcterms:isReferencedBy rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL/manifest.json"></dcterms:isReferencedBy><svcs:has_service rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL"/></edm:WebResource><edm:Agent rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/agent/base/25274"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Charles Edward Faxon</skos:prefLabel><skos:altLabel xml:lang="en">Faxon, Charles Edward</skos:altLabel><edm:end>1918-02-06</edm:end><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="en">Charles Edward Faxon (January 21, 1846 – February 6, 1918) was an American botanical artist and instructor of botany born in Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts.In 1867 he received his degree in civil engineering from Lawrence Scientific School in Cambridge. From 1879 to 1884, he taught classes in botany at the Bussey Institute.Faxon was knowledgeable in regards to the flora of New England, and in 1882 joined the staff at the Arnold Arboretum. Here he took charge of development of the herbarium and library. He worked closely with Charles Sprague Sargent (1841-1927), the director of the arboretum.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:dateOfBirth>1846-01-21</rdaGr2:dateOfBirth><rdaGr2:dateOfDeath>1918-02-06</rdaGr2:dateOfDeath><rdaGr2:placeOfBirth rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Jamaica_Plain"></rdaGr2:placeOfBirth><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://wikidata.dbpedia.org/resource/Q5077268"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://yago-knowledge.org/resource/Charles_Edward_Faxon"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://rdf.freebase.com/ns/m.04yfgg1"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5077268"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Charles_Edward_Faxon"/></edm:Agent><edm:Agent rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/agent/base/60779"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Рёскин, Джон</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="be">Джон Раскін</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pt">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lv">Džons Raskins</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hr">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="uk">Джон Раскін</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ka">ჯონ რესკინი</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sk">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sr">Џон Раскин</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sv">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ko">존 러스킨</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gl">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">Τζον Ράσκιν</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="es">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="zh">约翰·拉斯金</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cs">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="eu">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ar">جون راسكن</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cy">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ja">ジョン・ラスキン</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="az">Con Raskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pl">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="he">ג'ון ראסקין</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ro">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="tr">John Ruskin</skos:prefLabel><skos:altLabel xml:lang="en">Ruskin, John</skos:altLabel><dc:identifier>73859585</dc:identifier><edm:end>1900-01-20</edm:end><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="de">John Ruskin (* 8. Februar 1819 in London; † 20. Januar 1900 in Brantwood, Lake District in Cumbria) war ein britischer Schriftsteller, Maler, Kunsthistoriker und Sozialphilosoph.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="no">John Ruskin (8. februar 1819 – 20. januar 1900) var dominerende skikkelse og den ledende engelske kunstkritikeren i viktoriansk tid. Han tillegg var han beskytter av kunsten, tegner, akvarellmaler, en prominent sosial tenker og filantrop. Han skrev om emner som strakte seg geologi til arkitektur, myter til ornitologi, litteratur til utdannelse, botanikk til politisk økonomi, og andre emner. Hans skrivestil og litterære former varierte tilsvarende. Ruskin skrev essayer og avhandlinger, poesi og forelesninger, reiseguider og manualer, brev og selv et eventyr. Hans detaljerte stil som preget hans tidligste skrifter om kun ble senere fortrengt av forkjærlighet av et enklere og bedre språk formet for å kommunisere sine tanker mer effektivt. I alt han skrev, framhevet han forbindelsen mellom natur, kunst og samfunn. Han gjorde også detaljerte skisser og malerier av fjell, berg, planter, fugler, landskap, og arkitektoniske strukturer og ornamentering.Han hadde en særdeles stor innflytelse i løpet av den siste halvdelen av 1800-tallet og fram til den første verdenskrig. Deretter, etter en periode av relativ nedgang, har hans omdømme bedret seg jevnlig siden 1960-tallet med utgivelsen av tallrike akademiske undersøkelser av hans forfatterskap. I dag er hans tanker og interesser i stor grad anerkjent for å ha bidratt til å ha foregrepet interessen for økologi og bærekraftig utvikling, foruten framheve håndverksmessig dyktighet.Ruskin fikk først omfattende oppmerksomhet med det første bindet av Modern Painters (1843), et omfattende essay i forsvar for kunstverkene til J.M.W. Turner hvor han argumenterte at kunstnerens fremste rolle er å være «sannferdig overfor naturen». Fra 1850-tallet var han en forkjemper Det prerafaelittiske broderskap, som på sin side ble preget av hans tanker. Ruskins tekster og utgivelser fokuserte i økende grad på sosiale og politiske emner. Unto This Last (1860, 1862) markerte en endring av fokus. Det var et langt essay om økonomi som blant annet ble viktig for Gandhis tenkning. I 1869 ble Ruskin den første Slade-professor i kunst ved Universitetet i Oxford hvor han etablerte en egen tegneskole, Ruskin School of Drawing. I 1871 begynte han med månedlige «brev til arbeidere i Storbritannia», utgitt under tittelen Fors Clavigera (1871–1884). I løpet av dette komplekse og dypt personlige verket utviklet han prinsippene for sin oppfatning av det ideelle samfunn. Som er resultat grunnla han Guild of St George, en organisasjon som består den dag i dag.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ru">Джон Рёскин (также Ра́скин, англ. John Ruskin; 8 февраля 1819, Лондон — 20 января 1900, Брентвуд) — английский писатель, художник, теоретик искусства, литературный критик и поэт; член Арундельского общества. Оказал большое влияние на развитие искусствознания и эстетики второй половины XIX — начала XX века.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="be">Джон Раскін (англ.: John Ruskin) (8 лютага 1819 — 20 студзеня 1900) — брытанскі крытык, пісьменнік, мастак, тэарэтык архітэктуры і грамадскі дзеяч.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="fi">John Ruskin (8. helmikuuta 1819 – 20. tammikuuta 1900) oli englantilainen kirjailija, runoilija, taidemaalari ja taidekriitikko.Ruskin oli sherrytehtailijan poika, ja hän syntyi Lontoossa ja suoritti opintonsa Oxfordissa. Omaisuutensa ansiosta hän saattoi vierailla ympäri Eurooppaa olevissa museoissa opiskellen maalaustaidetta.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="pt">John Ruskin (Londres, 8 de fevereiro de 1819 – 20 de janeiro de 1900) foi um escritor mais lembrado por seu trabalho como crítico de arte e crítico social británico. Foi também poeta e desenhista. Os ensaios de Ruskin sobre arte e arquitetura foram extremamente influentes na era Vitoriana, repercutindo até hoje.O pensamento de Ruskin vincula-se ao Romantismo, movimento literário e ideológico (final do século XVIII até meado do século XIX), e que dá ênfase a sensibilidade subjetiva e emotiva em contraponto com a razão. Esteticamente, Ruskin apresenta-se como reação ao Classicismo e com admiração ao medievalismo. Na sua definição de restauração dos patrimônios históricos, considerava a real destruição daquilo que não se pode salvar, nem a mínima parte, uma destruição acompanhada de uma falsa descrição.A partir de 1851, foi um defensor inicial e patrono da Irmandade Pré-Rafaelita, inspirando a criação do movimento Arts &amp; Crafts.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="lv">Džons Raskins (angļu: John Ruskin, dzimis 1819. gada 8. februārī, miris 1900. gada 20. janvārī) bija angļu mākslas un sociālais kritiķis, rakstnieks un dzejnieks. Viens no ietekmīgākajiem Viktorijas un Edvarda laika kritiķiem. Viens no prerafaelītu atbalstītājiem.Dzimis Londonā, vīna tirgotāja ģimenē. Mācījās Oksfordas universitātē. 1843. gadā ar pseidonīmu An Oxford Graduate publicēja darbu "Mūsdienu gleznotāji" (Modern Painters), kurā pauda atbalstu toreizējai glezniecībai, sevišķi Džozefa Tērnera vēlīnajiem darbiem. Vēlāk publicēja ietekmīgus darbus arhitektūras teorijā. 1848. gadā Raskins aprecējās ar Efiju Greju (Effie Gray), tomēr laulība bija nelaimīga, un vēlāk Greja apprecējās ar Raskina protežē - gleznotāju Džonu Everetu Milē, izraisot skandālu. Milē kopā ar Viljamu Holmenu Hantu un Danti Gabrielu Roseti 1848. gadā bija nodibinājuši Prerafaelītu brālību, kuru finansiāli un morāli atbalstīja Raskins.XIX gadsimta otrajā pusē Raskins pameta mākslas kritiku un vairāk pievērsās sociālajiem jautājumiem, ietekmējoties no sava drauga Tomasa Kārlaila. Raskins nodibināja labdarības fondu. Dzīves nogalē cieta no garīgiem traucējumiem. 1858. gadā Raskins iepazinās ar deviņgadīgo, saasināti reliģiozo Rozu la Taču (Rose la Touche), kurā, pēc paša vārdiem, iemīlējies, un, kad viņai palika sešpadsmit, bildināja, tomēr meitene atteicās. Daži biogrāfi (piemēram, Tim Hilton, John Ruskin: The Early Years, Yale University Press, 1985) definē, ka seksuālo noslieču ziņā Raskins bija pedofils.Ietekmējis Ļeva Tolstoja, Marsela Prusta, Mahatmas Gandija un Oskara Vailda uzskatus.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="hr">John Ruskin (London, 8. veljače 1819. - Coniston, 20. siječnja 1900.), britanski estetičar i sociolog.Bio je profesor na Oxfordu, a umjetnošću se oduševio na putovanjima po Italiji. Za njega su "lijepo, istinito i dobro" istoznačni pojmovi. Težnja za ljepotom na svim područjima života navodi ga na stvaranje utopističkih planova o novom društvenom poretku. Oštro se suprotstavio svijetu tehničke civilizacije. Nadovezao se na shvaćanje romantičarskog pokreta, uz pokušaj njihova usklađivanja s modernim shvaćanjem života. 1869. postao je profesorom povijesti umjetnosti na Oxfordu. Nedovršeni članak John Ruskin koji govori o znanstveniku treba dopuniti. Dopunite ga prema pravilima Wikipedije.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="fr">John Ruskin, né le 8 février 1819 à Bloomsbury en Londres, mort le 20 janvier 1900 à Coniston (Cumbrie) est un écrivain, poète, peintre et critique d'art britannique.Fils unique d'une riche famille, il fut éduqué à domicile, avec une insistance particulière sur l'art et la religion. Il poursuivit son éducation en dilettante, en tant qu'auditeur libre à Oxford. Malgré des problèmes de santé, il y obtint son MA en 1843. Surtout, il s'y lia d'amitié avec nombre d'intellectuels.Il fut publié dès son adolescence. Grâce à la fortune de sa famille, il put consacrer sa vie à l'écriture. Il devint rapidement célèbre dans les années 1840 grâce à son travail de critique Modern Painters (1843 à 1860) où il proposait une nouvelle façon d'appréhender l'art. Il écrivit ensuite The Seven Lamps of Architecture en 1849 et surtout The Stones of Venice en 1853. Il fit aussi passer ses idées par l'enseignement. Il participa à la création de l'University Museum, donna des cours de dessin au Working Men's College, un établissement de formation continue fondé par ses amis socialistes chrétiens. Il en donna aussi dans une école pour jeunes filles et par correspondance. En 1870, il devint le premier titulaire de la chaire Slade à Oxford.Son mariage avec Effie Gray annulé pour non-consommation continue à alimenter de nos jours des légendes nombreuses et variées, des suppositions. Effie épousa très vite le peintre John Everett Millais, un membre du mouvement préraphaélite dont Ruskin fut le mécène et le soutien après s'être engagé pour Turner.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="hu">John Ruskin (London, 1819. február 8. – Coniston, Anglia, 1900. január 20.) angol művészeti író, festő és esztéta. A modern kortárs művészek pártfogója.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="uk">Джон Раскін (англ. John Ruskin; * 8 лютого 1819, Лондон — † 20 січня 1900, Брентвуд) — англійський письменник, теоретик мистецтва, літературний критик і поет, який значно вплинув на розвиток мистецтвознавства та естетики другої половини XIX — початку XX століття.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ka">ჯონ რესკინი (ინგლ. John Ruskin; დ. 8 თებერვალი, 1819 – გ. 20 იანვარი, 1900) — ინგლისელი მწერალი, ხელოვნების თეორეტიკოსი. რესკინის რომანტიკულმა პროტესტმა თანამედროვე საზოგადოების მიმართ განაპირობა მის მიერ შუა საუკუნეების სტილისტიკური და მხატვრული ფორმების აღორძინების მცდელობა. იგი იყო პრერაფაელიტების საძმოს იდეოლოგი. რესკინის პროზაული და პოეტური ნაწარმოებები გამოირჩევიან დახვეწილი სამწერლო და პოეტური ტექნიკით, უზადო სტილითა და თხრობის თავისებური მანერით.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="sk">John Ruskin (* 8. február 1819, Londýn, Spojené kráľovstvo – † 20. január 1900, Brantwood) bol anglický spisovateľ, básnik, vedec a umelecký kritik.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ca">John Ruskin (Londres, 8 de febrer de 1819 - Brantwood, 20 de gener de 1900) fou un escriptor, crític d'art i sociòleg britànic, un dels grans mestres de la prosa anglesa.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="sr">Џон Раскин (енгл. John Ruskin; Лондон, 8. фебруар 1819 — Брентвуд, 20. јануар 1900) је био енглески сликар и критичар уметности. Мада је усавршавао сопствене сликарске способности пре свега сликање акварела био је ипак пре свега теоретичар који се са посебним афинитетом бавио сликарством пејзажа и средњовековном архитектуром. Раскин се заузимао за прерафаелите као и за Вилијама Тарнера и имао је великог утицаја на покрет Arts and Crafts и на Modern style. У периоду од 1869. до 1884. године радио је као професор историје уметности на Оксфорду.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="sv">John Ruskin, född 8 februari 1819 i Bloomsbury, London, död 20 januari 1900 i Coniston, Cumbria, var en engelsk konstkritiker, poet och författare. Ruskin innehade en professur i konst vid universitetet i Oxford, där han själv var utbildad. Han hade tidigare varit anställd på Working Men's College i London, och det var under denna tid som han antog tidiga socialistiska idéer. Vid Oxford mötte han William Turner, vilken han själv givit berömmelse åt genom sin bok Modern Painters. Tillsammans med bland andra Rossetti, Millais och Hunt skapade Ruskin rörelsen prerafaeliterna, som syftade till ett antiindustriellt återtåg till hantverket och de estetiska värden som låg i detta. Hans idéer togs upp och fullföljdes av William Morris. Mot slutet av sitt liv propagerade Ruskin, som var en förmögen man, för att man inte kunde vara socialist och rik på samma gång. Han gav bort stora summor pengar till bland annat olika utbildningsanstalter.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ko">존 러스킨(John Ruskin, 1819년 2월 8일 ~ 1900년 1월 20일)은 영국의 사회 비평가이다. 화려한 예술비평가의 길과 험난한 사회사상가의 길을 차례로 걸었던 19세기 영국의 저명한 지식인이다.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="gl">John Ruskin, nado en Londres o 8 de febreiro de 1819 e finado en Brantwood o 20 de xaneiro de 1900, foi un escritor, crítico de arte e sociólogo británico, un dos grandes mestres da prosa inglesa.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="el">Ο Τζον Ράσκιν (John Ruskin:, Λονδίνο 8 Φεβρουαρίου 1819 - 20 Ιανουαρίου 1900), ήταν Άγγλος συγγραφέας, ζωγράφος και κριτικός τέχνης. Συνέγραψε μεταξύ άλλων τα βιβλία: Modern Painters (1843), (δουλειά που υποστήριζε θερμά τη τέχνη του Τέρνερ), The Seven Lamps Οf Architecture (1848), The Stones of Venice (1851-53), εργασίες που ανέδειξαν το κριτικό βάθος του πνεύματός του κι επηρέασαν τη μετέπειτα Βικτωριανή Τέχνη. Υποστήριξε θερμά τους καλλιτέχνες της Προ-Ραφαηλικής Περιόδου (Μιλέ, Χαντ, Ροσσέτι).Από το 1867 κι ύστερα, πήρε έδρα Λέκτορος στο Πανεπιστήμιο του Καίμπριτζ και μεταξύ 1869-84, δίδαξε ως Εξειδικευμένος Καθηγητής στο Ίδρυμα Καλών Τεχνών Οξφόρδης. Ίδρυσε Σχολή Καλών Τεχνών &amp; Μουσείο στην Οξφόρδη, καθώς επίσης και Νυχτερινή Σχολή Καλών Τεχνών στο Μήρσμπρουκ για τους εκεί εργαζόμενους ναυτικούς.Οι υδατογραφίες κι οι πίνακές του εκτέθηκαν μεταξύ 1873-84 στο Old Water-Color Society. Η ατμοσφαιρική Αλπική θέα-ματιά του στον πίνακα Σαμονί αποτίει φόρο τιμής στον αγαπημένο του Τέρνερ.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="en">John Ruskin (8 February 1819 – 20 January 1900) was the leading English art critic of the Victorian era, also an art patron, draughtsman, watercolourist, a prominent social thinker and philanthropist. He wrote on subjects ranging from geology to architecture, myth to ornithology, literature to education, and botany to political economy. His writing styles and literary forms were equally varied. Ruskin penned essays and treatises, poetry and lectures, travel guides and manuals, letters and even a fairy tale. The elaborate style that characterised his earliest writing on art was later superseded by a preference for plainer language designed to communicate his ideas more effectively. In all of his writing, he emphasised the connections between nature, art and society. He also made detailed sketches and paintings of rocks, plants, birds, landscapes, and architectural structures and ornamentation.He was hugely influential in the latter half of the 19th century, and up to the First World War. After a period of relative decline, his reputation has steadily improved since the 1960s with the publication of numerous academic studies of his work. Today, his ideas and concerns are widely recognised as having anticipated interest in environmentalism, sustainability and craft.Ruskin first came to widespread attention with the first volume of Modern Painters (1843), an extended essay in defence of the work of J. M. W. Turner in which he argued that the principal role of the artist is "truth to nature". From the 1850s he championed the Pre-Raphaelites who were influenced by his ideas. His work increasingly focused on social and political issues. Unto This Last (1860, 1862) marked the shift in emphasis. In 1869, Ruskin became the first Slade Professor of Fine Art at the University of Oxford, where he established the Ruskin School of Drawing. In 1871, he began his monthly "letters to the workmen and labourers of Great Britain", published under the title Fors Clavigera (1871–1884). In the course of this complex and deeply personal work, he developed the principles underlying his ideal society. As a result, he founded the Guild of St George, an organisation that endures today.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="it">John Ruskin (Londra, 8 febbraio 1819 – Brantwood, 20 gennaio 1900) è stato uno scrittore, pittore, poeta e critico d'arte britannico.La sua interpretazione dell'arte e dell'architettura influenzarono fortemente l'estetica vittoriana ed edoardiana.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="es">John Ruskin (Londres, 8 de febrero de 1819 - Brantwood, 20 de enero de 1900) fue un escritor, crítico de arte y sociólogo británico, uno de los grandes maestros de la prosa inglesa. Influyó notablemente en Mahatma Gandhi. Abogó por un socialismo cristiano.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="zh">约翰·拉斯金（John Ruskin，1819年2月8日－1900年1月20日）是英国维多利亚时代主要的艺术评论家之一，他还是一名艺术赞助家、制图师、水粉画家、和杰出的社会思想家及慈善家。他写作的题材涵盖从地质到建筑、从神话到鸟类学、从文学到教育、从园艺学到政治经济学包罗万象。他的写作风格和体裁同样多变。拉斯金写过从随笔到专著、从诗歌到演讲、从旅行指南到说明书、书信甚至到童话。在他所有的作品中，他无一不在强调自然、艺术和社会之间的联系。1843年，他因《现代画家》（Modern Painters）一书而成名，书中，他高度赞扬约瑟夫·玛罗德·威廉·透纳的绘画创作。这以及其后的写作总计39卷，使他成为维多利亚时代艺术趣味的代言人。他是前拉斐尔派的一员，本身亦为天才而多产的艺术家。</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="cs">John Ruskin (8. února 1819, Londýn – 20. ledna 1900, Brantwood) byl anglický spisovatel, básník, vědec a umělecký kritik.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="eu">John Ruskin (Londres, Ingalaterra, 1819 - Brantwood, Cumberland, Ingalaterra, 1900) ingelesezko idazlea, arte-kritikaria, historialaria eta soziologoa izan zen. William Turner ingeles pintorearen eta prerrafaelisten aldeko agertu zen Modern Painters (1843-1860, Pintore modernoak, bost liburuki) obra handian. Estetikari buruz zituen ikuspegiak The Seven Lamps of Architecture (1849, Arkitekturaren zazpi puntuak) eta The Stones of Venice (1851-1853, Veneziako harriak, hiru liburuki) obretan azaldu zituen. Ingalaterrako langileentzako gutun politikoak idatzi zituen (1871-1887, Fors Clavigera), eta amaitu gabe utzi zuen autobiografia bat (1885-1889, Praeterita). Oxfordeko Unibertsitateko arte-saileko irakasle izan zen 1869-1879 eta 1883-1884 urteetan. Gizarte modernoak eragiten dituen arazoak aztertu zituen ondorengo lanetan: The Two Paths (1859, Bi bideak), Sesame and Lilies (1865, Sesamo eta loreak) eta The Crown of Wild Olive (1866, Oihaneko olibondoaren koroa). Obra sozialetan ahitu zuen bere dirutza.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ar">«« لا يمكن للعالم ان يصبح كله ورشة عمل، لانه بتعلم فن الحياة، سوف تجد في نهاية المطاف أن كل الأشياء الجميلة كانت ضرورية »»جون راسكن (8 فبراير 1819- 20 يناير 1900) كان شاعراً إنجليزياً و ناقداً فنياً ومفكراً اجتماعياً, وله العديد من المؤلفات والأعمال الأدبية والفنية, وقد كان لكتاباته وفنه أثر كبير في العصر الفكتوري و العصر الإدواردي. وقد حاز راسكن على شهرة واسعة بعد أن قدم دعمه لأعمال جي. إم. دبليو تيرنر ومنافحته عن المذهب الطبيعي في الفن. كانت كتاباته الاجتماعية الدقيقة التي تناولت الارتباطات بين القضايا الاجتماعية والأخلاقية والثقافية والتي كان لها أثر في تطور الاشتراكية المسيحية. .تفسيره للفن والهندسة المعمارية أثر كبيرا على جماليات العصور الفيكتوري والإدواردي.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="cy">Beirniad celf a meddyliwr cymdeithasol Seisnig oedd John Ruskin (8 Chwefror 1819 – 20 Ionawr 1900), a gaiff ei gofio hefyd fel bardd ac arlunydd. Bu ei draethodau ar gelf a pensaerniaeth yn ddylanwadol iawn yn yr Oesoedd Fictoraidd ac Edwardaidd.Daeth Ruskin yn adnabyddadwy yn gyffredinol am y tro cyntaf am ei gefnogaeth o waith yr arlunydd J. M. W. Turner a'i amddiffyniaeth o naturoliaeth mewn celf. Ar ôl hynny rhoddodd bwysau ei ddylanwad tu ôl i'r symudiad Cyn-Raffaelaidd. Trodd ei lên diweddarach tuag at archwiliadau o faterion cymleth a phersonol diwylliant, cymdeithas a moesoldeb, a bu'n ddylanwadol yn natblygaeth Sosialaeth Cristnogol.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ja">ジョン・ラスキン（John Ruskin, 1819年2月8日 - 1900年1月20日）は、19世紀イギリス・ヴィクトリア時代を代表するの評論家・美術評論家である。同時に芸術家のパトロンであり、設計製図や水彩画をこなし、社会思想家であり、篤志家であった。ターナーやラファエル前派と交友を持ち、『近代画家論』を著した。また、中世のゴシック美術を賛美する『建築の七燈』『ヴェニスの石』などを執筆した。</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="az">Con Raskin(8 fevral 1819 - 20 yanvar 1900) — Viktoriya dövründə qabaqcıl ingilis sənətşünas həm də sənət patronu, dizayner, suluboya rəssamı, görkəmli ictimai mütəfəkkir və xeyriyyəçi idi. O geologiyadan memarlıqa, mifdən ornitologiyaya, ədəbiyyatdan təhsilə və botanikadan siyasi iqtisadiyyata qədər dəyişən mövzularda yazmışdır.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="pl">John Ruskin (ur. 8 lutego 1819 w Londynie, zm. 20 stycznia 1900 w Brantwood) był angielskim pisarzem, poetą i artystą, jednak najbardziej znany jest jako krytyk sztuki i krytyk społeczny. Jego książka Współcześni malarze (Modern Painters) przyczyniła się do popularności malarza Williama Turnera i ruchu prerafaelitów.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="he">ג'ון ראסקין (John Ruskin;‏8 בפברואר 1819 - 20 בינואר 1900), מבקר אמנות ותרבות, סוציאליסט מוקדם ומבקר חברתי אנגלי. מחשובי מבקרי האמנות בתקופה הוויקטוריאנית. עסק גם בציור, ספרות ושירה.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="da">John Ruskin (8. februar 1819 – 20. januar 1900) var en engelsk kunstkritiker og socialkritisk forfatter. Han gjorde sig også bemærket som kunstner og poet. Ruskins mange essay om kunst og arkitektur fik stor betydning i victoriatidens England. Ruskin havde et professorat i kunst ved universitetet i Oxford, hvor han selv havde fået sin uddannelse. Han havde tidligere arbejdet ved Working Men's College i London, og det var i denne tid han udviklede sine tidlige socialistiske idéer. Ved Oxford mødte han maleren William Turner som han bidrog til at gøre berømt gennem bogværket Modern Painters.Ruskin var en vigtig talsmand for den præ-rafaelittiske kunstbevægelsen i England, og han var central i udviklingen af The Arts and Crafts Movement i 1800-tallet.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ro">John Ruskin (n. 8 februarie 1819, Londra - d. 20 ianuarie 1900, Brantwood/Lancashire) a fost un scriitor, critic de artă și filozof englez. Ruskin a exercitat o remarcabilă influență asupra cercurilor intelectuale ale Angliei din epoca victoriană. A devenit cunoscut mai ales prin studiile sale aprofundate asupra arhitecturii și artelor plastice în general și asupra condițiilor istorice și sociale corespunzătoare. Ruskin consideră că cele mai remarcabile realizări ale artei trecutului sunt legate de existența unor condiții favorabile în societate și afirmă că numai o societate nobilă poate genera o artă de înaltă elevație spirituală.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="nl">John Ruskin (Londen, 8 februari 1819 - Brantwood (Lancashire), 20 januari 1900) was een Engels criticus die vooral bekend werd door zijn werk als kunstcriticus en sociaalcriticus, maar ook herinnerd wordt als schrijver, dichter en kunstschilder. Ruskins essays over kunst en architectuur waren zeer invloedrijk in het Victoriaanse tijdperk en het Edwardiaanse tijdperk.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="tr">John Ruskin, (d. 8 Şubat 1819 – ö. 20 Ocak 1900) XIX. yüzyılda yaşamış İngiliz yazar, şair, sanat ve toplum eleştirmenidir.Londra'da doğmuş güney Londra'da yetişmiş sonradan adı Allied Domecq olan şarap ithalatçısı şirketin kurucusu olan John James Ruskin'nin oğludur. Evde eğitim almıştır.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:dateOfBirth>1819-02-08</rdaGr2:dateOfBirth><rdaGr2:dateOfDeath>1900-01-20</rdaGr2:dateOfDeath><rdaGr2:placeOfBirth rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/London"></rdaGr2:placeOfBirth><rdaGr2:placeOfBirth rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Brunswick_Square"></rdaGr2:placeOfBirth><rdaGr2:placeOfBirth>54</rdaGr2:placeOfBirth><rdaGr2:placeOfBirth rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/England"></rdaGr2:placeOfBirth><rdaGr2:placeOfDeath rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Brantwood"></rdaGr2:placeOfDeath><rdaGr2:placeOfDeath rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Coniston,_Cumbria"></rdaGr2:placeOfDeath><rdaGr2:placeOfDeath rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/England"></rdaGr2:placeOfDeath><rdaGr2:professionOrOccupation rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Philanthropy"></rdaGr2:professionOrOccupation><rdaGr2:professionOrOccupation rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Drafter"></rdaGr2:professionOrOccupation><rdaGr2:professionOrOccupation xml:lang="en">Writer, art critic, draughtsman, watercolourist, social thinker, philanthropist</rdaGr2:professionOrOccupation><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://it.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ar.dbpedia.org/resource/جون_راسكن"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://fr.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://zh.dbpedia.org/resource/约翰·拉斯金"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q179126"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://el.dbpedia.org/resource/Τζον_Ράσκιν"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://de.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sk.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://pt.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ku.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://mr.dbpedia.org/resource/जॉन_रस्किन"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sr.dbpedia.org/resource/Џон_Раскин"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://hr.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://es.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://tr.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ru.dbpedia.org/resource/Рёскин,_Джон"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ja.dbpedia.org/resource/ジョン・ラスキン"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://pl.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://cy.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://fa.dbpedia.org/resource/جان_راسکین"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ro.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://simple.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://rdf.freebase.com/ns/m.0k5mt"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://id.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://la.dbpedia.org/resource/Ioannes_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://lv.dbpedia.org/resource/Džons_Raskins"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://pa.dbpedia.org/resource/ਜੌਨ_ਰਸਕਿਨ"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://gl.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sv.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://wikidata.dbpedia.org/resource/Q179126"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://uk.dbpedia.org/resource/Джон_Раскін"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://af.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://www4.wiwiss.fu-berlin.de/gutendata/resource/people/Ruskin_John_1819-1900"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://hu.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://da.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://nl.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://cs.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://pms.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://th.dbpedia.org/resource/จอห์น_รัสคิน"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://yago-knowledge.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sw.cyc.com/concept/Mx4rwCJtZZwpEbGdrcN5Y29ycA"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://no.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ur.dbpedia.org/resource/جان_رسکن"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ca.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://be.dbpedia.org/resource/Джон_Раскін"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://fi.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://az.dbpedia.org/resource/Con_Raskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://eo.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ka.dbpedia.org/resource/ჯონ_რესკინი"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ko.dbpedia.org/resource/존_러스킨"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://he.dbpedia.org/resource/ג'ון_ראסקין"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ml.dbpedia.org/resource/ജോൺ_റസ്കിൻ"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://eu.dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/John_Ruskin"/></edm:Agent><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/6"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">Bok</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hi">पुस्तक</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Buch</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">Kirja</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="be">Кніга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pt">Livro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bg">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lt">Knyga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hr">Knjiga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lv">Grāmata</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">Livre (document)</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">Könyv</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bs">Knjiga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hy">Գիրք</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ka">წიგნი</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="uk">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sk">Kniha</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sl">Knjiga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ga">Leabhar</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gd">Leabhar</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">Llibre</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="mk">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sq">Libri</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sr">Књига</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sv">Bok</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ko">책</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gl">Libro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">Βιβλίο</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Book</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="is">Bók</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">Libro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="zh">图书</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="es">Libro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">Raamat</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="eu">Liburu</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cs">Kniha</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ar">كتاب</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cy">Llyfr</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ja">本</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="az">Kitab</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pl">Książka</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ro">Carte</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">Bog</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="he">ספר</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="tr">Kitap</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">Boek (document)</skos:prefLabel><skos:note xml:lang="no">Bok (av norrønt bók) er en sammenbinding av flere blad av papir, pergament eller annet egnet materiale. Materialet er sammenføyd langs en side, ryggen, og som regel innbundet i et mer robust materiale. I overført betydning kan bok også betegne et litterært verk.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hi">पुस्तक या किताब लिखित या मुद्रित पेजों के संग्रह को कहते हैं। डिजिटल पुस्तकों को ई-पुस्तक (ई-बुक) कहते हैं।पुस्तकों की लिस्ट के लिए श्रेणी:पुस्तक देखें</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="de">Ein Buch ist eine mit einer Bindung und meistens auch mit Bucheinband (Umschlag) versehene Sammlung von bedruckten, beschriebenen, bemalten oder auch leeren Blättern aus Papier oder anderen geeigneten Materialien. Laut Unesco-Definition sind (für Statistiken) Bücher nichtperiodische Publikationen mit einem Umfang von 49 Seiten oder mehr. Die UNESCO legte 1995 den 23. April als Welttag des Buches fest.Zudem werden einzelne Werke oder große Textabschnitte, die in sich abgeschlossen sind, als Buch bezeichnet, insbesondere wenn sie Teil eines Bandes sind. Das ist vor allem bei antiken Werken, die aus zusammengehörigen Büchersammlungen bestehen, der Fall – Beispiele hierfür sind die Bibel und andere normative religiöse Heilige Schriften, die Aeneis sowie diverse antike und mittelalterliche Geschichtswerke.Elektronisch gespeicherte Buchtexte nennt man digitale Bücher (englisch e-book). Eine andere moderne Variante des Buches ist das Hörbuch.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fi">Kirja on nidos paperiarkkeja, joissa on painettua tekstiä tai kuvia, tai sen muotoisena ilmestynyt kirjallinen tuote. Kirjoja voidaan julkaista myös sähköisessä muodossa ja äänikirjoina.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="be">Кніга — друкаванае (даўней таксама рукапіснае) выданне ў выглядзе пераплеценых разам лістоў паперы з якім-небудзь тэкстам.У філасофскім значэнні кніга — форма замацавання і ўзнаўлення семантычнай інфармацыі (тэксту), найважнейшы сродак масавай інфармацыі, адукацыі і фактар культуры. Кніга з'яўляецца прадуктам кніжнай справы, якая ўключае стварэнне і размнажэнне кніг, распаўсюджванне (рэклама, кнігагандаль), захаванне і выкарыстанне. Сучасная кніга — звычайна неперыядычнае выданне ў выглядзе збрашураваных аркушаў аб'ёмам больш за 48 старонак. Складаецца з шэрагу элементаў матэрыяльнай канструкцыі і паліграфічнага афармлення.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ru">Кни́га — один из видов печатной продукции: непериодическое издание, состоящее из сброшюрованных бумажных листов (страниц) или тетрадей, на которых нанесена типографским или рукописным способом текстовая и графическая (иллюстрации) информация, имеющая объём более сорока восьми страниц и, как правило, твёрдый переплёт.Также книгой может называться литературное или научное произведение, предназначенное для печати в виде отдельного сброшюрованного издания.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pt">Livro é um volume transportável, composto por páginas encadernadas, contendo texto manuscrito ou impresso e/ou imagens e que forma uma publicação unitária (ou foi concebido como tal) ou a parte principal de um trabalho literário, científico ou outro.Em ciência da informação o livro é chamado monografia, para distingui-lo de outros tipos de publicação como revistas, periódicos, teses, tesauros, etc.O livro é um produto intelectual e, como tal, encerra conhecimento e expressões individuais ou colectivas. Mas também é nos dias de hoje um produto de consumo, um bem e sendo assim a parte final de sua produção é realizada por meios industriais (impressão e distribuição). A tarefa de criar um conteúdo passível de ser transformado em livro é tarefa do autor. Já a produção dos livros, no que concerne a transformar os originais em um produto comercializável, é tarefa do editor, em geral contratado por uma editora. Outra função associada ao livro é a coleta e organização e indexação de coleções de livros, típica do bibliotecário. Finalmente, destaca-se também o livreiro cuja função principal é de disponibilizar os livros editados ao público em geral, vendendo-os nas livrarias generalistas ou de especialidade. Compete também ao livreiro todo o trabalho de pesquisa que vá ao encontro da vontade dos leitores.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bg">Книгата е печатно произведение с научно или литературно съдържание, което е с броширани или подвързани листове. Книгата може да е с меки или твърди корици. Книгите се създават в печатници, а дистрибуцията им се нарича книгоразпространение. Но преди да отидат в печатниците биват измислени и написани от писател.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lt">Knyga – susiūti tušti popieriaus ar pergamento lapai arba lapai su spausdintu tekstu. Taip pat knyga – veikalas ar stambaus veikalo dalis. Elektroninė knyga – kūrinys, saugomas elektroniniame formate.Knygų mylėtojas paprastai vadinamas bibliofilu, knygų kolekcija – biblioteka.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hr">Knjiga je ukoričena tiskana omeđena publikacija od najmanje 49 stranica (UNESCO-va definicija), odnosno, knjiga je tiskana kolekcija papira. Ukoričena tiskana publikacija koja sadrži manje od 49 stranica naziva se brošura. U engleskom jeziku riječ "book" dolazi od staroengleske riječi "bōc", koja dolazi od njemačke riječi s sadržajem "*bōk-".</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lv">Grāmata ir neperiodisks iespieddarbs kodeksa formā ar muguriņā sastiprinātām lapām. Lapu daudzums ir ne mazāks par 3 iespiedloksnēm, tas ir 48 lappuses. Mūsdienās grāmatu lapas izgatavo no papīra. Parasti grāmata ir pabeigts teksts, kas izteikts ar rakstu zīmēm vai attēliem.Mūsdienās bez grāmatām pastāv arī elektroniski informācijas nesēji — elektroniskās grāmatas.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fr">Un livre est un document écrit formant une unité et conçu comme tel composé de pages en papier ou en carton reliées les unes aux autres.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hu">A könyv az ókortól a 20. század közepéig a legfontosabb és legelterjedtebb információhordozó médium. Megjelenési formája változatos, leginkább összefűzött vagy -kötött papírlapokból áll. A papírlapokra felvitt jelek hordozzák az információt. A hagyományosan valamilyen nyelven, írásban, szövegként rögzített információt az olvasás művelete segítségével kapjuk vissza. Képi információt is tartalmazhat.Használatának megkönnyítésére a lapok oldalait számozzák, a tartalom részei közötti eligazodást a tagolás és a tipográfia mellett külön tartalomjegyzék, tárgymutató vagy névmutató is segítheti.A könyv manapság nyomdaipari sokszorosítással előállított tömegtermék.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="yi">א בוך (מערצאל: ביכער) איז א זאמלונג פון בלעטער וואס זענען געשריבן, געדרוקט, אילוסטרירט אדער אפילו ליידיק, געמאכט פון פאפיר, פארמעט, אדער אנדערע מאטריאלן, צוזאמענגעהאפטן פון איין זייט . איין בויגן אין א בוך הייסט א בלאט, און א בלאט האט צוויי זייטן. היינט שאפט מען ביכער אויך אין עלעקטראנישן פארמאט.אלע ביכער און געשריבענער ווערק רופט מען ליטעראטור. איינער וואס פארקויפט ביכער איז א בוכהענדלער. א זאמלונג פון ביכער אין א ביבליאטעקאין 2010, האט גוגל געשאצט אז אין דער וועלט זענען פאראן אומגעפער 130 מיליאן פארשידענע ביכער.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bs">Knjiga je skup ili kolekcija pisanih, štampanih, ilustrovanih ili praznih listova, načinjenih od papira, pergamenta ili nekog drugog materijala, koje su obično spojene sa jedne strane. Strane listova knjige zovu se stranice. U novije vrijeme postale su poznate i elektronske knjige. Prema UNESCO-voj definiciji knjiga mora imati minimalno 49 stranica. Publikacija sa manje od 49 stranica naziva se brošura.Knjiga se koristi za čitanje očima ili vrhovima prstiju, te u slučaju audioknjiga sluhom. Na taj način se prikupljaju informacije koje su odštampane ili snimljene.Pod nazivom knjiga se također podrazumjevaju literarni radovi koji se sastoje određenog broja tomova, te se time razlikuju od časopisa i magazina, koji izlaze periodično i na neodređeno vrijeme. Ljudi koji vole da sakupljaju ili čitaju knjige zovu se bibliofili, knjigoljupci ili, neformalno, knjiški crvi.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hy">Գիրք, ձեռագիր, տպագիր կամ այլ կրիչի վրա գրական-գեղարվեստական, հասարակական-քաղաքական, գիտական բովանդակությամբ ստեղծագործություն է։ Ներկայումս առավել տարածվածը թղթի վրա տպագրված գիրքն է։Գիրքը կազմված է բնագրից, տիտղոսաթերթից և կազմից. վերջինս երբեմն ունենում է նաև կազմաշապիկ։ Տիտղոսաթերթի վրա գրվում են հեղինակի անունը և գրքի վերնագիրը, հրատարակության վայրը և տեսակը, հրատարակչությունը, տպագրության տարեթիվը։Գրքի սկզբնավորումը կապված է գրի ստեղծման հետ, որը մի քանի հազար տարվա պատմություն ունի։ Անցյալում բաբելացիները, ասորեստանցիները և այլ հին ժողովուրդներ գրել են հիմնականում կավե սալիկների վրա։ Պահպանվել է մ.թ. ա. III հազարամյակում սալիկների վրա գրված գեղարվեստական հնագույն՝ ասուրա-բաբելական «Գիլգամեշ» դյուցազներգությունը։ Այդ եղանակով կազմված գրքերից են ստեղծվել առաջին գրադարանները։ Չինաստանում գրել են հնդկեղեգից (բամբուկ) պատրաստված շերտիկների վրա և շարել ամուր թելի վրա։ Ավելի ուշ չինացիները գրել են մետաքսի, իսկ մ. թ. II դարից՝ թղթի վրա։ Հին Եգիպտոսում նախ գրել են կավե սալիկների, այնուհետև՝ պապիրուսի վրա, որը եղեգի մամլած շերտիկներն իրար սոսնձած մի քանի տասնյակ մետր երկարությամբ ժապավեն էր և պահվում էր գլանաձև փաթաթված։Մ. թ. ա. II դարում Պերգամոն քաղաքում կենդանիների կաշվից պատրաստվել է նոր գրանյութ և քաղաքի անունով կոչվել պերգամենտ։ Այն մեզ հայտնի մագաղաթն է։ Մագաղաթե ամենահին ձեռագիրը Հոմերոսի «Իլիական» պոեմի՝ III դարում գրված մի հատված է։ Մագաղաթը պապիրուսից ավելի ճկուն ու ամուր էր, հեշտությամբ ծալվում էր, իսկ ծալվածքի մասում թերթերը կարվում ու միացվում էին իրար։ Միջնադարում մագաղաթե թերթերն ամփոփվում էին կաշեպատ կամ լաթապատ փայտե կազմի մեջ։Գրքի զարգացման և ժողովրդականացման խոշոր ազդակ էր 1447 թ-ին Յոհան Գուտենբերգի տպագրության գյուտը, որով դրվեց գրքի տպագրության հիմքը։Հայաստանում թուղթը՝ որպես գրանյութ, օգտագործվել է VIII–IX դարերում։ Տպագրությունը XV դարում զգալիորեն խթանել է գրքի զարգացումն ու տարածումը։Հայերեն առաջին գրքերը՝ ձեռագիր մատյանները, ստեղծվել են V դարում՝ հայոց գրի գյուտից հետո։ Պահպանված հնագույն ձեռագիր մատյանը VII դարում ստեղծված Վեհամոր Ավետարանն է։ Ձեռագիր մատյաններ ստեղծվել են մինչև XVIII դարի վերջը։Թղթի վրա մեզ հասած առաջին ձեռագիր գիրքն ընդօրինակվել է 981 թ-ին։Մինչև 1800 թ. տպագրված գրքերը կոչվում են հնատիպ։ Դրանք բազմաբովանդակ են, բայց գերակշռում են կրոնական բնույթի գրքերը։ Հրատարակվել են փոքր տպաքանակներով, մեծ մասամբ՝ կաշեպատ զարդարուն կազմերով։ Հայերեն հնատիպ գրքերի թիվը անցնում է 1000-ից։ 1801–50 թթ-ին հրատարակվել է մոտ 1700 անուն գիրք։ Ներկայումս Հայաստանում և տարբեր երկրներում ամեն տարի լույս են տեսնում հազարավոր հայերեն գրքեր։</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ka">წიგნი — ინფორმაციის მნიშვნელოვანი საშუალება, ცოდნის გავრცელების, განათლებისა და აღზრდის იარაღი.წიგნის ტექსტების ფიქსირება ხდება ფურცლებზე ნიშნების, ასოების ან სხვა გრაფიკული გამოსახულებების საშუალებით, რომლებიც აღიქმება ვიზუალურად. (გამონაკლისია წიგნები უსინათლოთათვის, რომლებიც ბრაილის შრიფტით არის დაწერილი.)თანამედროვე წიგნი წარმოადგენს ყუაში ჩამაგრებული ტექსტებისა და ილუსტრაციების შემცველი ფურცლების კოდექსბლოკს გარე დამცველი ელემენტებითურთ (ყდა, გარეკანი) და ნაბეჭდი გვერდების განსაზღვრული რაოდენობით - იუნესკოს რეკომენდაციების შესატყვისად - ნაბეჭდ თაბახზე მეტი ე. ი. არანაკლებ 48 გვერდისა.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="uk">Кни́га, книжка — письмовий запис, неперіодичне видання у вигляді зброшурованих аркушів друкованого матеріалу, набір письмових, друкованих, ілюстрованих або порожніх аркушів, виготовлених з паперу, пергаменту або іншого матеріалу, як правило, скріплених з одного боку. Сторони аркуша називаються сторінками.Книга виготовлена в цифровому вигляді називається електронною книгою. Озвучену й записану на матеріальний носій книгу називають аудіокнигою (звуковою книгою, книгою вголос).Книжкова крамниця або книгарня — крамниця, де продаються книги. Також книги можна позичати у бібліотеках на певний час.Любителя книг, як правило, називають книголюбом, бібліофілом, або, неформально, книжковим хробаком (від англ. Bookworm).</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sk">Kniha je nejasne definovaný termín. Bežné definície sú nasledovné:definície s dôrazom na fyzické hľadisko:súhrn (potlačených alebo prázdnych) listov papiera, pergamenu, velínu, látky alebo iného materiálu zopnutý pozdĺž jednej hrany (bez ohľadu na to, či má alebo nemá dosky či puzdro) [táto definícia teda zahŕňa okrem slovesných diel aj rôzne záznamníky, albumy a podobne]slovesné dielo vydané tlačou v samostatnom zväzku opak brožúry, publikácia majúca (alebo len literárny produkt majúci) minimálne 48 strán a viacdielne dosky (namiesto prebalu) tlačený alebo akýkoľvek iným spôsobom rozmnožený grafický dokument, knihársky spracovaný do tvaru zväzku a tvoriaci myšlienkový a výtvarný celok (v tejto norme aj hudobniny, obrazové publikácie, albumy, atlasy, rôzne druhy tabuliek apod. vo forme knihy). definícia s dôrazom na neperiodicitu: knižná publikácia (t.j. neperiodická textová publikácia [iná než špeciálna publikácia ako napr. diplomová práca, konferenčný materiál a pod.]) definícia s dôrazom na neperiodicitu aj fyzické hľadisko: neseriálový tlačený dokument v kódexovej forme tlačená neperiodická publikácia (bez jej dosák), prístupná verejnosti, ktorá má rozsah minimálne 49 strán a je vydaná v (určitej) krajinedefinícia s dôrazom na tvorenie jedného celku: duševné dielo vydané v písanej, tlačenej alebo elektronickej forme, zvyčajne rozdelené na stránky a tvoriace fyzickú jednotku V poslednej definícii, ako vidno, termín kniha zahŕňa aj elektronickú knihu. O (ne)zaradení zvukových kníh (audiokníh) medzi knihy pozri článok zvuková kniha.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sl">Knjiga je zbirka popisanih, porisanih ali potiskanih listov iz papirja, pergamenta ali drugega materiala, na eni strani zvezanih skupaj in ovitih v platnice. Knjiga je lahko tudi oznaka za literarno delo, v zadnjem času pa z izrazom e-knjiga označujemo literarna dela, ki so shranjena (lahko izključno) na elektronskih medijih in dostopna s pomočjo računalnika.Za knjigo bi lahko rekli, da je predmet (lahko jo listamo, prijemamo, trgamo...), naprava (je oštevilčena in nam omogoča lažje iskanje informacij) ali medij (s knjigo lahko prenašamo sporočila, podatke, informacije...)V bibliotekarstvu se knjiga imenuje monografska publikacija, da se razlikuje od revij, časopisov in drugih publikacij. Celoti vseh napisanih del, vključno s knjigami, pravimo literatura. Knjige so eden glavnih načinov razširjanja znanja in idej med ljudmi. Najbolj uveljavljeni načini dostopa do knjig so knjigarne (nakup) in knjižnice (izposoja), posebej stare in dragocene knjige pa hranijo tudi muzeji.Ljubitelja knjig imenujemo bibliofil, človeka, ki veliko bere, pa pogovorno knjižni molj.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ga">Is éard atá i gceist le leabhar ná cnuasach de leathanaigh, ar a bhfuil focail nó íomhánna clóite, déanta de pháipéar nó ábhair eile atá fáiscthe le chéile ar thaobh amháin. Is féidir ríomhleabhair a fháil sa lá atá inniu ann. Ní leabhar clóite atá ann, ach comhad ar ríomhaire ar féidir é a léamh ar nós leabhair.Cuirtear bailiúchán mór leabhar i dtaisce i leabharlann. Leabhragán a ghlaoitear ar an dtroscán ar a gcuirtear leabhair ina seasamh.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="gd">'S e an t'iom-leabhar air a foillseachadh leabhar a th'ann.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ca">Un llibre (del llatí liber) és una obra impresa o manuscrita no periòdica que consta d'una sèrie de fulls de paper (si és pergamí o vitel·la es parla de còdex), cosits o enquadernats de manera que es reuneixen en un volum. Segons la definició de la UNESCO, ha de tenir 49 pàgines o més, sense comptar les cobertes. Un llibre pot tractar sobre qualsevol tema. Un llibre és també cadascuna de les parts de l'obra en els codis i lleis d'una gran extensió. També s'anomena llibre tota obra independent, fent abstracció de la concreció física formal. Un llibre és una col·lecció d'un o més treballs escrits, usualment imprès en paper i cobert amb tapes per a protegir-lo i organitzar el material imprès.Sintèticament, es pot dir que el llibre neix com a imitació del còdex, però en paper en comptes de pergamí. És arran de la impremta que el llibre va anar atenyent la majoria de trets que li són característics i que alhora el distingeixen del còdex.Avui dia, tanmateix, aquesta definició no queda circumscrita al món imprès o dels suports físics, donada l'aparició dels nous formats documentals i especialment del web World Wide Web. El llibre digital, conegut com a e-book en anglès col·loquial, està irrompent cada vegada amb més força en el món del llibre i en la pràctica professional bibliotecària i documental. A més, el llibre també pot trobar-se en format d'àudio, en el qual cas és anomenat audiollibre.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="mk">Книга е збир на пишани, печатени, илустрирани или празни страници, изработени од хартија, пергамент или друг вид на материјал, обично прицврстени заедно од едната страна. Секоја страна на лист од книгата се нарекува страница. Книга направена во електронска форма е позната како електронска книга или скратено е-книга.Книгите исто така се однесуваат и на литературни творби. Во библиотеките постои разлика меѓу периодичните часописи, магазини или весници и книгите. Една книга може да се подели во неколку тома или секции, и тогаш секоја од нив се нарекува исто така книга, но содржи и број, на пример прва книга, втора книга, итн. Вљубеникот во читање книги се нарекува библиофил. Местото каде се купуваат и се продаваат книгите се нарекува книжарница, а местото од каде што се позајмуваат книгите се нарекува библиотека.Во 2010 година Гугл проценил дека постојат околу 130 милиони наслови на книги во светот.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sq">Libri është tërësia unitare, e ilustruar ose jo, e botuar nën një titull në çfarëdo forme, që ka për objekt materializimin e një produkti mendor të një ose më shumë autorëve dhe që botohet një herë ose herë mbas here, në një vëllim ose në shumë vëllime.Zakonisht libri është një vepër shkencore, letrare, mësimore etj. me fletë të shtypura e të lidhura mes dy kapakëve së bashku në një vëllim dhe i cili del në shitje. Sipas definicionit të UNESCO logaritet si libër një botim i shtypur, i cili mund të blehet nga publiku, nuk del në formë periodike dhe ka së paku 49 faqe. Produkte të përafërta me Librin janë botime të shtypura. Në Kosovë këto produkte përfshihen: almanakë, vjetarë, katalogë,albume filatelie, albume për ngjyrosje, albume me figura për fëmijë, repertorë me informacione numerike, repertorë alfabetikë, broshura që shpjegojnë funksionimin e aparateve me të cilat janë të lidhura, partitura të thjeshta që përhapin tekstin dhe muzikën e një kënge, fletore muzike për detyra, si dhe botime të tjera të ngjashme siç janë librat me disqe, shirita magnetikë, kaseta, filma ose diapozitivë, me kushtin e dyfishtë:a) që këto të përbëjnë një tërësi dhe elementet e tyre të mos jenë objekt e një shitjeje të veçantë dheb) që mbështetja dëgjimore-pamore të jetë plotësuese e librit, dhe jo e kundërta, konsiderohen si libra.↑ 1,0 1,1</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sr">Књиге, овакве какве су данас, појавиле су се тек у средњем веку. Најближи њима били су свитуљци папируса. Листови папируса лепљени су један за другим, и тако се добијао дугачак свитуљак.Средином 5. века, пергамент је заменио папирус. Пергамент се прави од овчије или козје коже. Листови од тог материјала, исписани су на једној страни, сечени да буду исте величине, а потом су на једном крају спајани кожним копчама и повезани у књиге.Међутим, књиге налик на данашње први пут су направљене, у средњем веку. Четири комада велина савијена су тако да је сваки творио по два листа. Ти комади су онда стављени један у други, па се добијало 8 спојених листова, који се називају свезак. Они су се затим слали писару који ће исписати текст. Писар је раздвајао листове и писао страницу по страницу. Велин је био дебео, тако да се могло писати са обје стране.Идући корак било је слање исписаних свезака књиговезцу, да од њих направи књигу. Он их је прошивао дебелим концем, потом је правио дрвене корице, па је крајеве конца провлачио кроз рупе избушене на дашчицама, и на тај начин спајао странице на корицама. На крају је лепио велики комад коже на споју исписаних одељака и дрвених корица. Касније је повезивање усавршено. Пронађени су нови начини да се књига украси и боље сачува.Средњовековне књиге су већином биле Библије, проповеди и остали верски списи. Иза тога су се појавиле и књиге с подручја права, медицине, природних наука, а још касније и неколико летописа и романа. Највећи број књига у средњем веку писан је на латинском језику.Књиге су почели штампати у 15. веку а пионир технике штампања је био Јохан Гутенберг.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sv">För andra betydelser, se Bok (olika betydelser).En bok är ett medium för kommunikation – innehållet kan, men måste inte vara, någon form av litteratur. En bok är en produkt som består av flera sammanhäftade eller ihoplimmade blad (ark), vars innehåll ofta är text och/eller bilder, och som ofta täcks av ett omslag med upplysning om bokens titel och författare. Unesco har definierat en bok som "en icke-periodisk tryckt publikation bestående av minst 49 sidor". Det finns många typer av böcker, från pocketböcker till inbundna böcker i flera varianter, pekböcker samt talböcker.Bok har dock också en mindre specifik betydelse, där det kan syfta på såväl en bokrulle som en e-bok. En bok kan också vara detsamma som ett litterärt verk, som i frasen "Charles Darwins bok Om arternas uppkomst". En bok kan också vara en del i ett längre verk, såsom Första mosebok är den första delen av Gamla testamentet. Liknande produkter är tidningar och tidskrifter.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ko">책(冊)은 일정한 목적으로 쓴 글 및 참고 자료 등을 덧붙여 묶은 것이다. 서사(書史), 서질, 서적(書籍), 서전(書典), 서책(書冊), 책자(冊子), 문적(文籍), 전적(典籍), 편적(篇籍) 혹은 도서(圖書)로도 불린다. 책 도안은 겉표지, 서언 (서문, 추천서문), 머리말, 목차, 책 내용, 색인 (용어 색인) 따위로 구별 할 수 있다.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="gl">Un libro é unha obra manuscrita, impresa ou virtual, que consta dunha serie de follas que conteñen texto ou imaxes composto por, polo menos, 48 páxinas (sen contar as capas - segundo a Unesco). Un libro pode ser, por exemplo, unha novela, un ensaio ou un libro fotográfico.A palabra libro procede do latín liber, que significa cortiza.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="el">Το Βιβλίο είναι υλικός φορέας γραπτού ή και εικαστικού περιεχομένου. Παγκοσμίως εννοείται ως βασική κατηγορία έντυπου λόγου και αποτελείται από αριθμό συνδεδεμένων τεμαχίων χαρτιού και εξώφυλλο. Βιβλίο αποκαλείται επίσης το σύνολο του περιεχομένου του αντικειμένου αυτού ως πνευματικό έργο. Αν και η ύπαρξη του έντυπου λόγου χρονολογείται από την απαρχή της ανθρώπινης ιστορίας, το βιβλίο αποτελεί το κατεξοχήν μέσο διάδοσης της γνώσης από την εφεύρεση της τυπογραφίας από τον Ιωάννη Γουτεμβέργιο έως και σήμερα. Η αξία και το περιεχόμενο του βιβλίου συνδέθηκε περισσότερο με τη λογοτεχνία, την επιστήμη, και τη θρησκεία. Με την ανάπτυξη της τεχνολογίας το βιβλίο εμφανίζεται τις τελευταίες δεκαετίες και σε μη υλικούς φορείς όπως το ηλεκτρονικό βιβλίο (e-book) και το ακουστικό βιβλίο (audio book). Τα βιβλία απαντώνται στην τυπογραφική βιομηχανία, στις εκδοτικές επιχειρήσεις, στα βιβλιοπωλεία, στις βιβλιοθήκες, σε ιδιωτικές συλλογές και αλλού.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="en">A book is a set of written, printed, illustrated, or blank sheets, made of ink, paper, parchment, or other materials, usually fastened together to hinge at one side. A single sheet within a book is called a leaf, and each side of a leaf is called a page. A set of text-filled or illustrated pages produced in electronic format is known as an electronic book, or e-book.Books may also refer to works of literature, or a main division of such a work. In library and information science, a book is called a monograph, to distinguish it from serial periodicals such as magazines, journals or newspapers. The body of all written works including books is literature. In novels and sometimes other types of books (for example, biographies), a book may be divided into several large sections, also called books (Book 1, Book 2, Book 3, and so on). An avid reader of books is a bibliophile or colloquially, bookworm.A shop where books are bought and sold is a bookshop or bookstore. Books can also be borrowed from libraries. Google has estimated that as of 2010, approximately 130,000,000 unique titles had been published.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="is">Bók er safn blaða fest saman í band, oftast í umgjörð sem er sterkari en efnið í blöðunum (og kallast umgjörðin þá kápa). Blöðin geta m.a. verið úr skinni, pappír og pergamenti.Tilgangur bóka er oftast að miðla upplýsingum með texta, táknum og myndum. Bókasöfn eru staðir þar sem margar bækur eru, oft til útláns eða lestrar almenningi.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="it">Un libro è un insieme di fogli stampati oppure manoscritti delle stesse dimensioni rilegati insieme in un certo ordine e racchiusi da una copertina. Il libro, usato per acquisire informazioni o anche per divertimento, è ancora oggi lo "strumento principe del sapere".</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="zh">图书，通常在狭义上的理解是带有文字和图像的纸张的集合。书通常由墨水、纸张、羊皮纸或者其他材料固定在书脊上组成。组成书的一张纸称为一张，一张的一面称为一页。但随着科学技术的发展，狭义图书的概念也在扩展，制作书的材料也在改变，如电子格式的电子书。从广义理解的图书，则是一切传播訊息的媒介。书也指文学作品或者其中的一部分。在图书馆情报学中，书被称为专著，以区别于杂志、学报、报纸等连载期刊。所有的书面作品（包括图书）的主体是文学。在小说和一些类型（如传记）中，书可能还要分成卷。对书特别喜爱的人被称为爱书者或藏书家，更随意的称呼是书虫或者书呆子。买书的地方叫书店，借书可以到图书馆去。2010年，谷歌公司估计，从印刷术发明至今，大概出版了一亿三千万本不同名字的书籍。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="es">Un libro (del latín liber, libri, ‘membrana’ o ‘corteza de árbol’) es una obra impresa, manuscrita o pintada en una serie de hojas de papel, pergamino, vitela u otro material, unidas por un lado (es decir, encuadernadas) y protegidas con tapas, también llamadas cubiertas. Un libro puede tratar sobre cualquier tema.Según la definición de la Unesco, un libro debe poseer 49 o más páginas (25 hojas o más), pues desde 5 hasta 48 páginas sería un folleto (desde tres hasta 24 hojas), y desde una hasta cuatro páginas se consideran hojas sueltas (una o dos hojas).También se llama "libro" a una obra de gran extensión publicada en varias unidades independientes, llamados "tomos" o "volúmenes". Otras veces se llama también "libro" a cada una de las partes de una obra, aunque físicamente se publiquen todas en un mismo volumen (ejemplo: Libros de la Biblia).Hoy día, no obstante, esta definición no queda circunscrita al mundo impreso o de los soportes físicos, dada la aparición y auge de los nuevos formatos documentales y especialmente de la World Wide Web. El libro digital o libro electrónico, conocido como e-book, está viendo incrementado su uso en el mundo del libro y en la práctica profesional bibliotecaria y documental. Además, el libro también puede encontrarse en formato audio, en cuyo caso se denomina audiolibro.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="et">Raamat on köidetud kogu teksti või piltidega lehti; ehk ka kogum ühest servast kokku liidetud, tavaliselt ühesuurusi ja ristkülikukujulisi paberilehti, millel asub nähtaval või kombataval kujul märkidest koosnev tekst. Raamat üldisemas tähenduses on graafiline andmekandja.Kirjastustegevuses, raamatukaubanduses, raamatukogunduses jm nimetatakse raamatuks ühekordselt tiražeeritud tekstikogumikku, millel on reeglina rahvusvaheline 10-kohaline identifitseerimiskood (ISBN). Raamatul on lehekülgi vähemalt 49 (brošüüril 5 kuni 48). Käsikirjad, perioodilised ja seeriaväljaanded, samuti koomiksid, noodiraamatud, mitmesugused kataloogid, kasutusjuhendid jm raamatukujulised esemed selles mõttes raamatute hulka ei kuulu. E-raamat on elektrooniliselt salvestatud suurem tekstikogumik.Audioraamat on helikandjale salvestatud kuulatav tekstikogumik.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="eu">Liburua edo Idaztia idatzitako, zuriz inprimatutako edota irudiz hornitutako orrialdeen sorta da, paperez, pergaminoz edo beste material batzuez egindakoa. Normalean azal pare batek babesten du. 1501 baino lehen egindakoak "inkunable" edo jatorri zehaztezindun izena hartzen dute. Gaur egun, formato elektronikoa baldin badauka "e-book" izena hartzen du ingelesez.Liburutegiak dira objektu hauek irakurgai ditugun tokiak eta liburudendak salgai daudenak.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cs">Kniha je sešitý nebo slepený svazek listů nebo skládaný arch papíru, kartonu, pergamenu nebo jiného materiálu, popsaný, potištěný nebo prázdný s vazbou a opatřený přebalem.Kniha je též literární práce nebo hlavní oddíl této práce. Kniha publikovaná v elektronické formě se nazývá elektronická kniha (e-kniha) nebo e-book.Knihovní a informační věda definuje knihu jako monografii pro její rozlišení od periodických publikací jako jsou časopisy nebo noviny.Osoba se zaujetím pro knihy je označována jako bibliofil nebo knihomil. Člověk s chorobnou touhou psát knihy je označován jako grafoman, s nutkáním vydat vlastní knihu typoman.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ar">الكتب هي أوعية المعلومات غير الدورية والتي بطبيعة محتوياتها وتنظيمها وضعت لتُقرأ من أولها لآخرها في تتابع منطقيولكل منها عنوان محدد حتى ولو صدرت مجمعة تحت سلسلة ما. ومن أنواعها الكتب المرجعية: وهي أوعية المعلومات التي بطبيعة محتوياتها وتنظيمها لم توضع لتُقرأ من أولها إلى آخرها وإنما يرجع إليها عند الحاجة لاستقاء معلومات معينة، كالقواميس ودوائر المعارف والأدلة والببليوجرافيات وغيرها، ولا يسمح عادة بإعارة هذا النوع من الأوعية خارج المكتبات. و الكتاب شرعا (أي المفهوم الاصطلاحي في الدين الإسلامي) هو كلام الله يوحي به إلى رسول من رسله ليبلغه إلى الناس ليصلوا به إلى سعادتهم في الدنيا والاخرة.و الكتاب أيضا هو عبارة عن مجموعة من أوراق مطبوعة من الورق يغطى بين غلافين. ويمكن للكتاب أيضا أن يكون النص في أكبر مجموعة من النصوص. هذا النص لديه بعض الميزات التي لا تنطبق على مجموعة ككل. وبهذه الطريقة ربما هو مكتوب في كتاب من قبل مؤلف واحد، أو ان تتعامل مع عدة مؤلقين على موضوغ واحد. وكثيرا ما كتب في هذا المعنى يمكن فهمها دون معرفة المجموعة بأكملها. كتب مجلدة ويغطي الثابت من الورق المقوى مغطاة بقماش أو جلد ومخيط عادة معا. وتغطي الكتب غلاف ورقي من ورقة قوية وعادة ما يتم لصقها معا. ويمكن قراءة الكلمات بصوت عال، أو في الكتب المسجلة على أشرطة (الكاسيت) والأقراص المدمجة.يمكن استعارة الكتب من مكتبة أو تم شراؤها من محل لبيع الكتب. يمكن أن يجعل الناس كتب خاصة بهم ملئها الصور العائلية، والرسوم، أو الكتابة الخاصة بهم. بعض الكتب الخاصة مثل مذكرات، دفتر العناوين، أو ألبوم الصور الفوتوغرافية.في معظم الوقت، فإن كلمة "كتاب" تعني أن تكون داخل صفحات كلمات مطبوعة أو المكتوبة عليها.تتم كتابة بعض الكتب للأطفال فقط، أو للترفيه، في حين أن الكتب الأخرى للدراسة في المدرسة شيئا مثل الرياضيات أو التاريخ. وتحتوي الكتب على الصور الفوتوغرافية أو الرسوم.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cy">Fel arfer, mae llyfr yn golygu testun wedi ei sgrifennu neu ei argraffu ar bapur sydd wedi ei rwymo mewn clawr. Ers rhai blynyddoedd mae e-lyfrau ar gael, sef llyfrau ar ffurf meddalwedd y gellir eu darllen gan beiriant arbennig.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ja">本（ほん、英: book）は書物の一種であり、書籍・雑誌などの印刷・製本された出版物である。狭義では、複数枚の紙が一方の端を綴じられた状態になっているもの。この状態で紙の片面をページという。本を読む場合はページをめくる事によって次々と情報を得る事が出来る。つまり、狭義の本には巻物は含まれない。端から順を追ってしかみられない巻物を伸ばして蛇腹に折り、任意のページを開ける体裁としたものを折り本といい、折本の背面（文字の書かれていない側）で綴じたものが狭義の「本」といえる。本文が縦書きなら右綴じ、本文が横書きなら左綴じにする。また、1964年のユネスコ総会で採択された国際的基準は、「"本"とは、表紙はページ数に入れず、本文が少なくとも49ページ以上から成る、印刷された非定期刊行物」と、定義している。5ページ以上49ページ未満は小冊子として分類している。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="az">Kitab — üzərinə müxtəlif yollarla köçürülmüş mətn və ya rəsm şəklində informasiya daşıyıcılarından ibarət vərəqə toplusu. Bu vərəqələr bir tərəfdən tikilir və üzlüklə örtülür. Kitab kağızının hər vərəqinin üzləri səhifə adlanır. Bəzən böyük sənədin və ədəbi əsərin bir hissəsinə də kitab deyilir. Elektron formasında yazılmış kitab elektron kitabdır.Bu məqalənin azərbaycan dili əlifbasının ərəb qrafikası ilə qarşılığı vardır. Bax: کیتاب&lt;span id="interwiki-la-fa" /></skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pl">Książka – dokument piśmienniczy, zapis myśli ludzkiej, raczej obszerny, w postaci publikacji wielostronicowej o określonej liczbie stron, o charakterze trwałym.Dzisiejsza postać książki wywodzi się od kodeksu, czyli kartek połączonych grzbietem, które wraz z upowszechnieniem pergaminu zastąpiły poprzednią formę dokumentu piśmienniczego, czyli zwój.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ro">O carte este o colecție de hârtii, pergamente sau alte astfel de materiale, în formă de coli sau foi de cele mai multe ori egale între ele și legate sau broșate într-un volum. Cărțile sunt de obicei tipărite (rareori scrise și de mână) și conțin diverse lucrări scrise, pe cea mai mare diversitate de teme. O carte este de asemenea o operă literară sau științifică, sau o parte semnificativă dintr-o astfel de operă.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="da">For alternative betydninger, se Bog (flertydig). (Se også artikler, som begynder med Bog)En bog er typisk en samling af flere end 48 papirsider[Kilde mangler] påtrykt én eller flere tekster og/eller billeder eller andet kognitivt stimulerende materiale. Siderne i bogen er beskyttet i et omslag (for- og bagside), og som helhed repræsenterer bogen en bestemt, traditionel måde at organisere indhold på. Mindre bøger, pjecer eller småtryk består af færre end 48 sider.Bøger opdeles i forskellige formater afhængigt af det antal gange arkene er foldet. A4 (kvart) er foldet fire gange osv. Af praktiske årsager er en bog med en højde på under 25 cm er en oktav, en højde på mellem 26 og 35 cm er en kvart, og bøger derover er folio'er. Når bogens bredde er større end højden, tales der om oblong eller tværoktav, -kvart og -folio.Inden for biblioteks- og informationsvidenskab kaldes en bog for en monografi til forskel fra periodiske publikationer som tidsskrifter, aviser, ugeblade mv.Før trykpressens opfindelse blev stort set alle bøger møjsommeligt kopieret ved håndkraft. Det gjorde en bog sjælden og meget værdifuld. I den tidlige middelalder var det kun kirken, universiteterne og rige, der havde midler til at eje bøger eller få dem fremstillet. De første bøger blev skrevet på ark af pergament af kalveskind. Senere blev de skrevet eller trykt på papir.En hel side kunne skæres ud i relief på en træplade, som kunne anvendes til at producere mange eksemplarer af denne ene side. At producere en hel bog på den måde var en meget omstændelig affære.Reliefteknikken er brugt til at fremstille verdens ældste trykte bog. Den er fundet i Kina og dateret til 868 e. kr., dvs. 587 år før Gutenbergs bibel. Ligeledes i Kina blev der omkring 1045 eksperimenteret med et trykkesystem af lertyper fastgjort med voks i smalle træskinner, men der er ikke bevaret nogen eksemplarer af bøger trykt med denne teknik.Gutenbergs bibel blev udgivet i 1455 i et oplag på ca. 200 og var den første maskinelt masseproducerede bog i verden. Det revolutionerende ved Gutenbergs teknik var, at den byggede på genanvendelige, løse blytyper.I Danmark var det den tyske bogtrykker Johan Snell, der indførte bogtrykkerkunsten, da han i 1482 åbnede sit trykkeri i Odense. Der gik 13 år, inden Gotfred af Ghemen trykte den første bog i Danmark og på dansk: Den danske Rimkrønike. Kirken havde ikke længere monopol på bogfremstilling.Bogtrykkerkunstens hurtige udbredelse førte store omvæltninger med sig. Mediet skulle finde sin form. Sidenummerering, som forekommer os så naturligt, dukkede først op omkring 1470. Folkebiblioteker skaffede alle adgang til bøger. Senere har bogklubber, billigbøger, It-hæfter mv. gjort det muligt for alle at eje en bog.Bogbindere og forfattere solgte de første bøger. Senere overtog boghandlere; de havde længe monopol på salget i Danmark. Et Internationalt Standard Bognummer (ISBN) anvendes til entydig identifikation af bogen på tværs af landegrænser.Udviklingen i informationsteknologien medfører eksperimenter med forskellige former for elektroniske bøger, og Peter Poulsens "Rulletekster" er den første danske E-bog (elektronisk bog).</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="he">ספר הוא טקסט מודפס או כתוב בכתב יד בנושא מסוים, שדפיו כרוכים יחדיו. בשלהי המאה העשרים החלה הפקתם של ספרים אלקטרוניים המוצגים על קורא ספרים אלקטרוני, טאבלטים, צג המחשב ואפילו טלפונים חכמים.עוד מימי בראשית אסף האדם את יצירותיו הספרותיות תחת ספרים. בתחילה היו אלה מגילות קלף, וספרים מצומצמים בהיקפם. עם התפתחות הדפוס באמצע המאה ה-15 עלה היקפם של הספרים. במשך מאות שנים היו הספרים אמצעי עיקרי להפצת ידע ולהעברתו מדור לדור. במאה העשרים נוספו לספרים המודפסים שלל אמצעים נוספים: רדיו, קולנוע, טלוויזיה והאינטרנט, אך לספר ממשיך להישמר מקום מרכזי. ספרי עלילה רבים מוצאים את דרכם אל מסך הקולנוע או הטלוויזיה.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="tr">Kitap, bir kenarından birleştirilerek dışına kapak takılmış yani ciltlenmiş, (kâğıt, parşömen vb. malzemeden üretilmiş) üzeri baskılı sayfaların toplamıdır.Bir "yapıta" ya da yapıtın bir bölümüne de kitap dendiği olur. Elektronik ortamda yayınlanan kitaplara ise e-kitap yani elektronik kitap denir. Kütüphanecilik 'te, dergi, bülten ya da gazete gibi süreli yayınlardan ayırt etmek için monograf olarak da adlandırılır.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="nl">Het boek is een van de meest gebruikte manieren om informatie vast te leggen in de vorm van schrift en afbeeldingen en om deze informatie weer te geven, op te slaan en te verspreiden.</skos:note><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://te.dbpedia.org/resource/పుస్తకము"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://it.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ga.dbpedia.org/resource/Leabhar"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hy.dbpedia.org/resource/Գիրք"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://jv.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q571"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sl.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hr.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lb.dbpedia.org/resource/Buch"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://oc.dbpedia.org/resource/Libre"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ta.dbpedia.org/resource/நூல்_அமைப்பு"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://az.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitab"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lt.dbpedia.org/resource/Knyga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sw.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitabu"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://si.dbpedia.org/resource/පොත"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://arz.dbpedia.org/resource/كتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bs.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pnb.dbpedia.org/resource/کتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ne.dbpedia.org/resource/पुस्तक"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tl.dbpedia.org/resource/Aklat"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eo.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tt.dbpedia.org/resource/Китап"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://yo.dbpedia.org/resource/Ìwé"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://af.dbpedia.org/resource/Boek"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sq.dbpedia.org/resource/Libri"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ka.dbpedia.org/resource/წიგნი"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nl.dbpedia.org/resource/Boek_(document)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://id.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://th.dbpedia.org/resource/หนังสือ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mr.dbpedia.org/resource/पुस्तक"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sco.dbpedia.org/resource/Beuk"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mk.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cs.dbpedia.org/resource/Kniha"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sk.dbpedia.org/resource/Kniha"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ia.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://gl.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sah.dbpedia.org/resource/Кинигэ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ca.dbpedia.org/resource/Llibre"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://simple.dbpedia.org/resource/Book"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nds.dbpedia.org/resource/Book"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://vi.dbpedia.org/resource/Sách"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://als.dbpedia.org/resource/Buch"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ba.dbpedia.org/resource/Китап"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://qu.dbpedia.org/resource/Liwru"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ast.dbpedia.org/resource/Llibru"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ml.dbpedia.org/resource/പുസ്തകം"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mn.dbpedia.org/resource/Ном"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://new.dbpedia.org/resource/सफू"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://gd.dbpedia.org/resource/Leabhar"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uk.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ko.dbpedia.org/resource/책"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://no.dbpedia.org/resource/Bok"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ja.dbpedia.org/resource/本"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pa.dbpedia.org/resource/ਕਿਤਾਬ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pt.dbpedia.org/resource/Livro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ur.dbpedia.org/resource/کتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ms.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://la.dbpedia.org/resource/Liber"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mg.dbpedia.org/resource/Boky"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://wikidata.dbpedia.org/resource/Q571"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://io.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hi.dbpedia.org/resource/पुस्तक"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://is.dbpedia.org/resource/Bók"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://war.dbpedia.org/resource/Basahon"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eu.dbpedia.org/resource/Liburu"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://be.dbpedia.org/resource/Кніга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://zh.dbpedia.org/resource/图书"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sv.dbpedia.org/resource/Bok"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ckb.dbpedia.org/resource/کتێب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ku.dbpedia.org/resource/Pirtûk"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://kk.dbpedia.org/resource/Кітап"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bg.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://my.dbpedia.org/resource/စာအုပ်"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ar.dbpedia.org/resource/كتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tr.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitap"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cv.dbpedia.org/resource/Кĕнеке"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://da.dbpedia.org/resource/Bog"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nap.dbpedia.org/resource/Libbro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lmo.dbpedia.org/resource/Liber"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://de.dbpedia.org/resource/Buch"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://yi.dbpedia.org/resource/בוך"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nn.dbpedia.org/resource/Bok"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bn.dbpedia.org/resource/বই"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://he.dbpedia.org/resource/ספר"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fi.dbpedia.org/resource/Kirja"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://et.dbpedia.org/resource/Raamat"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://el.dbpedia.org/resource/Βιβλίο"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ru.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sr.dbpedia.org/resource/Књига"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://br.dbpedia.org/resource/Levr"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ce.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tg.dbpedia.org/resource/Китоб"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cy.dbpedia.org/resource/Llyfr"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fr.dbpedia.org/resource/Livre_(document)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pl.dbpedia.org/resource/Książka"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hu.dbpedia.org/resource/Könyv"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://scn.dbpedia.org/resource/Libbru"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://rdf.freebase.com/ns/m.0bt_c3"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lv.dbpedia.org/resource/Grāmata"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ht.dbpedia.org/resource/Liv_(pou_li)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uz.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitob"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sh.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://wa.dbpedia.org/resource/Live_(po_lére)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://su.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://es.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://an.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fa.dbpedia.org/resource/کتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ro.dbpedia.org/resource/Carte"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Book"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Books"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Documents"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Media_formats"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Paper_products"/></skos:Concept><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_173449"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449"/><edm:dataProvider>Harvard University Botany Libraries</edm:dataProvider><edm:hasView rdf:resource="http://www.archive.org/download/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL.pdf"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/173449"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:provider>Biodiversity Heritage Library</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:intermediateProvider>Internet Archive</edm:intermediateProvider></ore:Aggregation><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/provider/08711/item_173449"><dc:contributor>Bacon, Alice Elizabeth,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Bailey, L. H. (Liberty Hyde), 1858-1954</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Bailey, William Whitman, 1843-1914</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Baker, Harvey Humphrey, 1869-1915</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Barnes, Charles Reid, 1858-1910</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Bishop, James N.  (James Nathaniel),  185--190</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Brainerd, Ezra, 1844-1924</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Braithwaite, Robert, 1824-1917</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Briggs, George K.,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Britton, Elizabeth Gertrude Knight, , 1858-1934</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Britton, Nathaniel Lord, 1859-1934</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Brusati, Luigi,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Churchill, Joseph Richmond, , 1845-193</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Collins, Frank S. (Frank Shipley), 1848-1920</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Collins, J. Franklin (James Franklin) 1863-1940</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Crocker, George G. (George Glover), 1843-1913</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Cummings, Prentiss,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Cutter, Marshall Munroe,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Deane, Walter, 1848-1930</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Farlow, W. G. (William Gilson), 1844-1919</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Faxon, Charles Edward, 1846-1918</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Faxon, Edwin, , 1823-1898</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Faxon, Walter, 1848-1920</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Fernald, Merritt Lyndon, 1873-1950</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Floyd, Frederick Gillan, , 1869-1941</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Gibbs, W. B.,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Goodale, George L. (George Lincoln), 1839-1923</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Greenough, Charles P. (Charles Pelham), 1844-1924</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Grout, A. J. (Abel Joel), 1867-</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Hancock, John, 1737-1793</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Heller, Amos Arthur, 1867-1944</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Hodges, Almon Danforth, 1801-1878</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Holzinger, J. M. (John Michael), 1853-1929</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Hooker, Joseph Dalton, Sir, 1817-1911</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Huntington, John Warren,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Ingraham, Rhoby,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Jesup, Henry Griswold, , 1826-1903</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Jones, L. R. (Lewis Ralph), 1864-1945</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Kidder, Nathaniel Thayer, 1860-</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Lorenz, Annie,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Lorenz, William Albert,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Macoun, James Melville, 1862-1920</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Macoun, John, 1831-1920</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Morong, Thomas,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Rand, Edward Lothrop 1859-1924</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Richardson, W. L. (William Lambert), 1842-1932</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Robertson, J. Ross (John Ross), 1841-1918</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Robinson, Benjamin Lincoln, 1864-1935</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Ruskin, John, 1819-1900</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Sargent, Charles Sprague, 1841-1927</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Thaxter, Roland, 1858-1932</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Tilden, Josephine E. (Josephine Elizabeth)</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Tilton, George Henry, 1845-</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Trelease, William, 1857-1945</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>True, Rodney H. (Rodney Howard), 1866-1940</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Whorf, Edward Henry,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Williams, Blanche E. Wheeler,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Williams, Emile Francis, 1858-1929</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Harvard University,</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Quincy's Market (Boston, Mass.),</dc:contributor><dc:creator>Kennedy, George G.</dc:creator><dc:description xml:lang="en">Senders U-W, 1841-1918</dc:description><dc:format xml:lang="en">Print</dc:format><dc:language>en</dc:language><dc:relation xml:lang="en">Archives and specimens from the Boston Metropolitan Park Flora.</dc:relation><dc:relation xml:lang="en">Connecting content : a collaboration to link field notes to specimens and published literature.</dc:relation><dc:relation xml:lang="en">Papers of George Golding Kennedy.</dc:relation><dc:rights>Public domain. The BHL considers that this work is no longer under copyright protection.</dc:rights><dc:subject xml:lang="en">(George Golding),</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">1841-1918</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Autographs (manuscripts)</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Botanists</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Holographs (autographs)</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Kennedy, George G</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Postcards</dc:subject><dc:title xml:lang="en">George Golding Kennedy correspondence.</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">Text</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">Book</dc:type><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/bibliography/94780"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:europeanaProxy>false</edm:europeanaProxy><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_173449"/><edm:type>TEXT</edm:type></ore:Proxy><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/europeana/08711/item_173449"><dc:contributor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/agent/base/25274"></dc:contributor><dc:contributor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/agent/base/60779"></dc:contributor><dc:type rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/6"></dc:type><edm:europeanaProxy>true</edm:europeanaProxy><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/08711/item_173449"/><edm:type>TEXT</edm:type></ore:Proxy><edm:EuropeanaAggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/08711/item_173449"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449"/><edm:datasetName>08711_Ag_EU_BHL_usa</edm:datasetName><edm:country>United States of America</edm:country><edm:preview rdf:resource="https://api.europeana.eu/thumbnail/v2/url.json?uri=http%3A%2F%2Fiiif.archivelab.org%2Fiiif%2FGeorgeGoldingKe00KennL%241%2Ffull%2Ffull%2F0%2Fdefault.jpg&amp;type=TEXT"/><edm:landingPage rdf:resource="https://www.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449"/><edm:language>en</edm:language><edm:completeness>0</edm:completeness><dcterms:created>2017-08-02T22:11:08.745Z</dcterms:created><dcterms:modified>2017-08-02T23:58:45.816Z</dcterms:modified><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449#contentTier"/><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449#metadataTier"/></edm:EuropeanaAggregation><svcs:Service rdf:about="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GeorgeGoldingKe00KennL"><dcterms:conformsTo rdf:resource="http://iiif.io/api/image"></dcterms:conformsTo></svcs:Service><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449#contentTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-16T19:43:23.062Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_173449"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/contentTier4"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_173449#metadataTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-16T19:43:23.063Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_173449"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/metadataTierA"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation></rdf:RDF>