<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:owl="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#" xmlns:wgs84_pos="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:rdaGr2="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:ebucore="http://www.ebu.ch/metadata/ontologies/ebucore/ebucore#" xmlns:doap="http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#" xmlns:odrl="http://www.w3.org/ns/odrl/2/" xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:svcs="http://rdfs.org/sioc/services#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:dqv="http://www.w3.org/ns/dqv#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254"/><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/189254"><rdf:type rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/FullTextResource"/><ebucore:hasMimeType>text/html</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">89754</ebucore:fileByteSize></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.archive.org/download/GreenlandExpedi00Schm/GreenlandExpedi00Schm.pdf"><ebucore:hasMimeType>application/pdf</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">985622</ebucore:fileByteSize></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GreenlandExpedi00Schm$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"><ebucore:hasMimeType>image/jpeg</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">910945</ebucore:fileByteSize><ebucore:width rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">6100</ebucore:width><ebucore:height rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">4802</ebucore:height><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#2F4F4F</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#000000</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#696969</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#F5F5F5</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#C0C0C0</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#A9A9A9</edm:componentColor><ebucore:orientation rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#string">landscape</ebucore:orientation><dcterms:isReferencedBy rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GreenlandExpedi00Schm/manifest.json"></dcterms:isReferencedBy><svcs:has_service rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GreenlandExpedi00Schm"/></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pageimage/48512343"/><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/1937"><skos:prefLabel>1937</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/19xx_2_third"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:begin>Fri Jan 01 00:19:32 CET 1937</edm:begin><edm:end>Fri Dec 31 00:20:00 CET 1937</edm:end></edm:TimeSpan><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/19xx_2_third"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Середина 20-го века</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Mid 20th century</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/timespan/20"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:begin>Mon Jan 01 00:19:32 CET 1934</edm:begin><edm:end>Sat Dec 31 01:00:00 CET 1966</edm:end></edm:TimeSpan><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/19xx"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">20й век</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel>20..</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel>20??</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel>20e</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">20-th</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">20th</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">20th century</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">20e siècle</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">20de eeuw</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/AD2xxx"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:begin>Tue Jan 01 00:19:32 CET 1901</edm:begin><edm:end>Sun Dec 31 01:00:00 CET 2000</edm:end></edm:TimeSpan><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/AD2xxx"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Second millenium AD</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Second millenium AD, years 1001-2000</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">2e millénaire après J.-C.</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/ChronologicalPeriod"></dcterms:isPartOf></edm:TimeSpan><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/1676"><skos:altLabel xml:lang="de">Schwarz-weiss Photographien</skos:altLabel><skos:altLabel xml:lang="es">Fotografías en blanco y negro (obra visual)</skos:altLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Schwarz-weiß-Fotografien</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Черно-белая фотография</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bg">Черно-бяла фотография</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lt">Baltai juodos fotografijos</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Black-and-white photographs</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">Fotografie in bianco e nero</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">Photo en noir et blanch</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="zh">黑白照片</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="es">Fotografías en blanco y negro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="uk">Чорно-біла фотографія</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sl">Čiernobiela fotografia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pl">Fotografia czarno-biała</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">Sort-hvide fotografier</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">Fotografia blanc i negre</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">Zwartwitfoto</skos:prefLabel><skos:broader rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/1675"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bib.arts.kuleuven.be/photoVocabulary/-photoVocabulary-13001"/></skos:Concept><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/169"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">Zoologi</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hi">प्राणी विज्ञान</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Zoologie</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">Eläintiede</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="be">Заалогія</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Зоология</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pt">Zoologia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bg">Зоология</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lt">Zoologija</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hr">Zoologija</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">Zoologie</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">Zoológia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="yi">זאאלאגיע</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bs">Zoologija</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hy">Կենդանաբանություն</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ka">ზოოლოგია</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="uk">Зоологія</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sk">Zoológia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sl">Zoologija</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ga">Zó-eolaíocht</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">Zoologia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="mk">Зоологија</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sq">Zoologjia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sr">Зоологија</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sv">Zoologi</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ko">동물학</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gl">Zooloxía</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">Ζωολογία</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Zoology</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="is">Dýrafræði</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">Zoologia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="zh">动物学</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="es">Zoología</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">Zooloogia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="eu">Zoologia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cs">Zoologie</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ar">علم الحيوان</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cy">Söoleg</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ja">動物学</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="az">Zoologiya</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pl">Zoologia</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ro">Zoologie</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">Zoologi</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="he">זואולוגיה</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="tr">Zooloji</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">Zoölogie</skos:prefLabel><skos:note xml:lang="no">Zoologi er læren om dyr, og utgjør dermed et av biologiens fagområder. Ordet er avledet av gammelgresk ζῷον (zōon – dyr) og λόγος (logos – kunnskap). Kunnskap om dyr er trolig en av de eldste kunnskapene mennesket har, men ble først formalisert som et fag med opplysningstiden.Som med de øvrige biologiske fagene skjøt zoologien virkelig fart med Carl von Linnés klassifisering i Systema naturæ. Med Charles Darwins Artenes opprinnelse fra 1859 fikk zoologien en teoretisk underbygging som har preget zoologi og de øvrige biofagene siden.Fagets videre inndeling bygger på dyregruppene som studeres, bl.a.: entomologi – læren om insekter (evt. leddyr) herpetologi – læren om krypdyr (evt. også amfibier) iktyologi – læren om fisker konchologi eller malakologi – læren om bløtdyr mammalogi – læren om pattedyr ornitologi – læren om fugler kynologi – læren om hundedyr (tamhund, ulv og rødrev)Dyrenes inndeling: se dyr.Se også Norsk Zoologisk Forening</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hi">प्राणी विज्ञान या जंतु विज्ञान (en:Zoology) (जीव विज्ञान की शाखा है जो जानवरों और उनके जीवन, शरीर, विकास और वर्गीकरण (classification) से सम्बन्धित होती है ।</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="de">Die Zoologie (gr. ζῷον [zóon], „Tier“, „lebendes Wesen“ und λόγος [lógos], „Lehre“), im weitesten auch Tierkunde, ist die Disziplin der Biologie, deren Forschungsgegenstand die Tiere (Animalia), insbesondere die Vielzelligen Tiere (Metazoa) sind. Die Zoologie untersucht mit verschiedenen naturwissenschaftlichen Methoden Gestalt und Körperbau (Morphologie, Anatomie), Lebenstätigkeiten (Physiologie), Entwicklungs- und Stammesgeschichte (einschließlich Paläozoologie), Erbgeschehen (Genetik), Umweltbeziehungen (Ökologie), Verbreitung (Zoogeographie) sowie das Verhalten (Verhaltensbiologie) der Tiere und erstellt eine Systematik des Tierreiches. Die meisten Zoologen haben heute Biologie als Studienfach studiert. Aber auch Tierärzte, Forstwissenschaftler und Geographen arbeiten teilweise als Zoologen.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fi">Eläintiede eli zoologia (kreik. zoon, eläin; logos, tieto) on eläinten rakennetta, toimitaa, kehitystä, suhteita, luokittelua ja eläimistöä käsittelevä tieteenala, jonka osa-alueita ovat esimerkiksi eläinekologia, eläinfysiologia ja -anatomia ja etologia (eläinten käyttäytyminen). Eläintiede on biologian osa-alue, ja se on osaltaan läheisessä yhteydessä solubiologiaan, biokemiaan ja (perinnöllisyystieteeseen).Eri eläinryhmiin kohdistuvan tutkimuksen perusteella erotetaan myös alatieteitä, kuten esimerkiksi mammalogia (nisäkkäät), ornitologia (linnut), iktyologia (kalat), entomologia (hyönteiset) ja protozoologia (alkueläimet).</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="be">Заалогія — раздзел біялогіі, навука, якая вывучае жывёл.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ru">Зоология (от др.-греч. ζῷον — животное и λόγος — учение) — биологическая наука, предметом изучения которой являются представители царства животных.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pt">A zoologia (proveniente do grego Ζώο, zoon "animal", e λόγος, -logos "estudo") é a ciência que estuda os animais.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bg">Зоологията е наука за животните. Тя изучава формата и устройството на животните, процесите, които се извършват в тях, взаимоотношенията им с околната среда, индивидуалното им и историческо развитие.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lt">Zoologija (gr. zoon – gyvūnas, logos – mokslas) – biologijos šaka, tirianti gyvūnus.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hr">Zoologija (od grčkog zoon "živo biće") je biološka disciplina koja se bavi proučavanjem životinja, odnosno, oblikom i građom tijela (morfologija, anatomija), životnim aktivnostima (psihologijom), razvojem i porijeklom (uključujući paleontologiju), nasljednim odlikama (genetikom), odnosom s okolišem (ekologijom), rasprostranjenošću (zoogeografijom) i ponašanjem životinja. Sistematiku životinja pogledaj pod sistematika životinjskog carstva.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lv">Zooloģija (grieķu: ζῷον, zōon - dzīvnieks; λόγος, logos - jēdziens, mācība) ir bioloģijas nozare, kurā nodarbojas ar dzīvnieku pētīšanu. Mūsdienās tas vairāk ir zinātņu komplekss, tas ir, zooloģija apvieno vairākas citas nozares. To iedala šādās nozarēs: anatomija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta dzīvnieku makroskopiskā uzbūve; histoloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta audu mikroskopiskā struktūra; citoloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta šūnu uzbūve un tās funkcijas; fizioloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta organismu funkcijas; ģenētika - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta iedzimtība; ekoloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta dzīvnieku un vides mijiedarbība (attiecas galvenokārt uz sauszemes dzīvniekiem); hidrobioloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta ūdens dzīvnieku mijiedarbība ar apkārtējo vidi; parazitoloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīti parazīti embrioloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta dīgļa attīstība olā vai mātes organismā; etoloģija - nozare, kurā tiek pētīta dzīvnieku uzvedība</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fr">La zoologie (des termes grecs ζῷον, zôon, animal, et λόγος, logos, le discours) est la science qui étudie les animaux. Regroupant plusieurs disciplines et utilisant de nombreuses techniques, cette science s'est lentement élaborée au cours des siècles depuis la préhistoire. Historiquement, les premières réflexions scientifiques concernant la zoologie qui nous ont été transmises sont celles d'Aristote. Les tentatives de classification des espèces animales ont été nombreuses et souvent remaniées depuis cette époque.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hu">A zoológia vagy állattan az állatok rendszerezésével, állatfajok és közösségeik megismerésével foglalkozó tudomány, a biológia résztudománya. Állatnak az állatok országába (Regnum: Animalia) tartozó többsejtű heterotróf anyagcseréjű élőlényeket nevezzük.A zoológia szó a görög Ζωο, zoon ("állat") és λογος, -logosz ("tudomány") szóösszetételből ered.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="yi">זאָאָלאָגיִע איז די װיסנשאַפֿט װאָס שטודירט די חיות. דאס ווארט זאאלאגיע שטאמט פון אלטגריכיש ζῷον (זאאן, “בעל חי”) + λόγος (לאגאס, “וויסן”).די שטודיע פון זאאלאגיע נעמט זיך פון נאטורלעכער היסטאריע, וואס אריסטו און גאלען האבן שטודירט אין אוראלטע צייטן. א וויסנשאפטלער אין דעם פעלד פון זאאלאגיע הייסט א זאאלאג.זאאלאגיע איז כולל די פאלגנדע אפטיילונגען: אנאטאמיע פיזיאלאגיע עטאלאגיע</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bs">Zoologija je grana biologije koja se bavi proučavanjem životinjskih vrsta, odnosno, oblikom i građom tijela (morfologija, anatomija), životnim aktivnostima (psihologijom), razvojem i porijeklom (uključujući paleontologiju), nasljednim odlikama (genetikom), odnosom s okolišem (ekologijom), rasprostranjenošću (zoogeografijom) i ponašanjem životinja.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hy">Կենդանաբանությունը կամ զոոլոգիան գիտություն է կենդանիների մասին։ Կենսաբանության բաժին է, ուսումնասիրում է կենդանիների բազմազանությունը, տարածումը, կազմությունը և կենսագործունեության օրինաչափությունները։ Ժամանակակից կենդաբանությունը գիտությունների մի համալիր է, իր մեջ ընդգրկում է մասնաճյուղային շատ դիսցիպլիններ, որոնց ուսումնասիրության առարկան մի դեպքում կենդանիների կառուցվածքային, կենսագործունեության կամ զարգացման երևույթներն են, մյուս դեպքում՝ կարգաբանական որոշակի աստիճանում գտնվող կենդանիները։ Կենդանաբանական գիտությունների մեջ դասվում են. կենդանիների կարգաբանությունը, որն ուսումնասիրում է նրանց տեսակային բազմազանությունը, բացահայտում պատմական զարգացման ուղին և այլն կենդանիների սաղմնաբանությունը, որն զբաղվում է անհատական զարգացման (օնտոգենեզ) առանձնահատկություններով կենդանիների ձևաբանությունը, որն ուսումնասիրում է կենդանիների արտաքին և ներքին կառուցվածքները էկոլոգիան, որը բացահայտում է օրգանիզմի և արտաքին միջավայրի միջև եղած կապը կենդանիների աշխարհագրությունը, որը բացահայտում է կենդանիների տարածվածությունը ջրում և ցամաքում, Երկրի առանձին մասերի կենդանական աշխարհի կազմությունն ու ծագման առանձնահատկությունները։ Կենդանիների ֆիզիոլոգիան, որը հետազոտում է կենդանի օրգանիզմում կատարվող կենսագործունեության օրինաչափությունները և այլն։20-րդ դարում նշված գիտություններին ավելացան ևս երկուսը՝ գենետիկան և մոլեկուլային կենսաբանությունը: Կենդանաբանության մեջ են դասվում նաև այն բաժինները, որոնք ուսումնասիրում են կարգաբանական մեծ խմբերի մեջ մտնող կենդանիների տեսակները, օրինակ, պրոտոզոոլոգիան ուսումնասիրում է միաբջիջ կենդանիներին, միջատաբանությունը՝ միջատներին, իխթիոլոգիան՝ ձկներին, օրնիտոլոգիան՝ թռչուններին և այլն։ Կենդանիներին վերաբերող այնպիսի տեղեկություններ, որոնք անհրաժեշտ էին նրանց որսալու, ընտելացնելու կամ բուծելու, նրանցից պաշտպանվելու համար, մարդիկ հավաքել և ունեցել են հազարամյակների ընթացքում։ Սակայն կենդանաբանությունը, որպես գիտություն, ծնունդ է առել Հին Հունաստանում՝ կապված Արիստոտելի անվան հետ։ Արիստոտելն իր աշխատություններում տեղեկություններ է հայտնում կենդանիների շուրջ 500 տեսակի մասին, որոնց միավորել է մի քանի խոշոր խմբերում։ Մանրադիտակի գյուտն ու օգտագործումը հանգուցային նշանակություն ունեցող իրադարձություն էին կենդանաբանության և ընդհանրապես օրգանական աշխարհի ճանաչման համար։ Լևենհուկը հայտնաբերեց միաբջիջ պարզագույն կենդանիների աշխարհը, բացահայտվեցին կենդանիների բջջային կազմության առանձնահատկությունները, սեռական բազմացման բջջաբանական գաղտնիքները։ Այդ ժամանակաշրջանում հիմնադրվեցին կենդանական աշխարհի զարգացման և ժամանակակից դասակարգման հիմունքները, լույս տեսավ շվեդացի բնագետ Կարլ Լիննեյի «Բնության համակարգ» աշխատությունը, որտեղ գիտությանը հայտնի կենդանիներն ստացան մինչև օրս պահպանվող կրկնակի անվանումը։ Կենդանաբանության մեջ հեղաշրջող իրադարձություն հանդիսացավ կենդանիների բջջային կազմության և օրգանական աշխարհի զարգացման էվոլյուցիոն ուսմունքի ստեղծումը։ Նշվածներն ուղեցույց հանդիսացան կենդանիների ֆիլոգենետիկ զարգացման տեսության և բիոգենետիկ օրենքի ստեղծման համար։ 18-19-րդ դարերում կուտակված գիտելիքներից ծնունդ առան էկոլոգիայի, սաղմնաբանության, ձևաբանության նոր էվոլյուցիոն-համեմատական ուղղություններ, որոնց ստեղծման ու զարգացման ասպարեզում մեծ դեր են ունեցել ռուս կենդանաբաններ Ի.Ռուլեն, Ն.Սևերցովը, Ի.Մեչնիկովը և ուրիշներ։</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ka">ზოოლოგია (ბერძნ. ζῴον — „ცხოველი“, λόγος — „მოძღვრება“) — მეცნიერება, რომელიც ცხოველთა სამყაროს სწავლობს. უმაღლეს სკოლაში ზოოლოგიის სწავლების პრაქტიკაში მიღებულია ზოოლოგიის როგორც ერთი მთლიანი მეცნიერების დაყოფა ორ განყოფილებად: უხერხემლოთა ზოოლოგიად და ხერხემლიანთა ზოოლოგიად.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="uk">Зооло́гія (грец. ζωο та λογος) — це біологічна дисципліна, що вивчає навколишній світ тварин та їхні взаємозв'язки з довкіллям. Досліджує біологічну різноманітність світу тварин, систематизує й класифікує тварин, вивчає їх морфологічну та анатомічну будову, закономірності їхнього індивідуального та історичного розвитку, географічне поширення, функціональну біогеоценотичну й біосферну роль, зв'язки з середовищем. Поділяється на зоологію безхребетних і зоологію хребетних. Основна мета зоології як науки — одержання й узагальнення нових знань про рівні організації та різноманітність тварин, стан їхніх ресурсів, опрацювання методів раціонального використання й охорони тварин та їх угруповань.Основні зоологічні дисципліни: науки про окремі аспекти будови і життя тварин — систематика, екологія, морфологія, фізіологія, гістологія,, ембріологія тварин, зоогеографія, палеозоологія, філогенія, етологія, генетика, науки про певні, найбільші і найважливіші групи тварин — акарологія, герпетологія, етологія, іхтіологія, карцинологія, малакологія, оологія, орнітологія, протозоологія, теріологія, та ін.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sk">Zoológia je veda, ktorá študuje živočíchy. Osoba venujúca sa profesionálne zoológii sa nazýva zoológ.Delí sa na viacero disciplín: Anatómia – veda o vnútornej stavbe tela živočícha. Cytológia – skúma bunky, prípadne jednotlivé bunkové organely. Embryológia – študuje vývoj zárodku (embrya). Etológia – zaoberá sa správaním živočíchov. Fyziológia – skúma životné procesy prebiehajúce v tele živočícha. Histológia – skúma živočíšne tkanivá. Morfológia – zaoberá sa vonkajšou stavbou a tvarom tela živočícha a jeho jednotlivých častí. Organológia – skúma jednotlivé orgány, ich špecifickú stavbu a funkciu. Taxonómia (systematika) – zaoberá sa triedením živočíchov do kategórií (taxónov) na základe ich fylogenetickej príbuznosti.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sl">Zoologíja (grško zoon - živo bitje + λόγος: lógos - veda + pripona ια) je naravoslovna veda, poddisciplina biologije, ki preučuje živali. Preučuje njihov način hranjenja, razmnoževanja, zgradbo telesa ter telesni razvoj in mnogo drugih stvari. Ker je zoologija zaradi raznolikosti živali preobsežna, da bi jo lahko obvladal posameznik, se nadalje deli v več poddisciplin, ki se razlikujejo bodisi po preučevani živalski skupini (ornitologija, entomologija, herpetologija itd.), bodisi po pristopu (ekologija, etologija, fiziologija, paleozoologija, zoogeografija itd.).Znanstvenik, ki deluje na področju zoologije, je zoolog.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ga">Is í an Zó-eolaíocht (nó an mhíoleolaíocht) (ón Ghréigis: ζῴον, zoion, "ainmhí"; agus λόγος, logos, "eolas") an brainse den bhitheolaíocht ina ndéantar staidéar ar bheatha ainmhithe. Rangaítear na hainmhithe ó aimsir Arastatail de réir cosúlachtaí seachtracha is timpeallachta. Chuir Linnaeus go mór leis an rangú, ionas go n-ainmítear gach ainmhí (is planda) le dhá ainm Laidineacha, ceann don ghné is ceann don speiceas. Leath réimse na míoleolaíochta go mór le cur i bhfeidhm modhanna oibre is tuiscintí as sutheolaíocht, fiseolaíocht, cíteolaíocht, bithcheimic, géineolaíocht is éiceolaíocht. Ba mhór an chabhair modhanna turgnamhacha nua freisin, agus forbairtí in ionstraimí de shaghas micreascóp leictreonach.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ca">La zoologia (del grec ζῷον (zoon) = animal, ésser viu i λόγος (logos) = paraula, ciència), és la branca de la biologia que tracta tot allò que fa referència als animals incloent-hi la seva estructura, embriologia, evolució, classificació biològica, etologia i distribució, ja siguin animals vius o extints.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="mk">Зоологијата е она поле од биологијата кое се занимава со проучување на животните. Како наука, таа се дели на општ дел или општа зоологија и специјален дел или систематика на животните. Општата зоологија ги проучува сите појави во животинскиот свет кои имаат општо значење, а систематиката на животните се обидува сите животни, според различните карактеристики, да ги подели во одреден број разновидни систематски категории заради полесно распознавање и проучување.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sq">Zoologjia (gr. ζῷον [zóon],„Kafshë“, „Gjallesë“ dhe λόγος [lógos], „mësim“), ështe nje disciplinë e Biologjisë , që studion gjallesat (Animalia), posaqërisht ato shumëqelizore(Metazoa). Zoologjia kontrollon me metodat e saj shkencore formën dhe ndertimin e trupit (Morfologji, Anatomi), Statistikat e jetës (Fiziologji), Zhvillim-filogjenezë (përfshirë edhe palazoologjinë), Trashigimi (Gjenetika), Marrëdheniet me mjedis (Ekologji), Përhapja (Zoogjeografi) dhe sjellje (Biologjia e sjelljes) të kafshëve dhe krijon një sistematikë të botës shtazore.Shumica e zoologëve e kanë studiuar biologjinë. Por edhe veterinarët, shkenctarët pyjor dhe gjeografët punojnë pjesërisht me zoologjinë.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sr">Зоологија (од старогрчког ζῷον „живо биће“ и λόγος „наука, знање") је биолошка дисциплина која се бави проучавањем животиња, односно, обликом и грађом тела (морфологија, анатомија), животним активностима (психологијом), развојем и пореклом (укључујући палеонтологију), наследним одликама (генетиком), односима са околином (екологијом), распрострањеношћу (зоогеографијом) и понашањем животиња. Систематику животиња погледај под систематика животињског царства.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sv">Zoologi (från grekiskans: ζῴον, zoion, "djur"; och λόγος, logos, "kunskap eller vetenskap") är läran om djurriket efter biologiska riktlinjer. En person som är utbildad i zoologi kallas zoolog.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ko">동물학(動物學, zoology)은 생물학의 한 갈래로써 동물의 신체 구조, 역할, 성질, 그리고 진화에 초점을 둔 학문이다.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="gl">A zooloxía (dos termos do grego antigo ζῷον zõon, 'animal', e λόγος lógos, 'discurso', 'tratado') é a ciencia que estuda os animais, incluíndo a súa estrutura, embrioloxía, evolución, clasificación, hábitos e distribución de todas as especies.Reunindo varias disciplinas e utilizando numerosas técnicas, esta ciencia foi lentamente elaborada a través do paso dos tempos, desde a máis remota antigüidade. Historicamente, as primeiras reflexións precientíficas referidas á zooloxía que chegaron até nós, son as do filósofo grego Aristóteles, do IV a.C.. As tentativas de clasificación das especeies animais foron numerosas e frecuentemente modificadas desde aquela lonxana época.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="el">Η Ζωολογία (από τις λέξεις ζώο + λόγος) είναι ο κλάδος της βιολογίας που ασχολείται με τη μελέτη των ζώων.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="en">Zoology /zoʊˈɒlədʒi/, or animal biology, is the branch of biology that relates to the animal kingdom, including the structure, embryology, evolution, classification, habits, and distribution of all animals, both living and extinct. The term is derived from Ancient Greek ζῷον, zōon, i.e. "animal" and λόγος, logos, i.e. "knowledge, study".</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="is">Dýrafræði er undirgrein líffræðinnar sem fæst við rannsóknir á dýrum. Þeir sem leggja stund á greinina kallast dýrafræðingar.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="it">La zoologia (dal greco: zoon = animale; logos = discorso) è la disciplina biologica che si occupa dello studio degli animali (o metazoi) e dei protozoi. Questi ultimi, pur non essendo veri e propri animali, per somiglianze biologiche ed affinità filogenetica, in passato venivano considerati membri effettivi del regno animale e che, solo in seguito, furono trasferiti al più accettato regno dei protisti.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="zh">动物学作为生物学的一大分支，研究范围涉及动物的形态、生理构造、生活习性、发展及进化史、遗传及行为特征、分布、以及与环境间相互关系。您也可以通过以下链接找到动物的分类。專門研究動物學的學者，稱為動物學家。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="es">Zoología (del griego «ζωον» zoon = "animal", y «-λογία» -logía, tratado, estudio, ciencia) es la disciplina biológica que se encarga del estudio de los animales.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="et">Zooloogia on bioloogia haru, mis uurib loomi.Zooloogia harud on entomoloogia, malakoloogia, ihtüoloogia, ornitoloogia, terioloogia jt.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="eu">Zoologia (grezieratik ζῷον [zóon], "animalia", eta λόγος [lógos], "ikasketa"), animaliak aztertu eta ikertzen dituen zientzia da. Zoologoek milioi bat espezie baino gehiago identifikatu dituzte dagoeneko (1,3 milioi animalia-espezie, gutxi gorabehera). Kopuru horrek nabarmen gainditzen ditu landareen espeziena (350.000 inguru).Animaliak sailkatzeko zoologiak hainbat tresna erabiltzen ditu. Antzina, gaur egungo aurrerapen teknologikorik ez zegoenean, irizpide morfologikoak eta anatomikoak erabakigarriak ziren animalia bat talde batean edo bestean sailkatzeko orduan. Geroago, hibridazioaren kontzeptua agertu zen Cuvierren eskutik: bi animalia espezie berekoak ziren ondorengo ugalkorrak edukitzeko gai baldin baziren. Orokorrean, Cuvier-en irizpideak zutik dirau oraindik, salbuespen batzuek betetzen ez badute ere.Mikroskopioaren agerpenak histologiaren garrantzia taxonomia-ikerketarako agerian jarri zuen. Bestalde, eboluzioaren teoriaren garapenak enbriologia konparatiboaren ikerkuntza bultzatu zuen, oso lagungarri izango zena zoologiarentzat ikuspuntu berri bat zekarrelako.Genetikaren aurkikuntzek, besteak beste, aplikazioak ere izan dituzte biologiaren adar honetan, espezie bateko animalia guztiek antzeko kariotipoa dutelako. Fisiologia eta biokimikaren ekarpenek ez dira nolanahikoak izan: gaur egun biokimika konparatuak, esaterako, informazio ugari ematen du espezieak desberdintzeko, irizpide kimikoak aplikatuz.Etologiaren agerpenak, azkenik, espezieak definitzen ere lagundu du, portaeraren arau gehienak berezkoak baitira talde bereko banakoen artean.Ikertzen duen animali taldearen arabera zoologiak adar desberdinak ditu: entomologia (intsektuak) helmintologia (zizareak) herpetologia (narrastiak eta anfibioak) iktiologia (arrainak) malakologia (moluskuak) mastozoologia (ugaztunak) ornitologia (hegaztiak) paleozoologia (animalien fosilak) primatologia (primateak)</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cs">Zoologie je přírodní věda spadající do okruhu biologických věd, zabývající se studiem organismů z říše živočichů (Animalia). Tradičně se zoologie zabývá také studiem prvoků (protozoologií), kteří v současnosti již ovšem nejsou považováni za živočichy. Název pochází z řečtiny: ζοον (zoon) = zvíře, živočich, tvor; λόγος = slovoZoologii lze dělit na všeobecnou zoologii, zabývající se obecnými jevy a zákonitostmi vlastními všem nebo mnoha skupinám živočichů, a systematickou zoologii, která studuje jednotlivé skupiny živočichů. Aplikovaná zoologie přenáší teoretické znalosti zoologie do praxe (např. lesnická zoologie).Za zakladatele zoologie je považován Aristoteles. Odborníci zabývající se zoologií se nazývají zoologové.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ar">علم الحيوان Zoology (باليونانية zoo'n حيوان وlogos كلمة أو دراسة) هو العلم الذي يتناول دراسة الحيوان من حيث كل من:التركيب ، الوظيفة ، طرق التعايش ، وانتقال المادة الوراثية على مدى الأجيال. وهو أحد فرعى علم الأحياء Biology (الفرع الآخر هو علم النبات Botany.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cy">Astudiaeth anifeiliaid yw söoleg neu sooleg.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ja">動物学（どうぶつがく、英語：zoology）は動物を対象とする学問。現在では生物学の一分野とされ、自然史学の一部門に由来する。古典的には物質を鉱物、植物と動物にわけることが一般的だったため、博物学も鉱物学、植物学、動物学にわけられていた。『動物誌』などを記した古代ギリシアのアリストテレスを動物学の祖と見ることができる。発生学、生理学、生態学、動物行動学、形態学などの視点から研究が行われてきた。近年では生物の分類が様変わりし、研究分野が細分化されたため、動物学の内容が多様化し、この語が用いられる頻度は低くなった。対象とする分類群によって哺乳類学、昆虫学、魚類学などと分けられることもある。動物の古生物を対象とする場合は古動物学と呼ぶ。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="az">Zoologiya (yunan. ζῷον; zoon, "heyvan" + yunan. λόγος, "loqos", "bilgi") Heyvanlar aləmindən bəhs edən elm. Zoologiya heyvanlar aləminin müxtəlifliyini, onların bədən quruluşunu və həyat fəaliyyətini, yaşadığı mühitlə əlaqəsini, fərdi və tarixi inkişaf qanunauyğunluqlarını öyrənir. Heyvanlar aləmində ən ali sistematik vahid tip adlanır. Hazırda heyvanlar 23 tipə ayrılır.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pl">Zoologia (od gr. zoon = zwierzę, i logos = słowo, myśl, rozumowanie) – nauka o zwierzętach, czyli wszystkich żywych organizmach zdolnych do przemieszczania i odżywiania się (z wyjątkiem mikroorganizmów), a także ich zachowaniach i budowie.W skład zoologii wchodzą nauki zajmujące się poszczególnymi grupami zwierząt, m.in.: protozoologia, entomologia, ichtiologia, herpetologia, ornitologia i teriologia. Gałęziami zoologii są także nauki o zwierzętach poprzednich epok (paleozoologia i paleozoogeografia), o strukturze populacji zwierzęcych i ich wzajemnym oddziaływaniu na środowisko (ekologia) czy zachowaniu i psychice zwierząt (etologia, zoopsychologia) oraz nauki obejmujące systematykę wszystkich organizmów zwierzęcych, także nauki zajmujące się budową i funkcjami ciała zwierząt, np.: anatomia, fizjologia, morfologia, embriologia, cytologia.Pierwsze prace z dziedziny zoologii są autorstwa Arystotelesa (IV w. p.n.e.). Spośród około 300 jego dzieł do najważniejszych należą: Zoologia (Historia naturalna zwierząt), O częściach zwierząt oraz O pochodzeniu zwierząt. Arystoteles jest nazywany ojcem zoologii.Rewolucyjny wpływ na postęp zoologii wywarła teoria ewolucji Darwina, ogłoszona w wydanym w 1859 roku dziele O powstawaniu gatunków drogą doboru naturalnego, która przyczyniła się do wyjaśnienia m.in. procesów i zjawisk z zakresu ewolucji i embriologii, a także anatomii porównawczej.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ro">Zoologia este o ramură a biologiei care se ocupă cu studiul organismelor care sunt încadrate în regnul Animalia. Actual, organismele sunt clasificate în 5 regnuri: Monera, Protozoa, Fungi, Plantae și Animalia. Termenul de zoologie provine de la cuvintele grecești zoon = animal și logos = stiinta. Zoologia studiază structura, funcțiile, comportarea, dezvoltarea, filogenia, clasificarea, distribuirea, și utilizarea animalelor. La dezvoltatarea Zoologiei au adus contribuții remarcabile și cercetările unor savanți români, precum Emil Racoviță, Grigore Antipa și alții.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="da">Zoologi er videnskaben om dyrene. (gr. zoo = Levende væsen + logi = Viden). En person som beskræfter sig med zoologi kaldes en zoolog.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="he">זואולוגיה היא ענף במדעי החיים העוסק בחקר בעלי החיים. מקור המילה ביוונית: זוֹאוֹן (ζώον) פירושו "חיה", לוגיה (λογία) פירושו "תורה". איש מדע העוסק בזואולוגיה הוא זואולוג.הזואולוגיה חוקרת את מבנה גופם של בעלי חיים, את אורחות חייהם, דרכי גידולם והתרבותם ואת היחסים בינם לבין סביבת חייהם ובינם לבין בעלי חיים אחרים. הזואולוגיה, אם כן, משתמשת, או כוללת בתוכה, תחומים רבים אחרים בביולוגיה, כגון אנטומיה, פיזיולוגיה, אבולוציה ואקולוגיה.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="tr">Zooloji (hayvan bilimi) zoo (hayvanlar topluluğu) ve logos (bilim) sözcüklerinin birleştirilmesiyle türetilmiş bir terim olup biyolojinin hayvanları çeşitli yönleriyle inceleyen bir bilim dalıdır. Eski çağlarda yaşamış ve bugün soyu tükenmiş birçok tür ve günümüzde yaşayan bütün hayvanlar, zoolojinin inceleme alanına girmektedir. İnsanların merak ve araştırma eğilimiyle ortaya çıkan zoolojinin insanlık tarihi kadar eski olma olasılığı vardır. İlk olarak Mısır, İran ve Yunan kültürlerinde hayvanları incelemelere ait fikirler, yazılı belgeler görülmektedir. Geçmişte hayvanların basit tanımı ve işlevi, embriyonik gelişimi, beslenmeleri, sağlığı, davranışları, kalıtım ve evrimleriyle; çevreleri ve diğer canlılarla olan etkileşim ve iletişimlerini, incelemeye başlamış olup, daha sonraları altdallara ayrılacak kadar gelişmiştir. Günümüzde her bilimadamı bu bilimin altdallarından biriyle ilgilenmekte, ve ilgilendiği dala göre adlandırılmaktadır.Zooloji, tıptan, toplum sağlığından, ziraatten ve toplum bilimlerinden, uzay bilimlerine kadar tüm alanları ilgilendirmekte, bu alanlarda yapılacak herhangi bir araştırma biyoloji, ve dolayısıyla zooloji kapsamına girmektedir.Tüm düşünceler, tüm araştırmalar kökünü doğadan almakta olduğu gerçeği, zoolojinin neden bu kadar önemli bir bilim dalı olduğunu anlatmaktadır. Zooloji, Taksonomik ve Taksonomik olmayan alt dallara ayrılır. Taksonomik kısım, Protozooloji (Tek hücreliler), Helmintoloji (Solucanlar), Malakoloji (Kabuklular, Entomoloji (Böcekler) gibi bazı omurgasızları, Ihtiyoloji (Balıklar), Herpotoloji (Kurbağa ve Sürüngenler), Ornitoloji (Kuşlar), Memeliler gibi bazı omurgalıları taksonomik yönden inceler. Taksonomik yönden olmayan kısım ise, tüm hayvansal organizmaların morfolojisi ve fizyolojisidir.Zooloji veterinerlikle bağdaştırılabilir.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="nl">Zoölogie of dierkunde is een discipline in de biologie die dieren bestudeert. De naam is afgeleid van de Oudgriekse woorden ζῷον (zōon, "dier") en λόγος (logos, lett. "woord", in de wetenschap vaak vertaald als "kunde").</skos:note><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sk.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoológia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pnb.dbpedia.org/resource/زوالوجی"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://an.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoolochía"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ko.dbpedia.org/resource/동물학"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lt.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologija"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://wikidata.dbpedia.org/resource/Q431"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://br.dbpedia.org/resource/Loenoniezh"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tg.dbpedia.org/resource/Ҷонваршиносӣ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ta.dbpedia.org/resource/விலங்கியல்"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://my.dbpedia.org/resource/သတ္တဗေဒ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://oc.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ka.dbpedia.org/resource/ზოოლოგია"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ga.dbpedia.org/resource/Zó-eolaíocht"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://es.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoología"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ro.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologie"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ar.dbpedia.org/resource/علم_الحيوان"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://zh.dbpedia.org/resource/动物学"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ru.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоология"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ms.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologi"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://kk.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоология"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fi.dbpedia.org/resource/Eläintiede"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fr.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologie"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ja.dbpedia.org/resource/動物学"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://id.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologi"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://simple.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoology"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ca.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pl.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://vi.dbpedia.org/resource/Động_vật_học"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tt.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоология"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://gl.dbpedia.org/resource/Zooloxía"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sl.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologija"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nn.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologi"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://th.dbpedia.org/resource/สัตววิทยา"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fy.dbpedia.org/resource/Soölogy"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://kn.dbpedia.org/resource/ಪ್ರಾಣಿಶಾಸ್ತ್ರ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ia.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cs.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologie"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q431"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sco.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoology"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://gu.dbpedia.org/resource/પ્રાણીશાસ્ત્ર"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://si.dbpedia.org/resource/සත්ත්ව_විද්‍යාව"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://qu.dbpedia.org/resource/Suwuluhiya"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pt.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mr.dbpedia.org/resource/प्राणिशास्त्र"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://is.dbpedia.org/resource/Dýrafræði"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eo.dbpedia.org/resource/Bestoscienco"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hr.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologija"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sh.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologija"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ml.dbpedia.org/resource/ജന്തുശാസ്ത്രം"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ur.dbpedia.org/resource/حیوانیات"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cy.dbpedia.org/resource/Söoleg"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mk.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоологија"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://vo.dbpedia.org/resource/Nimav"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uz.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologiya"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sr.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоологија"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://yi.dbpedia.org/resource/זאאלאגיע"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://et.dbpedia.org/resource/Zooloogia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ast.dbpedia.org/resource/Zooloxía"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://no.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologi"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://de.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologie"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://el.dbpedia.org/resource/Ζωολογία"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://te.dbpedia.org/resource/జంతుశాస్త్రం"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bn.dbpedia.org/resource/প্রাণিবিজ্ঞান"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uk.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоологія"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://scn.dbpedia.org/resource/Zûluggìa"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://he.dbpedia.org/resource/זואולוגיה"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://io.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologio"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nds.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologie"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://it.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eu.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lv.dbpedia.org/resource/Zooloģija"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sv.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologi"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ku.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoolojî"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sah.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоология"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://arz.dbpedia.org/resource/زولوجيا"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sw.cyc.com/concept/Mx4rvVj8MZwpEbGdrcN5Y29ycA"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hy.dbpedia.org/resource/Կենդանաբանություն"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://war.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoolohiya"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://az.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologiya"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lb.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologie"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tr.dbpedia.org/resource/Zooloji"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://af.dbpedia.org/resource/Dierkunde"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sq.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologjia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://la.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fa.dbpedia.org/resource/جانورشناسی"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bs.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologija"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://jv.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologi"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://da.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoologi"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bg.dbpedia.org/resource/Зоология"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nl.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoölogie"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hu.dbpedia.org/resource/Zoológia"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tl.dbpedia.org/resource/Soolohiya"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://rdf.freebase.com/ns/m.088tb"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hi.dbpedia.org/resource/प्राणी_विज्ञान"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://be.dbpedia.org/resource/Заалогія"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Zoology"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Zoology"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Biology"/></skos:Concept><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_189254"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254"/><edm:dataProvider>Smithsonian Institution Archives</edm:dataProvider><edm:hasView rdf:resource="http://www.archive.org/download/GreenlandExpedi00Schm/GreenlandExpedi00Schm.pdf"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/189254"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GreenlandExpedi00Schm$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GreenlandExpedi00Schm$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:provider>Biodiversity Heritage Library</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:intermediateProvider>Internet Archive</edm:intermediateProvider></ore:Aggregation><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/provider/08711/item_189254"><dc:creator>Bartlett, Bob, 1875-1946</dc:creator><dc:creator>Schmitt, Waldo L., (Waldo Lasalle) 1887-1977</dc:creator><dc:format xml:lang="en">Print</dc:format><dc:identifier>10.5962/bhl.title.107406</dc:identifier><dc:publisher>1937</dc:publisher><dc:language>en</dc:language><dc:relation xml:lang="en">SIA RU007231</dc:relation><dc:relation xml:lang="en">Smithsonian Field Book Project : an initiative to improve access to field book content that documents natural history</dc:relation><dc:relation xml:lang="en">Waldo L. Schmitt Papers, 1907-1978</dc:relation><dc:rights>No known copyright restrictions as determined by scanning institution.</dc:rights><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Bartlett Arctic Expeditions (1928-1947)</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Black-and-white photographs</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Effie M. Morrissey (Schooner)</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Field notes</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Greenland Expedition of 1937</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Zoology</dc:subject><dc:title xml:lang="en">Greenland Expedition of 1937 : photographs, some identified</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">Text</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">Issue</dc:type><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/bibliography/107406"></dcterms:isPartOf><dcterms:issued>1937</dcterms:issued><dcterms:spatial xml:lang="en">Greenland</dcterms:spatial><dcterms:spatial xml:lang="en">Melville Bugt</dcterms:spatial><edm:europeanaProxy>false</edm:europeanaProxy><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_189254"/><edm:type>TEXT</edm:type></ore:Proxy><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/europeana/08711/item_189254"><dc:date rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/19xx_2_third"></dc:date><dc:subject rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/1676"></dc:subject><dc:subject rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/169"></dc:subject><dcterms:issued rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/1937"></dcterms:issued><dcterms:temporal rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/19xx"></dcterms:temporal><edm:europeanaProxy>true</edm:europeanaProxy><edm:year>1937</edm:year><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/08711/item_189254"/><edm:type>TEXT</edm:type></ore:Proxy><edm:EuropeanaAggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/08711/item_189254"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254"/><edm:datasetName>08711_Ag_EU_BHL_usa</edm:datasetName><edm:country>United States of America</edm:country><edm:preview rdf:resource="https://api.europeana.eu/thumbnail/v2/url.json?uri=http%3A%2F%2Fiiif.archivelab.org%2Fiiif%2FGreenlandExpedi00Schm%241%2Ffull%2Ffull%2F0%2Fdefault.jpg&amp;type=TEXT"/><edm:landingPage rdf:resource="https://www.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254"/><edm:language>en</edm:language><edm:completeness>0</edm:completeness><dcterms:created>2017-08-02T22:15:26.234Z</dcterms:created><dcterms:modified>2017-08-03T00:03:01.384Z</dcterms:modified><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254#contentTier"/><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254#metadataTier"/></edm:EuropeanaAggregation><svcs:Service rdf:about="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/GreenlandExpedi00Schm"><dcterms:conformsTo rdf:resource="http://iiif.io/api/image"></dcterms:conformsTo></svcs:Service><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254#contentTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-16T19:43:44.304Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_189254"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/contentTier4"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_189254#metadataTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-16T19:43:44.304Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_189254"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/metadataTierA"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation></rdf:RDF>