<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:edm="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/" xmlns:owl="http://www.w3.org/2002/07/owl#" xmlns:wgs84_pos="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:rdaGr2="http://rdvocab.info/ElementsGr2/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:ebucore="http://www.ebu.ch/metadata/ontologies/ebucore/ebucore#" xmlns:doap="http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#" xmlns:odrl="http://www.w3.org/ns/odrl/2/" xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" xmlns:ore="http://www.openarchives.org/ore/terms/" xmlns:svcs="http://rdfs.org/sioc/services#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:dqv="http://www.w3.org/ns/dqv#"><edm:ProvidedCHO rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336"/><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/182336"><rdf:type rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/edm/FullTextResource"/><ebucore:hasMimeType>text/html</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">116931</ebucore:fileByteSize></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/pageimage/47399510"/><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/b22651901$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"><ebucore:hasMimeType>image/jpeg</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">1445380</ebucore:fileByteSize><ebucore:width rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">1971</ebucore:width><ebucore:height rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#integer">2996</ebucore:height><edm:hasColorSpace>sRGB</edm:hasColorSpace><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#CD853F</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#A0522D</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#556B2F</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#BDB76B</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#8B4513</edm:componentColor><edm:componentColor rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#hexBinary">#808000</edm:componentColor><ebucore:orientation rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#string">portrait</ebucore:orientation><dcterms:isReferencedBy rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/b22651901/manifest.json"></dcterms:isReferencedBy><svcs:has_service rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/b22651901"/></edm:WebResource><edm:WebResource rdf:about="http://www.archive.org/download/b22651901/b22651901.pdf"><ebucore:hasMimeType>application/pdf</ebucore:hasMimeType><ebucore:fileByteSize rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#long">5429431</ebucore:fileByteSize></edm:WebResource><edm:Agent rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/agent/base/60590"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Мейбридж, Эдвард</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pt">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lv">Edvards Meibridžs</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hr">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bs">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="uk">Едвард Майбрідж</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ka">ედვარდ მეიბრიჯი</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="mk">Едвард Мајбриџ</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sr">Edvard Majbridž</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sv">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ko">에드워드 마이브리지</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gl">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">Ίντγουιρντ Μάιμπριτζ</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="es">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="zh">埃德沃德·迈布里奇</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cs">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="eu">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ar">إدوارد مويبريدج</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ja">エドワード・マイブリッジ</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="az">Edvard Maybric</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pl">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="he">אדוארד מייברידג'</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ro">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="tr">Eadweard Muybridge</skos:prefLabel><skos:altLabel xml:lang="en">Muggeridge, Edward James</skos:altLabel><skos:altLabel xml:lang="en">Muybridge, Eadweard</skos:altLabel><dc:identifier>2538199</dc:identifier><edm:end>1904-05-08</edm:end><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="de">Eadweard Muybridge (* 9. April 1830 in Kingston upon Thames; † 8. Mai 1904 ebenda; eigentlich Edward James Muggeridge) war ein britischer Fotograf und Pionier der Fototechnik.Er gilt – neben Étienne-Jules Marey und Ottomar Anschütz – aufgrund seiner Reihenfotografien und Serienaufnahmen mit Studien des menschlichen und des tierischen Bewegungsablaufs als einer der bedeutendsten frühen Vertreter der Chronofotografie.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="no">Eadweard Muybridge (født 9. april 1830, død 8. mai 1904) var en engelsk-amerikansk fotograf og fotopioner. Han er først og fremst kjent for en mengde fotografiserier som dokumenterer dyr og mennesker i bevegelse. Hans fotoeksperimenter begynte i 1878 da han satte opp en rekke kameraer etter hverandre og lot en hest utløse dem da den løp forbi. Hans øyeblikksbilder beviste blant annet at en hest i galopp har alle fire beina oppe fra bakken samtidig. Han vant dermed et veddemål om en premie på 25 000 dollar for forretningsmannen Leland Stanford. Muybridge oppfant også zoopraxiscope (zoetrope), en innretning for å vise bevegelige bilder. Denne ble forløperen for film av celluloid, en teknikk som fortsatt brukes i de fleste kinoer.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ru">Эдвард Мейбридж, или Майбридж (англ. Eadweard Muybridge; 9 апреля 1830(18300409), Кингстон-на-Темзе — 8 мая 1904, Кингстон-на-Темзе) — английский и американский фотограф. Впервые в истории фотографии начал применять несколько фотокамер одновременно. Изобретатель зоопраксископа — устройства для проецирования фильмов, которое существовало до появления целлулоидной плёнки.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="fi">Eadweard Muybridge (9. huhtikuuta 1830 – 8. toukokuuta 1904 Lontoo) oli englantilaissyntyinen valokuvaaja. Hänet tunnetaan 1800-luvun Amerikan elämää tallentaneista kuvista ja liikettä kuvaavista kuvasarjoista.Muybridge tuli tunnetuksi Yosemiten kansallispuistossa ja San Franciscossa kuvaamistaan kuvasarjoista. Aiheet kuvasivat Yhdysvaltojen levittäytymistä länteen. 1872 hän ratkaisi aikalaisia vaivanneen kysymyksen, irtoavatko kaikki hevosen neljä jalkaa maasta laukan aikana. Kalifornian kuvernööri Leland Stanford oli jalkojen irtoamisen kannalla ja palkkasi Muybridgen todistamaan väitteensä. Muybridge käytti sähköistä laukaisinta ja 24:ää kameraa ja sai aikaan kuvasarjan, joka todisti väitteen oikeaksi.Vuonna 1874 Muybridge joutui hankaluuksiin yksityiselämässään, kun paljastui, että hänen vaimollaan oli rakastaja. Muybridge ampui miehen, jota epäili myös lapsensa isäksi. Oikeudenkäynnissä hänet todettiin syyntakeettomaksi, koska hän väitti saaneensa aivovaurioon johtaneen täräyksen päähänsä. Oikeudenkäynnin jälkeen hän lähti Keski-Amerikkaan ja palasi vasta 1877. Koska hän epäili, että hänen poikansa ei ollut hänen lapsensa (huolimatta heidän yhdennäköisyydestään), hän pisti tämän orpokotiin.Myöhemmin Muybridge kehitti zoetrooppeja ja piti Chicagossa luentoja. Lisäksi hän jatkoi tutkimuksiaan ihmisen liikkeistä. Muybridge palasi 1894 Englantiin, jossa hän kuoli 8. toukokuuta 1904.Juho Gartz on tehnyt Muybridgestä dokumentin Eadweard Muybridge (2007).</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="pt">Eadweard J. Muybridge ( /ˌɛdwərd ˈmaɪbrɪdʒ/; 9 de abril de 1830 – 8 de maio de 1904) foi um fotógrafo inglês conhecido por seus experimentos com o uso de múltiplas câmeras para captar o movimento, além de inventor do zoopraxiscópio, um dispositivo para projetar os retratos de movimento que seria o precursor da película de celulóide, usada ainda hoje.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="lv">Edvards Maibridžs (angļu: Eadweard Muybridge; dzimis 1830. gada 9. aprīlī, miris 1904. gada 8. maijā) bija angļu fotogrāfs, kas lielāko profesionālo dzīvi pavadījis ASV. Pirmais fotogrāfijas vēsturē izmantoja vienlaicīgi vairākus fotoaparātus. Izgudrojis Zoopraxiscope — iekārta filmu projicēšanai, kas pastāvēja līdz pat celuloīda filmu lentes izgudrošanai.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="hr">Eadweard Muybridge (9. travnja 1830. - 8. svibnja 1904.) bio je fotograf porijeklom iz Britanije, poznat prvenstveno po ranom korištenju višestrukih fotoaparata da uhvati kretanje, te po zoopraksiskopu, uređaju za projiciranje pokretnih slika koji se koristio prije današnje celuloidne filmske trake.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="fr">Eadweard Muybridge, né Edward James Muybridge le 9 avril 1830 à Kingston-upon-Thames dans la banlieue de Londres et mort dans cette même agglomération principale au sud-ouest de Londres le 8 mai 1904 à l'âge de 74 ans, est un photographe britannique renommé pour ses décompositions photographiques du mouvement.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="hu">Eadweard J. Muybridge (Kingston upon Thames, Anglia, 1830. április 9. – Kingston upon Thames, 1904. május 8.) holland származású angol fényképész, a mozgófilm fejlesztésének úttörője, aki többnyire az Egyesült Államokban élt és dolgozott. Több kamerából álló rendszerrel készített felvételeket különböző mozgásokról.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="bs">Eadweard Muybridge (9. april 1830. - 8. maj 1904.) bio je fotograf porijeklom iz Britanije, poznat prvenstveno po ranom korištenju višestrukih fotoaparata da uhvati kretanje, te po zoopraksiskopu, uređaju za projeciranje pokretnih slika koji se koristio prije današnje celuloidne filmske trake.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="uk">Е́двард Мáйбрідж (англ. Eadweard Muybridge; * 9 квітня 1830, Кінгстон-на-Темзі, Англія — † 8 травня 1904, там же) — англійський та американський фотограф і дослідник, відомий вивченням процесу руху та його фіксації, один з винахідників-предтеч кіно.Едвард Майбрідж послідовно займався вивченням руху, зокрема, руху тварин та його фіксації і відображення. У цих своїх дослідженнях він вдався до експериментів з пофазовим фотографуванням коней та їх бігу, які проводились у 1872—78 роках.Дослідник відомий як перший фотограф, який використав відразу декілька фотокамер одночасно; він провів із ними цілу низку експериментів. Підсумком стало винайдення Едвардом Майбріджем так званого зоопраксископа (zoopraxiscope) — приладу, що служив для проектування картинок (фільму).У 1887 році вийшло 11 томів праці Едварда Майбріджа «Рух тварин: електрофотографічні дослідження послідовних фаз руху тварин», опублікованих під егідою Пенсильванського університету, що містили всі фотографічні експерименти Майбріджа, здійснені в період від 1872 до 1885 року (понад 100 тисяч світлин).У 1901 році Майбрідж випустив також книгу «Фігура людини в русі», що містила зафіксовані фото руху чоловіків та жінок.Діяльність Едварда Майбріджа — його масові фотографування та технічні винаходи — стали великим внеском у справу винайдення кінематографа.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ka">ედვარდ მეიბრიჯი (ინგლ. Eadweard Muybridge; დ. 9 აპრილი 1830 — გ. 8 მაისი 1904) — ინგლისელ-ამერიკელი ფოტოგრაფი. მან პირველად ფოტოგრაფიის ისტორიაში დაიწყო რამდენიმე კამერის ერთდროულად გამოყენება. მან გამოიგონა „Zoopraxiscope“. ედვარდ მეიბრიჯი იკვლევდა არსებათა მოძრაობებს (მათ შორის ადამიანისას), განსაკუთრებით კი ცხოველთა მოძრაობებს. დაიბადა 1830 წლის 9 აპრილს და გარდაიცვალა 1904 წლის 8 მაისს. მან დიდი წვლილი შეიტანა კინემატოგრაფიაში.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="mk">Едвард Џ. Мајбриџ (англиски: Eadweard J. Muybridge; /ˌɛdwərd ˈmaɪbrɪdʒ/) (9 април, 1830 – 8 мај, 1904) бил англиски фотограф кој поминал голем дел од својот живот во САД. Познат е по неговата пионерска работа на животински движења, за што користел неколку фотоапарати и неговиот зоопраксископ, направа за проектирање движечки слики, што е претходник на филмската лента.Во младоста во Сан Франциско, Мајбриџ станал познат поради неговите пејсажи. Во 1874 тој го застрелал и убил Хери Леркинс, љубовник на неговата жена.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ca">Eadweard Muybridge (pseudònim d'Edward James Muggeridge) va ser un fotògraf i investigador nascut a Kingston upon Thames (Anglaterra) el 9 d'abril de 1830.Va canviar el seu nom quan va emigrar als Estats Units l'any 1851. Fou un dels pioners de la Cronofotografia.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="sr">Edvard Majbridž (engl. Eadweard Muybridge, 9. april 1830 — 8. maj 1904), fotograf poreklom iz Britanije, poznat je prvenstveno po ranom korišćenju višestrukih foto-aparata da uhvati kretanje, te po zoopraksiskopu, uređaju za projektovanje pokretnih slika koji se koristio pre današnje celuloidne filmske trake.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="sv">Eadweard Muybridge (född 9 april 1830, död 8 maj 1904) var en engelsk fotograf som är mest känd för sina insatser inom fotografin och för att han hjälpte Leland Stanford i ett vad. Vadet gällde huruvida om en häst vid något tillfälle släpper alla hovarna från marken eller ej när den galopperar. Eadweard Muybridge satte upp ett antal kameror i en rad längsmed en bana, från varje kamera lät han sedan spänna ett snöre tvärs över banan, när sedan en häst passerade och därmed drog i snöret utlöstes respektive kamera som på så sätt registrerade en ögonblicksbild. Eadweard Muybridge bevisade med hjälp av egenhändigt utvecklad kamerateknik att en häst kan släppa alla hovarna från marken och fick därmed priset på 25 000 dollar, en avsevärt stor summa pengar på den tiden. Dock lär Eadweard Muybridge ha spenderat ca 50 000 dollar på genomförandet av experimentet. På den plats där experimentet utfördes ligger idag Stanford University.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ko">에드워드 제임스 마이브리지(Eadweard James Muybridge, IPA: [ˌɛdwərd ˈmaɪbrɪdʒ], 1830년 4월 9일 ~ 1904년 5월 8일)는 영국의 사진가이다. 동물의 움직임에 대한 획기적인 연구와, 영화를 만들 때 사용하는 필름을 앞서는 기계 (Zoopraxiscope)를 개발한 것으로 유명하다.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="gl">Eadweard James Muybridge, nado en Kingston upon Thames o 9 de abril de 1830 e finado na mesma vila o 8 de maio de 1904, foi un fotógrafo e investigador inglés, coñecido principalmente polos seus experimentos como a xeración do movemento.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="el">Ο Ίντγουιρντ Μάιμπριτζ (αγγλικά: Eadweard J. Muybridge), ( Κίνγκστον απόν Τέιμς 9 Απριλίου 1830 - Κίνγκστον απόν Τέιμς 8 Μαΐου 1904) ήταν Βρετανός φωτογράφος με ολλανδική καταγωγή, που έζησε μεγάλο μέρος της ζωής του στις ΗΠΑ. Είναι γνωστός για την πρωτοποριακή εργασία του και ανακάλυψη σχετικά με τον τρόπο ανάλυσης και σύνθεσης της κίνησης δια μέσου της κάμερας. Ανακάλυψε το zoopraxiscope , μια συσκευή για την προβολή φωτογραφιών που θεωρείται ο πρόδρομος των κινηματογραφικών ταινιών .</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="en">Eadweard James Muybridge (/ˌɛdwərd ˈmaɪbrɪdʒ/; 9 April 1830 – 8 May 1904, birth name Edward James Muggeridge) was an English photographer important for his pioneering work in photographic studies of motion, and early work in motion-picture projection. He adopted the name Eadweard Muybridge, believing it to be the original Anglo-Saxon form of his name.He emigrated to the United States as a young man and became a bookseller. He returned to England in 1861 and took up professional photography, learning the wet-plate collodion process, and secured at least two British patents for his inventions. He went back to San Francisco in 1867, and in 1868 his large photographs of Yosemite Valley made him world famous. Today, Muybridge is known for his pioneering work on animal locomotion in 1877 and 1878, which used multiple cameras to capture motion in stop-motion photographs, and his zoopraxiscope, a device for projecting motion pictures that pre-dated the flexible perforated film strip used in cinematography.In 1874 he shot and killed Major Harry Larkyns, his wife's lover, but was acquitted in a jury trial on the grounds of justifiable homicide. He travelled for more than a year in Central America on a photographic expedition in 1875.In the 1880s, Muybridge entered a very productive period at the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia, producing over 100,000 images of animals and humans in motion, capturing what the human eye could not distinguish as separate movements. He spent much of his later years giving public lectures and demonstrations of his photography and early motion picture sequences, traveling back to England and Europe to publicise his work. He also edited and published compilations of his work, which greatly influenced visual artists and the developing fields of scientific and industrial photography. He returned to his native England permanently in 1894, and in 1904, the Kingston Museum, containing a collection of his equipment, was opened in his hometown.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="it">Eadweard Muybridge (Kingston upon Thames, 9 aprile 1830 – Kingston upon Thames, 8 maggio 1904) è stato un fotografo inglese.Fu un pioniere della fotografia del movimento.Battezzato Edward James Muggeridge, cambiò il cognome prima in Muygridge, infine in Muybridge.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="es">Eadweard Muybridge (seudónimo de Edward James Muggeridge) fue un fotógrafo e investigador nacido en Kingston upon Thames (Gran Bretaña) el 9 de abril de 1830. Cambió su nombre cuando emigró a los Estados Unidos en 1851. Murió el 8 de mayo de 1904. Sus experimentos sobre la cronofotografía sirvieron de base para el posterior invento del cinematógrafo.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="zh">埃德沃德·迈布里奇（Eadweard J. Muybridge，1830年4月9日－1904年5月8日），英国摄影师，他因使用多个相机拍摄运动的物体而著名，他发明的“动物实验镜”（Zoopraxiscope）是一种可以播放运动图像的投影机，将连续图像绘制在一块玻璃圆盘的边缘，随着玻璃的旋转，将影像投射出去，这样就使这些影象显得像在运动。他在美国开创其事业之前学习了摄影，他因拍摄大量运动中的动物和人物的照片而著名，他同时也是一个成功的风景和勘察摄影师，纪录片艺术家，战地记者和发明家。迈布里奇革命性的技术创造了永恒的形象，进而深深影响了几代摄影师，电影制作者和艺术家，其中包括Francis Bacon, Marcel Duchamp, Jasper Johns, Cy Twombly, 和 Douglas Gordon。</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="et">Eadweard J. Muybridge (9. aprill 1830 – 8. mai 1904) oli inglise fotograaf ja filmipioneer. Ta püüdis esimesena kujutada kulgemist liikuvate piltidena.Muybridge'i fotodest tehtud animatsioon.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="cs">Eadweard Muybridge (* 9. dubna 1830, Londýn Anglie – 8. května, 1904) byl anglický fotograf a vynálezce. Zabýval se fotografií krajiny, ale proslavil se svými studiemi pohybu, používáním několika fotoaparátů zároveň a také vynálezem zoopraxiskopu a kinematoskopu, což byla zařízení na promítání pohyblivých obrázků, o mnoho let dříve, než přišel na trh celuloidový kinofilm. Považuje se za zakladatele chronofotografie.Roku 1874 zastřelil milence své ženy, v soudním procesu byl však zproštěn viny s tím, že šlo o důvodné zabití.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="eu">Eadweard Muybridge (jaiotze izena Edward James Muggeridge) 1830eko apirilaren 9an Erresuma Batuko Kingston-on-Thames udalerrian jaiotako argazkilari eta ikertzaile ingelesa izan zen. 1904ko maiatzaren 8an udalerri berdinean zendu zen. Kronoargazkilaritzari buruzko bere ikerketek ondorengo zinematografo izeneko gailuaren aurkikuntzarako oinarri izan ziren.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ar">ادوارد مويبرديدج (بالإنجليزية:Eadweard Muybridge))، عالم بريطاني من أصل هولندي، من مواليد 9 أبريل 1830م وتوفي بتاريخ 8 مايو 1904م، كان رائدا لأولى التجارب لتحريك الصور، وعاش فترة حياته في مدينة سان فرانسيسكو.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ja">エドワード・J・マイブリッジ（Eadweard J. Muybridge 、1830年4月9日 - 1904年5月8日）は、イギリス出身の写真家。本名はエドワード・ジェームズ・マガーリッジ（Edward James Muggeridge ）。イングランドのキングストン・アポン・テムズで生まれた。1855年にアメリカに移住し、サンフランシスコで出版業界に身を置くようになった。</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="az">Edvard Maybric (ing. Eadweard Muybridge) - rəsmləri birləşdirmək yolu ilə hərəkəti yaradan ilk şəxs.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="pl">Eadweard Muybridge (ur. 9 kwietnia 1830 w Kingston upon Thames na przedmieściach Londynu, zm. 8 maja 1904) – brytyjski fotograf, działający w USA. Znany przede wszystkim jako autor zdjęć, wykonywanych zespołem sprzężonych aparatów fotograficznych, przedstawiających kolejne fazy ruchu np. galopującego konia, idącego człowieka itp. Jako wynalazca zoopraksiskopu – urządzenia pozwalającego na animowanie tych zdjęć – był jednym z pionierów kinematografii.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="he">אדוארד מייברידג' (באנגלית: Eadweard Muybridge‏; 9 באפריל 1830 - 8 במאי 1904) היה צלם אמריקני יליד בריטניה וממבשרי אמנות הקולנוע; הראשון שהצליח לצלם תנועה מהירה והראשון שעשה שימוש במספר רב של מצלמות סטילס במטרה ליצור אשליה של תנועה המבוססת על עקרון רציפות הראייה. מייברידג' המציא במסגרת ניסוייו מתקן הקרנה של תמונות נעות (בשם זואופרקסיסקופ), שהקדים בכמה שנים את מקרן סרטי הקולנוע הנמצא בשימוש עד היום.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="da">Eadweard James Muybridge (9. april 1830 – 8. maj 1904) var en britisk-amerikansk fotograf og fotopioner. Han er først og fremmest kendt for en mængde fotografiserier som dokumenterer dyr og mennesker i bevægelse. Hans fotoeksperimenter begyndte i 1878 da han opsatte en række kameraer efter hinanden og lod en hest udløse dem da den løb forbi. Hans øjebliksbilleder beviste blandt andet at en hest i galop har alle fire ben oppe fra jorden samtidig. Han vandt dermed et væddemål om en præmie på 25.000 dollar for forretningsmanden Leland Stanford. Muybridge opfandt også zoopraxiskop (zoetrop), en indretning for at vise levende billeder. Denne blev forløberen for film af celluloid, en teknik som fortsat bruges i de fleste biografer.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="ro">Eadweard J. Muybridge (n. 9 aprilie 1830 – d. 8 mai 1904) a fost un fotograf englez - american, cunoscut mai ales pentru dezvoltarea tehnicii fotografierii cu aparate de fotografiat multiple, menite a capta mișcarea și apoi a o prezenta sub formă animată, cu un aparat inventat de el însuși, zoopraxiscopul, înaintea inventării aparatelor de filmat cu bandă de celuloid.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="nl">Eadweard Muybridge (Kingston upon Thames, 9 april 1830 – aldaar, 8 mei 1904) was een naar de VS uitgeweken Brits fotograaf.Muybridge kreeg van Leland Stanford, oud-gouverneur van Californië, de opdracht om via fotografie te achterhalen of een paard in galop helemaal loskomt van de grond. Via een ingewikkelde proefopstelling met twaalf snelle fototoestellen en een paard genaamd Sallie Gardner vond hij het antwoord: ja! Het was alleen anders dan men tot dan toe een paard had afgebeeld. Met een eigen uitvinding, de zoopraxiscoop probeerde Muybridge nu de nageschilderde foto's te projecteren. Ook werkte hij aan een project getiteld 'Animal Locomotion' waarin hij de bewegingen van een hele reeks dieren via foto's kon analyseren. In 'The Human Figure in Motion' legde hij bewegingen van mensen door middel van reeksen kleine foto's vast in allerlei posities. Muybridge was de eerste die foto's maakte waarbij de belichtingstijd maar een fractie van een seconde duurde. Tot dan toe was de belichtingstijd niet korter dan een paar seconden. Zo kon hij dus onbewogen foto's maken van het paard. Hij was ook de eerste die een mechanische snelwerkende sluiter gebruikt.Tijdens zijn onderzoek voor de gouverneur van Californië vermoordde Muybridge de minnaar van zijn vrouw. Dankzij de juiste relaties verbleef hij slechts kort in de gevangenis en kon hij zijn onderzoekswerk snel hervatten.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:biographicalInformation xml:lang="tr">Eadweard Muybridge (9 Nisan 1830; Londra, İngiltere - 8 Mayıs 1904; Londra), birden fazla kamera kullanarak yaptığı hareket incelemeleriyle bilinen İngiliz asıllı fotoğrafçıdır.Sinemanın ilkel halini ilk bulan kişidir. Asıl adı Edward James Muggeridge olan İngiliz fotoğrafçı, fotoğraf tarihinin önemli isimlerinden birisidir. Muybridge önceleri devlet için çalışmış, daha sonra ise endüstriyel ve manzara fotoğrafçılığı konularında uzmanlaşmıştır.Muybridge, o dönemde çok merak edilen ve üzerine bahisler oynan Bir at dört nala koşerken dört ayağı birden aynı anda yerden kesilir mi? sorusunu ispatlatmak isteyen dönemin Kaliforniya valisi ve yarış atları sahibi Lelan Stanford tarafından görevlendirilir. Bunun üzerine atın hareket halindeki görüntüsünü yakalamaya çalışan Muybridge, fotoğraf makinelerinden oluşan bir düzenek kurarak, 1/1000 enstantane hızıyla bu görüntüyü elde eder. 1878 yılında gerçekleştirdiği bu deneyde, yaş kolodyum tekniğiyle dört nala giden bir atın bütün hareketlerini kayıt altına almayı başarmıştır.</rdaGr2:biographicalInformation><rdaGr2:dateOfBirth>1830-04-09</rdaGr2:dateOfBirth><rdaGr2:dateOfDeath>1904-05-08</rdaGr2:dateOfDeath><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://zh.dbpedia.org/resource/埃德沃德·迈布里奇"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://hu.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://rdf.freebase.com/ns/m.0gc57"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sw.cyc.com/concept/Mx4rhIEg6RUiRryYNDxrWn408A"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://it.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://eu.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sr.dbpedia.org/resource/Edvard_Majbridž"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://az.dbpedia.org/resource/Edvard_Maybric"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://fi.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://bs.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://da.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://br.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://pl.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://nl.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://de.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://yago-knowledge.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q190568"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ru.dbpedia.org/resource/Мейбридж,_Эдвард"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://mk.dbpedia.org/resource/Едвард_Мајбриџ"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://gl.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://nds.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sh.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://fr.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://uk.dbpedia.org/resource/Едвард_Майбрідж"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://hr.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://lb.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://sv.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ka.dbpedia.org/resource/ედვარდ_მეიბრიჯი"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://lv.dbpedia.org/resource/Edvards_Meibridžs"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://fa.dbpedia.org/resource/ادوارد_مایبریج"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://el.dbpedia.org/resource/Ίντγουιρντ_Μάιμπριτζ"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://es.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://eo.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://et.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ko.dbpedia.org/resource/에드워드_마이브리지"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ca.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://no.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ro.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://tr.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://wikidata.dbpedia.org/resource/Q190568"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ja.dbpedia.org/resource/エドワード・マイブリッジ"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://he.dbpedia.org/resource/אדוארד_מייברידג'"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://cs.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://pt.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://id.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://ar.dbpedia.org/resource/إدوارد_مويبريدج"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://simple.dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/><owl:sameAs rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Eadweard_Muybridge"/></edm:Agent><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/18xx"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">19й век</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel>19..</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel>19??</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel>19e</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">19-th</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">19th</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">19th century</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">19e siècle</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">19de eeuw</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/AD2xxx"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:begin>Thu Jan 01 01:00:00 CET 1801</edm:begin><edm:end>Mon Dec 31 00:19:32 CET 1900</edm:end></edm:TimeSpan><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/18xx_4_quarter"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">4-я четверть 19-го века</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">4 quarter of the 19th century</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">4e quart 19e siècle</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/18xx_2_half"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:begin>Sat Jan 01 01:00:00 CET 1876</edm:begin><edm:end>Mon Dec 31 00:19:32 CET 1900</edm:end></edm:TimeSpan><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/18xx_2_half"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Вторая половина 19-го века</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Second half of the 19th century</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">19e (fin)</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/timespan/19"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:begin>Wed Jan 01 01:00:00 CET 1851</edm:begin><edm:end>Tue Dec 31 00:19:32 CET 1901</edm:end></edm:TimeSpan><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/1893"><skos:prefLabel>1893</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/18xx_4_quarter"></dcterms:isPartOf><edm:begin>Sun Jan 01 01:00:00 CET 1893</edm:begin><edm:end>Sun Dec 31 01:00:00 CET 1893</edm:end></edm:TimeSpan><edm:TimeSpan rdf:about="http://semium.org/time/AD2xxx"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Second millenium AD</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Second millenium AD, years 1001-2000</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">2e millénaire après J.-C.</skos:prefLabel><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/ChronologicalPeriod"></dcterms:isPartOf></edm:TimeSpan><skos:Concept rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/6"><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="no">Bok</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hi">पुस्तक</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="de">Buch</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fi">Kirja</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="be">Кніга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ru">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pt">Livro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bg">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lt">Knyga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hr">Knjiga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="lv">Grāmata</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">Livre (document)</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hu">Könyv</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="bs">Knjiga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="hy">Գիրք</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ka">წიგნი</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="uk">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sk">Kniha</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sl">Knjiga</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ga">Leabhar</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gd">Leabhar</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ca">Llibre</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="mk">Книга</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sq">Libri</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sr">Књига</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="sv">Bok</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ko">책</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="gl">Libro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="el">Βιβλίο</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">Book</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="is">Bók</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="it">Libro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="zh">图书</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="es">Libro</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="et">Raamat</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="eu">Liburu</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cs">Kniha</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ar">كتاب</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="cy">Llyfr</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ja">本</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="az">Kitab</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="pl">Książka</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="ro">Carte</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="da">Bog</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="he">ספר</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="tr">Kitap</skos:prefLabel><skos:prefLabel xml:lang="nl">Boek (document)</skos:prefLabel><skos:note xml:lang="no">Bok (av norrønt bók) er en sammenbinding av flere blad av papir, pergament eller annet egnet materiale. Materialet er sammenføyd langs en side, ryggen, og som regel innbundet i et mer robust materiale. I overført betydning kan bok også betegne et litterært verk.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hi">पुस्तक या किताब लिखित या मुद्रित पेजों के संग्रह को कहते हैं। डिजिटल पुस्तकों को ई-पुस्तक (ई-बुक) कहते हैं।पुस्तकों की लिस्ट के लिए श्रेणी:पुस्तक देखें</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="de">Ein Buch ist eine mit einer Bindung und meistens auch mit Bucheinband (Umschlag) versehene Sammlung von bedruckten, beschriebenen, bemalten oder auch leeren Blättern aus Papier oder anderen geeigneten Materialien. Laut Unesco-Definition sind (für Statistiken) Bücher nichtperiodische Publikationen mit einem Umfang von 49 Seiten oder mehr. Die UNESCO legte 1995 den 23. April als Welttag des Buches fest.Zudem werden einzelne Werke oder große Textabschnitte, die in sich abgeschlossen sind, als Buch bezeichnet, insbesondere wenn sie Teil eines Bandes sind. Das ist vor allem bei antiken Werken, die aus zusammengehörigen Büchersammlungen bestehen, der Fall – Beispiele hierfür sind die Bibel und andere normative religiöse Heilige Schriften, die Aeneis sowie diverse antike und mittelalterliche Geschichtswerke.Elektronisch gespeicherte Buchtexte nennt man digitale Bücher (englisch e-book). Eine andere moderne Variante des Buches ist das Hörbuch.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fi">Kirja on nidos paperiarkkeja, joissa on painettua tekstiä tai kuvia, tai sen muotoisena ilmestynyt kirjallinen tuote. Kirjoja voidaan julkaista myös sähköisessä muodossa ja äänikirjoina.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="be">Кніга — друкаванае (даўней таксама рукапіснае) выданне ў выглядзе пераплеценых разам лістоў паперы з якім-небудзь тэкстам.У філасофскім значэнні кніга — форма замацавання і ўзнаўлення семантычнай інфармацыі (тэксту), найважнейшы сродак масавай інфармацыі, адукацыі і фактар культуры. Кніга з'яўляецца прадуктам кніжнай справы, якая ўключае стварэнне і размнажэнне кніг, распаўсюджванне (рэклама, кнігагандаль), захаванне і выкарыстанне. Сучасная кніга — звычайна неперыядычнае выданне ў выглядзе збрашураваных аркушаў аб'ёмам больш за 48 старонак. Складаецца з шэрагу элементаў матэрыяльнай канструкцыі і паліграфічнага афармлення.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ru">Кни́га — один из видов печатной продукции: непериодическое издание, состоящее из сброшюрованных бумажных листов (страниц) или тетрадей, на которых нанесена типографским или рукописным способом текстовая и графическая (иллюстрации) информация, имеющая объём более сорока восьми страниц и, как правило, твёрдый переплёт.Также книгой может называться литературное или научное произведение, предназначенное для печати в виде отдельного сброшюрованного издания.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pt">Livro é um volume transportável, composto por páginas encadernadas, contendo texto manuscrito ou impresso e/ou imagens e que forma uma publicação unitária (ou foi concebido como tal) ou a parte principal de um trabalho literário, científico ou outro.Em ciência da informação o livro é chamado monografia, para distingui-lo de outros tipos de publicação como revistas, periódicos, teses, tesauros, etc.O livro é um produto intelectual e, como tal, encerra conhecimento e expressões individuais ou colectivas. Mas também é nos dias de hoje um produto de consumo, um bem e sendo assim a parte final de sua produção é realizada por meios industriais (impressão e distribuição). A tarefa de criar um conteúdo passível de ser transformado em livro é tarefa do autor. Já a produção dos livros, no que concerne a transformar os originais em um produto comercializável, é tarefa do editor, em geral contratado por uma editora. Outra função associada ao livro é a coleta e organização e indexação de coleções de livros, típica do bibliotecário. Finalmente, destaca-se também o livreiro cuja função principal é de disponibilizar os livros editados ao público em geral, vendendo-os nas livrarias generalistas ou de especialidade. Compete também ao livreiro todo o trabalho de pesquisa que vá ao encontro da vontade dos leitores.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bg">Книгата е печатно произведение с научно или литературно съдържание, което е с броширани или подвързани листове. Книгата може да е с меки или твърди корици. Книгите се създават в печатници, а дистрибуцията им се нарича книгоразпространение. Но преди да отидат в печатниците биват измислени и написани от писател.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lt">Knyga – susiūti tušti popieriaus ar pergamento lapai arba lapai su spausdintu tekstu. Taip pat knyga – veikalas ar stambaus veikalo dalis. Elektroninė knyga – kūrinys, saugomas elektroniniame formate.Knygų mylėtojas paprastai vadinamas bibliofilu, knygų kolekcija – biblioteka.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hr">Knjiga je ukoričena tiskana omeđena publikacija od najmanje 49 stranica (UNESCO-va definicija), odnosno, knjiga je tiskana kolekcija papira. Ukoričena tiskana publikacija koja sadrži manje od 49 stranica naziva se brošura. U engleskom jeziku riječ "book" dolazi od staroengleske riječi "bōc", koja dolazi od njemačke riječi s sadržajem "*bōk-".</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="lv">Grāmata ir neperiodisks iespieddarbs kodeksa formā ar muguriņā sastiprinātām lapām. Lapu daudzums ir ne mazāks par 3 iespiedloksnēm, tas ir 48 lappuses. Mūsdienās grāmatu lapas izgatavo no papīra. Parasti grāmata ir pabeigts teksts, kas izteikts ar rakstu zīmēm vai attēliem.Mūsdienās bez grāmatām pastāv arī elektroniski informācijas nesēji — elektroniskās grāmatas.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="fr">Un livre est un document écrit formant une unité et conçu comme tel composé de pages en papier ou en carton reliées les unes aux autres.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hu">A könyv az ókortól a 20. század közepéig a legfontosabb és legelterjedtebb információhordozó médium. Megjelenési formája változatos, leginkább összefűzött vagy -kötött papírlapokból áll. A papírlapokra felvitt jelek hordozzák az információt. A hagyományosan valamilyen nyelven, írásban, szövegként rögzített információt az olvasás művelete segítségével kapjuk vissza. Képi információt is tartalmazhat.Használatának megkönnyítésére a lapok oldalait számozzák, a tartalom részei közötti eligazodást a tagolás és a tipográfia mellett külön tartalomjegyzék, tárgymutató vagy névmutató is segítheti.A könyv manapság nyomdaipari sokszorosítással előállított tömegtermék.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="yi">א בוך (מערצאל: ביכער) איז א זאמלונג פון בלעטער וואס זענען געשריבן, געדרוקט, אילוסטרירט אדער אפילו ליידיק, געמאכט פון פאפיר, פארמעט, אדער אנדערע מאטריאלן, צוזאמענגעהאפטן פון איין זייט . איין בויגן אין א בוך הייסט א בלאט, און א בלאט האט צוויי זייטן. היינט שאפט מען ביכער אויך אין עלעקטראנישן פארמאט.אלע ביכער און געשריבענער ווערק רופט מען ליטעראטור. איינער וואס פארקויפט ביכער איז א בוכהענדלער. א זאמלונג פון ביכער אין א ביבליאטעקאין 2010, האט גוגל געשאצט אז אין דער וועלט זענען פאראן אומגעפער 130 מיליאן פארשידענע ביכער.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="bs">Knjiga je skup ili kolekcija pisanih, štampanih, ilustrovanih ili praznih listova, načinjenih od papira, pergamenta ili nekog drugog materijala, koje su obično spojene sa jedne strane. Strane listova knjige zovu se stranice. U novije vrijeme postale su poznate i elektronske knjige. Prema UNESCO-voj definiciji knjiga mora imati minimalno 49 stranica. Publikacija sa manje od 49 stranica naziva se brošura.Knjiga se koristi za čitanje očima ili vrhovima prstiju, te u slučaju audioknjiga sluhom. Na taj način se prikupljaju informacije koje su odštampane ili snimljene.Pod nazivom knjiga se također podrazumjevaju literarni radovi koji se sastoje određenog broja tomova, te se time razlikuju od časopisa i magazina, koji izlaze periodično i na neodređeno vrijeme. Ljudi koji vole da sakupljaju ili čitaju knjige zovu se bibliofili, knjigoljupci ili, neformalno, knjiški crvi.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="hy">Գիրք, ձեռագիր, տպագիր կամ այլ կրիչի վրա գրական-գեղարվեստական, հասարակական-քաղաքական, գիտական բովանդակությամբ ստեղծագործություն է։ Ներկայումս առավել տարածվածը թղթի վրա տպագրված գիրքն է։Գիրքը կազմված է բնագրից, տիտղոսաթերթից և կազմից. վերջինս երբեմն ունենում է նաև կազմաշապիկ։ Տիտղոսաթերթի վրա գրվում են հեղինակի անունը և գրքի վերնագիրը, հրատարակության վայրը և տեսակը, հրատարակչությունը, տպագրության տարեթիվը։Գրքի սկզբնավորումը կապված է գրի ստեղծման հետ, որը մի քանի հազար տարվա պատմություն ունի։ Անցյալում բաբելացիները, ասորեստանցիները և այլ հին ժողովուրդներ գրել են հիմնականում կավե սալիկների վրա։ Պահպանվել է մ.թ. ա. III հազարամյակում սալիկների վրա գրված գեղարվեստական հնագույն՝ ասուրա-բաբելական «Գիլգամեշ» դյուցազներգությունը։ Այդ եղանակով կազմված գրքերից են ստեղծվել առաջին գրադարանները։ Չինաստանում գրել են հնդկեղեգից (բամբուկ) պատրաստված շերտիկների վրա և շարել ամուր թելի վրա։ Ավելի ուշ չինացիները գրել են մետաքսի, իսկ մ. թ. II դարից՝ թղթի վրա։ Հին Եգիպտոսում նախ գրել են կավե սալիկների, այնուհետև՝ պապիրուսի վրա, որը եղեգի մամլած շերտիկներն իրար սոսնձած մի քանի տասնյակ մետր երկարությամբ ժապավեն էր և պահվում էր գլանաձև փաթաթված։Մ. թ. ա. II դարում Պերգամոն քաղաքում կենդանիների կաշվից պատրաստվել է նոր գրանյութ և քաղաքի անունով կոչվել պերգամենտ։ Այն մեզ հայտնի մագաղաթն է։ Մագաղաթե ամենահին ձեռագիրը Հոմերոսի «Իլիական» պոեմի՝ III դարում գրված մի հատված է։ Մագաղաթը պապիրուսից ավելի ճկուն ու ամուր էր, հեշտությամբ ծալվում էր, իսկ ծալվածքի մասում թերթերը կարվում ու միացվում էին իրար։ Միջնադարում մագաղաթե թերթերն ամփոփվում էին կաշեպատ կամ լաթապատ փայտե կազմի մեջ։Գրքի զարգացման և ժողովրդականացման խոշոր ազդակ էր 1447 թ-ին Յոհան Գուտենբերգի տպագրության գյուտը, որով դրվեց գրքի տպագրության հիմքը։Հայաստանում թուղթը՝ որպես գրանյութ, օգտագործվել է VIII–IX դարերում։ Տպագրությունը XV դարում զգալիորեն խթանել է գրքի զարգացումն ու տարածումը։Հայերեն առաջին գրքերը՝ ձեռագիր մատյանները, ստեղծվել են V դարում՝ հայոց գրի գյուտից հետո։ Պահպանված հնագույն ձեռագիր մատյանը VII դարում ստեղծված Վեհամոր Ավետարանն է։ Ձեռագիր մատյաններ ստեղծվել են մինչև XVIII դարի վերջը։Թղթի վրա մեզ հասած առաջին ձեռագիր գիրքն ընդօրինակվել է 981 թ-ին։Մինչև 1800 թ. տպագրված գրքերը կոչվում են հնատիպ։ Դրանք բազմաբովանդակ են, բայց գերակշռում են կրոնական բնույթի գրքերը։ Հրատարակվել են փոքր տպաքանակներով, մեծ մասամբ՝ կաշեպատ զարդարուն կազմերով։ Հայերեն հնատիպ գրքերի թիվը անցնում է 1000-ից։ 1801–50 թթ-ին հրատարակվել է մոտ 1700 անուն գիրք։ Ներկայումս Հայաստանում և տարբեր երկրներում ամեն տարի լույս են տեսնում հազարավոր հայերեն գրքեր։</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ka">წიგნი — ინფორმაციის მნიშვნელოვანი საშუალება, ცოდნის გავრცელების, განათლებისა და აღზრდის იარაღი.წიგნის ტექსტების ფიქსირება ხდება ფურცლებზე ნიშნების, ასოების ან სხვა გრაფიკული გამოსახულებების საშუალებით, რომლებიც აღიქმება ვიზუალურად. (გამონაკლისია წიგნები უსინათლოთათვის, რომლებიც ბრაილის შრიფტით არის დაწერილი.)თანამედროვე წიგნი წარმოადგენს ყუაში ჩამაგრებული ტექსტებისა და ილუსტრაციების შემცველი ფურცლების კოდექსბლოკს გარე დამცველი ელემენტებითურთ (ყდა, გარეკანი) და ნაბეჭდი გვერდების განსაზღვრული რაოდენობით - იუნესკოს რეკომენდაციების შესატყვისად - ნაბეჭდ თაბახზე მეტი ე. ი. არანაკლებ 48 გვერდისა.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="uk">Кни́га, книжка — письмовий запис, неперіодичне видання у вигляді зброшурованих аркушів друкованого матеріалу, набір письмових, друкованих, ілюстрованих або порожніх аркушів, виготовлених з паперу, пергаменту або іншого матеріалу, як правило, скріплених з одного боку. Сторони аркуша називаються сторінками.Книга виготовлена в цифровому вигляді називається електронною книгою. Озвучену й записану на матеріальний носій книгу називають аудіокнигою (звуковою книгою, книгою вголос).Книжкова крамниця або книгарня — крамниця, де продаються книги. Також книги можна позичати у бібліотеках на певний час.Любителя книг, як правило, називають книголюбом, бібліофілом, або, неформально, книжковим хробаком (від англ. Bookworm).</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sk">Kniha je nejasne definovaný termín. Bežné definície sú nasledovné:definície s dôrazom na fyzické hľadisko:súhrn (potlačených alebo prázdnych) listov papiera, pergamenu, velínu, látky alebo iného materiálu zopnutý pozdĺž jednej hrany (bez ohľadu na to, či má alebo nemá dosky či puzdro) [táto definícia teda zahŕňa okrem slovesných diel aj rôzne záznamníky, albumy a podobne]slovesné dielo vydané tlačou v samostatnom zväzku opak brožúry, publikácia majúca (alebo len literárny produkt majúci) minimálne 48 strán a viacdielne dosky (namiesto prebalu) tlačený alebo akýkoľvek iným spôsobom rozmnožený grafický dokument, knihársky spracovaný do tvaru zväzku a tvoriaci myšlienkový a výtvarný celok (v tejto norme aj hudobniny, obrazové publikácie, albumy, atlasy, rôzne druhy tabuliek apod. vo forme knihy). definícia s dôrazom na neperiodicitu: knižná publikácia (t.j. neperiodická textová publikácia [iná než špeciálna publikácia ako napr. diplomová práca, konferenčný materiál a pod.]) definícia s dôrazom na neperiodicitu aj fyzické hľadisko: neseriálový tlačený dokument v kódexovej forme tlačená neperiodická publikácia (bez jej dosák), prístupná verejnosti, ktorá má rozsah minimálne 49 strán a je vydaná v (určitej) krajinedefinícia s dôrazom na tvorenie jedného celku: duševné dielo vydané v písanej, tlačenej alebo elektronickej forme, zvyčajne rozdelené na stránky a tvoriace fyzickú jednotku V poslednej definícii, ako vidno, termín kniha zahŕňa aj elektronickú knihu. O (ne)zaradení zvukových kníh (audiokníh) medzi knihy pozri článok zvuková kniha.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sl">Knjiga je zbirka popisanih, porisanih ali potiskanih listov iz papirja, pergamenta ali drugega materiala, na eni strani zvezanih skupaj in ovitih v platnice. Knjiga je lahko tudi oznaka za literarno delo, v zadnjem času pa z izrazom e-knjiga označujemo literarna dela, ki so shranjena (lahko izključno) na elektronskih medijih in dostopna s pomočjo računalnika.Za knjigo bi lahko rekli, da je predmet (lahko jo listamo, prijemamo, trgamo...), naprava (je oštevilčena in nam omogoča lažje iskanje informacij) ali medij (s knjigo lahko prenašamo sporočila, podatke, informacije...)V bibliotekarstvu se knjiga imenuje monografska publikacija, da se razlikuje od revij, časopisov in drugih publikacij. Celoti vseh napisanih del, vključno s knjigami, pravimo literatura. Knjige so eden glavnih načinov razširjanja znanja in idej med ljudmi. Najbolj uveljavljeni načini dostopa do knjig so knjigarne (nakup) in knjižnice (izposoja), posebej stare in dragocene knjige pa hranijo tudi muzeji.Ljubitelja knjig imenujemo bibliofil, človeka, ki veliko bere, pa pogovorno knjižni molj.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ga">Is éard atá i gceist le leabhar ná cnuasach de leathanaigh, ar a bhfuil focail nó íomhánna clóite, déanta de pháipéar nó ábhair eile atá fáiscthe le chéile ar thaobh amháin. Is féidir ríomhleabhair a fháil sa lá atá inniu ann. Ní leabhar clóite atá ann, ach comhad ar ríomhaire ar féidir é a léamh ar nós leabhair.Cuirtear bailiúchán mór leabhar i dtaisce i leabharlann. Leabhragán a ghlaoitear ar an dtroscán ar a gcuirtear leabhair ina seasamh.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="gd">'S e an t'iom-leabhar air a foillseachadh leabhar a th'ann.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ca">Un llibre (del llatí liber) és una obra impresa o manuscrita no periòdica que consta d'una sèrie de fulls de paper (si és pergamí o vitel·la es parla de còdex), cosits o enquadernats de manera que es reuneixen en un volum. Segons la definició de la UNESCO, ha de tenir 49 pàgines o més, sense comptar les cobertes. Un llibre pot tractar sobre qualsevol tema. Un llibre és també cadascuna de les parts de l'obra en els codis i lleis d'una gran extensió. També s'anomena llibre tota obra independent, fent abstracció de la concreció física formal. Un llibre és una col·lecció d'un o més treballs escrits, usualment imprès en paper i cobert amb tapes per a protegir-lo i organitzar el material imprès.Sintèticament, es pot dir que el llibre neix com a imitació del còdex, però en paper en comptes de pergamí. És arran de la impremta que el llibre va anar atenyent la majoria de trets que li són característics i que alhora el distingeixen del còdex.Avui dia, tanmateix, aquesta definició no queda circumscrita al món imprès o dels suports físics, donada l'aparició dels nous formats documentals i especialment del web World Wide Web. El llibre digital, conegut com a e-book en anglès col·loquial, està irrompent cada vegada amb més força en el món del llibre i en la pràctica professional bibliotecària i documental. A més, el llibre també pot trobar-se en format d'àudio, en el qual cas és anomenat audiollibre.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="mk">Книга е збир на пишани, печатени, илустрирани или празни страници, изработени од хартија, пергамент или друг вид на материјал, обично прицврстени заедно од едната страна. Секоја страна на лист од книгата се нарекува страница. Книга направена во електронска форма е позната како електронска книга или скратено е-книга.Книгите исто така се однесуваат и на литературни творби. Во библиотеките постои разлика меѓу периодичните часописи, магазини или весници и книгите. Една книга може да се подели во неколку тома или секции, и тогаш секоја од нив се нарекува исто така книга, но содржи и број, на пример прва книга, втора книга, итн. Вљубеникот во читање книги се нарекува библиофил. Местото каде се купуваат и се продаваат книгите се нарекува книжарница, а местото од каде што се позајмуваат книгите се нарекува библиотека.Во 2010 година Гугл проценил дека постојат околу 130 милиони наслови на книги во светот.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sq">Libri është tërësia unitare, e ilustruar ose jo, e botuar nën një titull në çfarëdo forme, që ka për objekt materializimin e një produkti mendor të një ose më shumë autorëve dhe që botohet një herë ose herë mbas here, në një vëllim ose në shumë vëllime.Zakonisht libri është një vepër shkencore, letrare, mësimore etj. me fletë të shtypura e të lidhura mes dy kapakëve së bashku në një vëllim dhe i cili del në shitje. Sipas definicionit të UNESCO logaritet si libër një botim i shtypur, i cili mund të blehet nga publiku, nuk del në formë periodike dhe ka së paku 49 faqe. Produkte të përafërta me Librin janë botime të shtypura. Në Kosovë këto produkte përfshihen: almanakë, vjetarë, katalogë,albume filatelie, albume për ngjyrosje, albume me figura për fëmijë, repertorë me informacione numerike, repertorë alfabetikë, broshura që shpjegojnë funksionimin e aparateve me të cilat janë të lidhura, partitura të thjeshta që përhapin tekstin dhe muzikën e një kënge, fletore muzike për detyra, si dhe botime të tjera të ngjashme siç janë librat me disqe, shirita magnetikë, kaseta, filma ose diapozitivë, me kushtin e dyfishtë:a) që këto të përbëjnë një tërësi dhe elementet e tyre të mos jenë objekt e një shitjeje të veçantë dheb) që mbështetja dëgjimore-pamore të jetë plotësuese e librit, dhe jo e kundërta, konsiderohen si libra.↑ 1,0 1,1</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sr">Књиге, овакве какве су данас, појавиле су се тек у средњем веку. Најближи њима били су свитуљци папируса. Листови папируса лепљени су један за другим, и тако се добијао дугачак свитуљак.Средином 5. века, пергамент је заменио папирус. Пергамент се прави од овчије или козје коже. Листови од тог материјала, исписани су на једној страни, сечени да буду исте величине, а потом су на једном крају спајани кожним копчама и повезани у књиге.Међутим, књиге налик на данашње први пут су направљене, у средњем веку. Четири комада велина савијена су тако да је сваки творио по два листа. Ти комади су онда стављени један у други, па се добијало 8 спојених листова, који се називају свезак. Они су се затим слали писару који ће исписати текст. Писар је раздвајао листове и писао страницу по страницу. Велин је био дебео, тако да се могло писати са обје стране.Идући корак било је слање исписаних свезака књиговезцу, да од њих направи књигу. Он их је прошивао дебелим концем, потом је правио дрвене корице, па је крајеве конца провлачио кроз рупе избушене на дашчицама, и на тај начин спајао странице на корицама. На крају је лепио велики комад коже на споју исписаних одељака и дрвених корица. Касније је повезивање усавршено. Пронађени су нови начини да се књига украси и боље сачува.Средњовековне књиге су већином биле Библије, проповеди и остали верски списи. Иза тога су се појавиле и књиге с подручја права, медицине, природних наука, а још касније и неколико летописа и романа. Највећи број књига у средњем веку писан је на латинском језику.Књиге су почели штампати у 15. веку а пионир технике штампања је био Јохан Гутенберг.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="sv">För andra betydelser, se Bok (olika betydelser).En bok är ett medium för kommunikation – innehållet kan, men måste inte vara, någon form av litteratur. En bok är en produkt som består av flera sammanhäftade eller ihoplimmade blad (ark), vars innehåll ofta är text och/eller bilder, och som ofta täcks av ett omslag med upplysning om bokens titel och författare. Unesco har definierat en bok som "en icke-periodisk tryckt publikation bestående av minst 49 sidor". Det finns många typer av böcker, från pocketböcker till inbundna böcker i flera varianter, pekböcker samt talböcker.Bok har dock också en mindre specifik betydelse, där det kan syfta på såväl en bokrulle som en e-bok. En bok kan också vara detsamma som ett litterärt verk, som i frasen "Charles Darwins bok Om arternas uppkomst". En bok kan också vara en del i ett längre verk, såsom Första mosebok är den första delen av Gamla testamentet. Liknande produkter är tidningar och tidskrifter.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ko">책(冊)은 일정한 목적으로 쓴 글 및 참고 자료 등을 덧붙여 묶은 것이다. 서사(書史), 서질, 서적(書籍), 서전(書典), 서책(書冊), 책자(冊子), 문적(文籍), 전적(典籍), 편적(篇籍) 혹은 도서(圖書)로도 불린다. 책 도안은 겉표지, 서언 (서문, 추천서문), 머리말, 목차, 책 내용, 색인 (용어 색인) 따위로 구별 할 수 있다.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="gl">Un libro é unha obra manuscrita, impresa ou virtual, que consta dunha serie de follas que conteñen texto ou imaxes composto por, polo menos, 48 páxinas (sen contar as capas - segundo a Unesco). Un libro pode ser, por exemplo, unha novela, un ensaio ou un libro fotográfico.A palabra libro procede do latín liber, que significa cortiza.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="el">Το Βιβλίο είναι υλικός φορέας γραπτού ή και εικαστικού περιεχομένου. Παγκοσμίως εννοείται ως βασική κατηγορία έντυπου λόγου και αποτελείται από αριθμό συνδεδεμένων τεμαχίων χαρτιού και εξώφυλλο. Βιβλίο αποκαλείται επίσης το σύνολο του περιεχομένου του αντικειμένου αυτού ως πνευματικό έργο. Αν και η ύπαρξη του έντυπου λόγου χρονολογείται από την απαρχή της ανθρώπινης ιστορίας, το βιβλίο αποτελεί το κατεξοχήν μέσο διάδοσης της γνώσης από την εφεύρεση της τυπογραφίας από τον Ιωάννη Γουτεμβέργιο έως και σήμερα. Η αξία και το περιεχόμενο του βιβλίου συνδέθηκε περισσότερο με τη λογοτεχνία, την επιστήμη, και τη θρησκεία. Με την ανάπτυξη της τεχνολογίας το βιβλίο εμφανίζεται τις τελευταίες δεκαετίες και σε μη υλικούς φορείς όπως το ηλεκτρονικό βιβλίο (e-book) και το ακουστικό βιβλίο (audio book). Τα βιβλία απαντώνται στην τυπογραφική βιομηχανία, στις εκδοτικές επιχειρήσεις, στα βιβλιοπωλεία, στις βιβλιοθήκες, σε ιδιωτικές συλλογές και αλλού.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="en">A book is a set of written, printed, illustrated, or blank sheets, made of ink, paper, parchment, or other materials, usually fastened together to hinge at one side. A single sheet within a book is called a leaf, and each side of a leaf is called a page. A set of text-filled or illustrated pages produced in electronic format is known as an electronic book, or e-book.Books may also refer to works of literature, or a main division of such a work. In library and information science, a book is called a monograph, to distinguish it from serial periodicals such as magazines, journals or newspapers. The body of all written works including books is literature. In novels and sometimes other types of books (for example, biographies), a book may be divided into several large sections, also called books (Book 1, Book 2, Book 3, and so on). An avid reader of books is a bibliophile or colloquially, bookworm.A shop where books are bought and sold is a bookshop or bookstore. Books can also be borrowed from libraries. Google has estimated that as of 2010, approximately 130,000,000 unique titles had been published.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="is">Bók er safn blaða fest saman í band, oftast í umgjörð sem er sterkari en efnið í blöðunum (og kallast umgjörðin þá kápa). Blöðin geta m.a. verið úr skinni, pappír og pergamenti.Tilgangur bóka er oftast að miðla upplýsingum með texta, táknum og myndum. Bókasöfn eru staðir þar sem margar bækur eru, oft til útláns eða lestrar almenningi.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="it">Un libro è un insieme di fogli stampati oppure manoscritti delle stesse dimensioni rilegati insieme in un certo ordine e racchiusi da una copertina. Il libro, usato per acquisire informazioni o anche per divertimento, è ancora oggi lo "strumento principe del sapere".</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="zh">图书，通常在狭义上的理解是带有文字和图像的纸张的集合。书通常由墨水、纸张、羊皮纸或者其他材料固定在书脊上组成。组成书的一张纸称为一张，一张的一面称为一页。但随着科学技术的发展，狭义图书的概念也在扩展，制作书的材料也在改变，如电子格式的电子书。从广义理解的图书，则是一切传播訊息的媒介。书也指文学作品或者其中的一部分。在图书馆情报学中，书被称为专著，以区别于杂志、学报、报纸等连载期刊。所有的书面作品（包括图书）的主体是文学。在小说和一些类型（如传记）中，书可能还要分成卷。对书特别喜爱的人被称为爱书者或藏书家，更随意的称呼是书虫或者书呆子。买书的地方叫书店，借书可以到图书馆去。2010年，谷歌公司估计，从印刷术发明至今，大概出版了一亿三千万本不同名字的书籍。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="es">Un libro (del latín liber, libri, ‘membrana’ o ‘corteza de árbol’) es una obra impresa, manuscrita o pintada en una serie de hojas de papel, pergamino, vitela u otro material, unidas por un lado (es decir, encuadernadas) y protegidas con tapas, también llamadas cubiertas. Un libro puede tratar sobre cualquier tema.Según la definición de la Unesco, un libro debe poseer 49 o más páginas (25 hojas o más), pues desde 5 hasta 48 páginas sería un folleto (desde tres hasta 24 hojas), y desde una hasta cuatro páginas se consideran hojas sueltas (una o dos hojas).También se llama "libro" a una obra de gran extensión publicada en varias unidades independientes, llamados "tomos" o "volúmenes". Otras veces se llama también "libro" a cada una de las partes de una obra, aunque físicamente se publiquen todas en un mismo volumen (ejemplo: Libros de la Biblia).Hoy día, no obstante, esta definición no queda circunscrita al mundo impreso o de los soportes físicos, dada la aparición y auge de los nuevos formatos documentales y especialmente de la World Wide Web. El libro digital o libro electrónico, conocido como e-book, está viendo incrementado su uso en el mundo del libro y en la práctica profesional bibliotecaria y documental. Además, el libro también puede encontrarse en formato audio, en cuyo caso se denomina audiolibro.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="et">Raamat on köidetud kogu teksti või piltidega lehti; ehk ka kogum ühest servast kokku liidetud, tavaliselt ühesuurusi ja ristkülikukujulisi paberilehti, millel asub nähtaval või kombataval kujul märkidest koosnev tekst. Raamat üldisemas tähenduses on graafiline andmekandja.Kirjastustegevuses, raamatukaubanduses, raamatukogunduses jm nimetatakse raamatuks ühekordselt tiražeeritud tekstikogumikku, millel on reeglina rahvusvaheline 10-kohaline identifitseerimiskood (ISBN). Raamatul on lehekülgi vähemalt 49 (brošüüril 5 kuni 48). Käsikirjad, perioodilised ja seeriaväljaanded, samuti koomiksid, noodiraamatud, mitmesugused kataloogid, kasutusjuhendid jm raamatukujulised esemed selles mõttes raamatute hulka ei kuulu. E-raamat on elektrooniliselt salvestatud suurem tekstikogumik.Audioraamat on helikandjale salvestatud kuulatav tekstikogumik.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="eu">Liburua edo Idaztia idatzitako, zuriz inprimatutako edota irudiz hornitutako orrialdeen sorta da, paperez, pergaminoz edo beste material batzuez egindakoa. Normalean azal pare batek babesten du. 1501 baino lehen egindakoak "inkunable" edo jatorri zehaztezindun izena hartzen dute. Gaur egun, formato elektronikoa baldin badauka "e-book" izena hartzen du ingelesez.Liburutegiak dira objektu hauek irakurgai ditugun tokiak eta liburudendak salgai daudenak.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cs">Kniha je sešitý nebo slepený svazek listů nebo skládaný arch papíru, kartonu, pergamenu nebo jiného materiálu, popsaný, potištěný nebo prázdný s vazbou a opatřený přebalem.Kniha je též literární práce nebo hlavní oddíl této práce. Kniha publikovaná v elektronické formě se nazývá elektronická kniha (e-kniha) nebo e-book.Knihovní a informační věda definuje knihu jako monografii pro její rozlišení od periodických publikací jako jsou časopisy nebo noviny.Osoba se zaujetím pro knihy je označována jako bibliofil nebo knihomil. Člověk s chorobnou touhou psát knihy je označován jako grafoman, s nutkáním vydat vlastní knihu typoman.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ar">الكتب هي أوعية المعلومات غير الدورية والتي بطبيعة محتوياتها وتنظيمها وضعت لتُقرأ من أولها لآخرها في تتابع منطقيولكل منها عنوان محدد حتى ولو صدرت مجمعة تحت سلسلة ما. ومن أنواعها الكتب المرجعية: وهي أوعية المعلومات التي بطبيعة محتوياتها وتنظيمها لم توضع لتُقرأ من أولها إلى آخرها وإنما يرجع إليها عند الحاجة لاستقاء معلومات معينة، كالقواميس ودوائر المعارف والأدلة والببليوجرافيات وغيرها، ولا يسمح عادة بإعارة هذا النوع من الأوعية خارج المكتبات. و الكتاب شرعا (أي المفهوم الاصطلاحي في الدين الإسلامي) هو كلام الله يوحي به إلى رسول من رسله ليبلغه إلى الناس ليصلوا به إلى سعادتهم في الدنيا والاخرة.و الكتاب أيضا هو عبارة عن مجموعة من أوراق مطبوعة من الورق يغطى بين غلافين. ويمكن للكتاب أيضا أن يكون النص في أكبر مجموعة من النصوص. هذا النص لديه بعض الميزات التي لا تنطبق على مجموعة ككل. وبهذه الطريقة ربما هو مكتوب في كتاب من قبل مؤلف واحد، أو ان تتعامل مع عدة مؤلقين على موضوغ واحد. وكثيرا ما كتب في هذا المعنى يمكن فهمها دون معرفة المجموعة بأكملها. كتب مجلدة ويغطي الثابت من الورق المقوى مغطاة بقماش أو جلد ومخيط عادة معا. وتغطي الكتب غلاف ورقي من ورقة قوية وعادة ما يتم لصقها معا. ويمكن قراءة الكلمات بصوت عال، أو في الكتب المسجلة على أشرطة (الكاسيت) والأقراص المدمجة.يمكن استعارة الكتب من مكتبة أو تم شراؤها من محل لبيع الكتب. يمكن أن يجعل الناس كتب خاصة بهم ملئها الصور العائلية، والرسوم، أو الكتابة الخاصة بهم. بعض الكتب الخاصة مثل مذكرات، دفتر العناوين، أو ألبوم الصور الفوتوغرافية.في معظم الوقت، فإن كلمة "كتاب" تعني أن تكون داخل صفحات كلمات مطبوعة أو المكتوبة عليها.تتم كتابة بعض الكتب للأطفال فقط، أو للترفيه، في حين أن الكتب الأخرى للدراسة في المدرسة شيئا مثل الرياضيات أو التاريخ. وتحتوي الكتب على الصور الفوتوغرافية أو الرسوم.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="cy">Fel arfer, mae llyfr yn golygu testun wedi ei sgrifennu neu ei argraffu ar bapur sydd wedi ei rwymo mewn clawr. Ers rhai blynyddoedd mae e-lyfrau ar gael, sef llyfrau ar ffurf meddalwedd y gellir eu darllen gan beiriant arbennig.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ja">本（ほん、英: book）は書物の一種であり、書籍・雑誌などの印刷・製本された出版物である。狭義では、複数枚の紙が一方の端を綴じられた状態になっているもの。この状態で紙の片面をページという。本を読む場合はページをめくる事によって次々と情報を得る事が出来る。つまり、狭義の本には巻物は含まれない。端から順を追ってしかみられない巻物を伸ばして蛇腹に折り、任意のページを開ける体裁としたものを折り本といい、折本の背面（文字の書かれていない側）で綴じたものが狭義の「本」といえる。本文が縦書きなら右綴じ、本文が横書きなら左綴じにする。また、1964年のユネスコ総会で採択された国際的基準は、「"本"とは、表紙はページ数に入れず、本文が少なくとも49ページ以上から成る、印刷された非定期刊行物」と、定義している。5ページ以上49ページ未満は小冊子として分類している。</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="az">Kitab — üzərinə müxtəlif yollarla köçürülmüş mətn və ya rəsm şəklində informasiya daşıyıcılarından ibarət vərəqə toplusu. Bu vərəqələr bir tərəfdən tikilir və üzlüklə örtülür. Kitab kağızının hər vərəqinin üzləri səhifə adlanır. Bəzən böyük sənədin və ədəbi əsərin bir hissəsinə də kitab deyilir. Elektron formasında yazılmış kitab elektron kitabdır.Bu məqalənin azərbaycan dili əlifbasının ərəb qrafikası ilə qarşılığı vardır. Bax: کیتاب&lt;span id="interwiki-la-fa" /></skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="pl">Książka – dokument piśmienniczy, zapis myśli ludzkiej, raczej obszerny, w postaci publikacji wielostronicowej o określonej liczbie stron, o charakterze trwałym.Dzisiejsza postać książki wywodzi się od kodeksu, czyli kartek połączonych grzbietem, które wraz z upowszechnieniem pergaminu zastąpiły poprzednią formę dokumentu piśmienniczego, czyli zwój.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="ro">O carte este o colecție de hârtii, pergamente sau alte astfel de materiale, în formă de coli sau foi de cele mai multe ori egale între ele și legate sau broșate într-un volum. Cărțile sunt de obicei tipărite (rareori scrise și de mână) și conțin diverse lucrări scrise, pe cea mai mare diversitate de teme. O carte este de asemenea o operă literară sau științifică, sau o parte semnificativă dintr-o astfel de operă.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="da">For alternative betydninger, se Bog (flertydig). (Se også artikler, som begynder med Bog)En bog er typisk en samling af flere end 48 papirsider[Kilde mangler] påtrykt én eller flere tekster og/eller billeder eller andet kognitivt stimulerende materiale. Siderne i bogen er beskyttet i et omslag (for- og bagside), og som helhed repræsenterer bogen en bestemt, traditionel måde at organisere indhold på. Mindre bøger, pjecer eller småtryk består af færre end 48 sider.Bøger opdeles i forskellige formater afhængigt af det antal gange arkene er foldet. A4 (kvart) er foldet fire gange osv. Af praktiske årsager er en bog med en højde på under 25 cm er en oktav, en højde på mellem 26 og 35 cm er en kvart, og bøger derover er folio'er. Når bogens bredde er større end højden, tales der om oblong eller tværoktav, -kvart og -folio.Inden for biblioteks- og informationsvidenskab kaldes en bog for en monografi til forskel fra periodiske publikationer som tidsskrifter, aviser, ugeblade mv.Før trykpressens opfindelse blev stort set alle bøger møjsommeligt kopieret ved håndkraft. Det gjorde en bog sjælden og meget værdifuld. I den tidlige middelalder var det kun kirken, universiteterne og rige, der havde midler til at eje bøger eller få dem fremstillet. De første bøger blev skrevet på ark af pergament af kalveskind. Senere blev de skrevet eller trykt på papir.En hel side kunne skæres ud i relief på en træplade, som kunne anvendes til at producere mange eksemplarer af denne ene side. At producere en hel bog på den måde var en meget omstændelig affære.Reliefteknikken er brugt til at fremstille verdens ældste trykte bog. Den er fundet i Kina og dateret til 868 e. kr., dvs. 587 år før Gutenbergs bibel. Ligeledes i Kina blev der omkring 1045 eksperimenteret med et trykkesystem af lertyper fastgjort med voks i smalle træskinner, men der er ikke bevaret nogen eksemplarer af bøger trykt med denne teknik.Gutenbergs bibel blev udgivet i 1455 i et oplag på ca. 200 og var den første maskinelt masseproducerede bog i verden. Det revolutionerende ved Gutenbergs teknik var, at den byggede på genanvendelige, løse blytyper.I Danmark var det den tyske bogtrykker Johan Snell, der indførte bogtrykkerkunsten, da han i 1482 åbnede sit trykkeri i Odense. Der gik 13 år, inden Gotfred af Ghemen trykte den første bog i Danmark og på dansk: Den danske Rimkrønike. Kirken havde ikke længere monopol på bogfremstilling.Bogtrykkerkunstens hurtige udbredelse førte store omvæltninger med sig. Mediet skulle finde sin form. Sidenummerering, som forekommer os så naturligt, dukkede først op omkring 1470. Folkebiblioteker skaffede alle adgang til bøger. Senere har bogklubber, billigbøger, It-hæfter mv. gjort det muligt for alle at eje en bog.Bogbindere og forfattere solgte de første bøger. Senere overtog boghandlere; de havde længe monopol på salget i Danmark. Et Internationalt Standard Bognummer (ISBN) anvendes til entydig identifikation af bogen på tværs af landegrænser.Udviklingen i informationsteknologien medfører eksperimenter med forskellige former for elektroniske bøger, og Peter Poulsens "Rulletekster" er den første danske E-bog (elektronisk bog).</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="he">ספר הוא טקסט מודפס או כתוב בכתב יד בנושא מסוים, שדפיו כרוכים יחדיו. בשלהי המאה העשרים החלה הפקתם של ספרים אלקטרוניים המוצגים על קורא ספרים אלקטרוני, טאבלטים, צג המחשב ואפילו טלפונים חכמים.עוד מימי בראשית אסף האדם את יצירותיו הספרותיות תחת ספרים. בתחילה היו אלה מגילות קלף, וספרים מצומצמים בהיקפם. עם התפתחות הדפוס באמצע המאה ה-15 עלה היקפם של הספרים. במשך מאות שנים היו הספרים אמצעי עיקרי להפצת ידע ולהעברתו מדור לדור. במאה העשרים נוספו לספרים המודפסים שלל אמצעים נוספים: רדיו, קולנוע, טלוויזיה והאינטרנט, אך לספר ממשיך להישמר מקום מרכזי. ספרי עלילה רבים מוצאים את דרכם אל מסך הקולנוע או הטלוויזיה.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="tr">Kitap, bir kenarından birleştirilerek dışına kapak takılmış yani ciltlenmiş, (kâğıt, parşömen vb. malzemeden üretilmiş) üzeri baskılı sayfaların toplamıdır.Bir "yapıta" ya da yapıtın bir bölümüne de kitap dendiği olur. Elektronik ortamda yayınlanan kitaplara ise e-kitap yani elektronik kitap denir. Kütüphanecilik 'te, dergi, bülten ya da gazete gibi süreli yayınlardan ayırt etmek için monograf olarak da adlandırılır.</skos:note><skos:note xml:lang="nl">Het boek is een van de meest gebruikte manieren om informatie vast te leggen in de vorm van schrift en afbeeldingen en om deze informatie weer te geven, op te slaan en te verspreiden.</skos:note><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://te.dbpedia.org/resource/పుస్తకము"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://it.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ga.dbpedia.org/resource/Leabhar"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hy.dbpedia.org/resource/Գիրք"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://jv.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q571"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sl.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hr.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lb.dbpedia.org/resource/Buch"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://oc.dbpedia.org/resource/Libre"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ta.dbpedia.org/resource/நூல்_அமைப்பு"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://az.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitab"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lt.dbpedia.org/resource/Knyga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sw.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitabu"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://si.dbpedia.org/resource/පොත"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://arz.dbpedia.org/resource/كتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bs.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pnb.dbpedia.org/resource/کتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ne.dbpedia.org/resource/पुस्तक"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tl.dbpedia.org/resource/Aklat"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eo.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tt.dbpedia.org/resource/Китап"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://yo.dbpedia.org/resource/Ìwé"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://af.dbpedia.org/resource/Boek"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sq.dbpedia.org/resource/Libri"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ka.dbpedia.org/resource/წიგნი"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nl.dbpedia.org/resource/Boek_(document)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://id.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://th.dbpedia.org/resource/หนังสือ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mr.dbpedia.org/resource/पुस्तक"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sco.dbpedia.org/resource/Beuk"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mk.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cs.dbpedia.org/resource/Kniha"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sk.dbpedia.org/resource/Kniha"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ia.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://gl.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sah.dbpedia.org/resource/Кинигэ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ca.dbpedia.org/resource/Llibre"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://simple.dbpedia.org/resource/Book"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nds.dbpedia.org/resource/Book"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://vi.dbpedia.org/resource/Sách"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://als.dbpedia.org/resource/Buch"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ba.dbpedia.org/resource/Китап"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://qu.dbpedia.org/resource/Liwru"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ast.dbpedia.org/resource/Llibru"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ml.dbpedia.org/resource/പുസ്തകം"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mn.dbpedia.org/resource/Ном"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://new.dbpedia.org/resource/सफू"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://gd.dbpedia.org/resource/Leabhar"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uk.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ko.dbpedia.org/resource/책"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://no.dbpedia.org/resource/Bok"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ja.dbpedia.org/resource/本"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pa.dbpedia.org/resource/ਕਿਤਾਬ"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pt.dbpedia.org/resource/Livro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ur.dbpedia.org/resource/کتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ms.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://la.dbpedia.org/resource/Liber"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://mg.dbpedia.org/resource/Boky"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://wikidata.dbpedia.org/resource/Q571"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://io.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hi.dbpedia.org/resource/पुस्तक"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://is.dbpedia.org/resource/Bók"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://war.dbpedia.org/resource/Basahon"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://eu.dbpedia.org/resource/Liburu"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://be.dbpedia.org/resource/Кніга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://zh.dbpedia.org/resource/图书"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sv.dbpedia.org/resource/Bok"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ckb.dbpedia.org/resource/کتێب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ku.dbpedia.org/resource/Pirtûk"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://kk.dbpedia.org/resource/Кітап"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bg.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://my.dbpedia.org/resource/စာအုပ်"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ar.dbpedia.org/resource/كتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tr.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitap"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cv.dbpedia.org/resource/Кĕнеке"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://da.dbpedia.org/resource/Bog"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nap.dbpedia.org/resource/Libbro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lmo.dbpedia.org/resource/Liber"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://de.dbpedia.org/resource/Buch"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://yi.dbpedia.org/resource/בוך"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://nn.dbpedia.org/resource/Bok"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://bn.dbpedia.org/resource/বই"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://he.dbpedia.org/resource/ספר"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fi.dbpedia.org/resource/Kirja"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://et.dbpedia.org/resource/Raamat"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://el.dbpedia.org/resource/Βιβλίο"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ru.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sr.dbpedia.org/resource/Књига"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://br.dbpedia.org/resource/Levr"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ce.dbpedia.org/resource/Книга"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://tg.dbpedia.org/resource/Китоб"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://cy.dbpedia.org/resource/Llyfr"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fr.dbpedia.org/resource/Livre_(document)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://pl.dbpedia.org/resource/Książka"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://hu.dbpedia.org/resource/Könyv"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://scn.dbpedia.org/resource/Libbru"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://rdf.freebase.com/ns/m.0bt_c3"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://lv.dbpedia.org/resource/Grāmata"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ht.dbpedia.org/resource/Liv_(pou_li)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://uz.dbpedia.org/resource/Kitob"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://sh.dbpedia.org/resource/Knjiga"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://wa.dbpedia.org/resource/Live_(po_lére)"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://su.dbpedia.org/resource/Buku"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://es.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://an.dbpedia.org/resource/Libro"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://fa.dbpedia.org/resource/کتاب"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://ro.dbpedia.org/resource/Carte"/><skos:exactMatch rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Book"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Books"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Documents"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Media_formats"/><skos:related rdf:resource="http://dbpedia.org/resource/Category:Paper_products"/></skos:Concept><ore:Aggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_182336"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336"/><edm:dataProvider>Royal College of Physicians, London</edm:dataProvider><edm:hasView rdf:resource="http://www.archive.org/download/b22651901/b22651901.pdf"/><edm:isShownAt rdf:resource="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/182336"/><edm:isShownBy rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/b22651901$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:object rdf:resource="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/b22651901$1/full/full/0/default.jpg"/><edm:provider>Biodiversity Heritage Library</edm:provider><edm:rights rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/"/><edm:intermediateProvider>Internet Archive</edm:intermediateProvider></ore:Aggregation><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/provider/08711/item_182336"><dc:contributor>Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904</dc:contributor><dc:contributor>Royal College of Physicians of London.</dc:contributor><dc:coverage xml:lang="en">Chicago, Illinois :</dc:coverage><dc:creator>Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904</dc:creator><dc:format xml:lang="en">Print</dc:format><dc:identifier>10.5962/bhl.title.102216</dc:identifier><dc:publisher>Chicago, Illinois : Lakeside Press, 1893.</dc:publisher><dc:language>en</dc:language><dc:relation xml:lang="en">Medical Heritage Library.</dc:relation><dc:rights>Not provided. Contact Contributing Library to verify copyright status.</dc:rights><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Animals</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Electronic books</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Locomotion</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Movement</dc:subject><dc:subject xml:lang="en">Photography</dc:subject><dc:title>Descriptive zoopraxography.</dc:title><dc:title>Science of animal locomotion made popular.</dc:title><dc:title>Zoopraxography or the science of animal locomotion.</dc:title><dc:title xml:lang="en">Descriptive zoopraxography; or, the science of animal locomotion made popular : with selected outline tracings reduced from some of the illustrations of "Animal Locomotion" an electro-photographic investigation of consecutive phases of animal movements, commenced 1872, completed 1855, and published, 1887, under the auspices of the University of Pennsylvania. Published as a memento of a series of lectures given by the author under the auspices of the United States Government Bureau of Education at the World's Columbian Exposition, in Zoopraxographical Hall 1893 /</dc:title><dc:type xml:lang="en">Text</dc:type><dc:type xml:lang="en">Book</dc:type><dcterms:isPartOf rdf:resource="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/bibliography/102216"></dcterms:isPartOf><dcterms:issued>1893</dcterms:issued><edm:europeanaProxy>false</edm:europeanaProxy><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_182336"/><edm:type>TEXT</edm:type></ore:Proxy><ore:Proxy rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/proxy/europeana/08711/item_182336"><dc:creator rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/agent/base/60590"></dc:creator><dc:date rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/18xx_2_half"></dc:date><dc:type rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/concept/base/6"></dc:type><dcterms:issued rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/1893"></dcterms:issued><dcterms:temporal rdf:resource="http://semium.org/time/18xx"></dcterms:temporal><edm:europeanaProxy>true</edm:europeanaProxy><edm:year>1893</edm:year><ore:proxyFor rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336"/><ore:proxyIn rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/08711/item_182336"/><edm:type>TEXT</edm:type></ore:Proxy><edm:EuropeanaAggregation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/europeana/08711/item_182336"><edm:aggregatedCHO rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336"/><edm:datasetName>08711_Ag_EU_BHL_usa</edm:datasetName><edm:country>United States of America</edm:country><edm:preview rdf:resource="https://api.europeana.eu/thumbnail/v2/url.json?uri=http%3A%2F%2Fiiif.archivelab.org%2Fiiif%2Fb22651901%241%2Ffull%2Ffull%2F0%2Fdefault.jpg&amp;type=TEXT"/><edm:landingPage rdf:resource="https://www.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336"/><edm:language>en</edm:language><edm:completeness>5</edm:completeness><dcterms:created>2017-08-02T22:13:28.619Z</dcterms:created><dcterms:modified>2017-08-03T00:01:11.870Z</dcterms:modified><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336#contentTier"/><dqv:hasQualityAnnotation rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336#metadataTier"/></edm:EuropeanaAggregation><svcs:Service rdf:about="http://iiif.archivelab.org/iiif/b22651901"><dcterms:conformsTo rdf:resource="http://iiif.io/api/image"></dcterms:conformsTo></svcs:Service><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336#contentTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-16T19:42:05.970Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_182336"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/contentTier4"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation><dqv:QualityAnnotation rdf:about="http://data.europeana.eu/item/08711/item_182336#metadataTier"><dcterms:created>2019-07-16T19:42:05.970Z</dcterms:created><oa:hasTarget rdf:resource="http://data.europeana.eu/aggregation/provider/08711/item_182336"/><oa:hasBody rdf:resource="http://www.europeana.eu/schemas/epf/metadataTierA"/></dqv:QualityAnnotation></rdf:RDF>